<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="apparatus-fontium">
            <head>Apparatus Fontium</head>

            <p>An apparatus fontium collects references to texts quoted or cited by the author(s) in
               the text of the edition. This section demonstrates how to encode such references so
               that they will be displayed appropriately in the text and so that bibliographical
               information about them will appear in the edition.</p>

            <p>The basic form of the encoding for an entry in the apparatus fontium has much in
               common with the encoding for entries in the apparatus criticus, so reading the <ref
                  target="#apparatus-criticus">section on the apparatus criticus</ref> is
               recommended.</p>

            <p>
               <specList>
                  <specDesc key="app"/>
                  <specDesc key="lem"/>
                  <specDesc key="rdg"/>
                  <specDesc key="cit"/>
                  <specDesc key="quote"/>
                  <specDesc key="ref"/>
                  <specDesc key="bibl"/>
                  <specDesc key="note"/>
               </specList>
            </p>

            <list>
               <item><gi>app</gi> (apparatus entry) with contains information about a quotation or a
                  reference made by the author of a text.</item>
               <item><gi>lem</gi> (lemma) contains the lemma, or base text, of the citation.</item>
               <item><gi>rdg</gi> (reading) contains a variant form of the citation, if one exists
                  in another witness or source (see more on witnesses and sources in the section
                     "<ref target="#apparatus-criticus-concepts-definitions">Apparatus Criticus:
                     Concepts and Definitions</ref>").</item>
               <item><gi>cit</gi> (cited quotation) contains a quotation (in <gi>quote</gi>) from
                  another source or a reference (in <gi>ref</gi>) to another source, together with
                  bibliographical information about the source (in <gi>bibl</gi>).</item>
               <item><gi>quote</gi> (quotation) contains a phrase or passage attributable to some
                  agency external to the text.</item>
               <item><gi>bibl</gi> (bibliographic citation) contains the bibliographical information
                  supplied by the author.</item>
               <item><gi>note</gi> (note), with <att>type</att>="fontium" and <att>target</att>
                  pointing to the <att>xml:id</att> of the <gi>lem</gi>, contains a standardized
                  form of reference (using <gi>bibl</gi>) provided by the editor. <hi rend="italic"
                     >This is the information that will appear in the apparatus fontium</hi>.</item>
            </list>

            <p>Any text in <gi>quote</gi> will be displayed or printed in quotation marks on the
               same line as the rest of the text. Any text in <gi>quote</gi> with
               <att>rend</att>="blockquote" will be or printed on a new line and indented. In the
               latter case, prose and verse text within <gi>quote</gi> should be encoded according
               to the guidelines in the sections "<ref target="#edition-text-prose">Prose</ref>" and
                  "<ref target="#edition-text-verse">Verse</ref>.”</p>

            <p>As for the source of the quotation, the two types of encoding for entries in the
               apparatus fontium depend on whether or not the author has identified the source of
               the quotation in the text.</p>

            <div xml:id="apparatus-fontium-author-attribution">
               <head>Source Identified by the Author</head>

               <p>When the author identifies a source in the text, <gi>bibl</gi> should be used to
                  the extent that the author has provided bibliographical information. A
                  standardized form of the bibliographical information should be inserted in a
                     <gi>note</gi>.</p>

               <p>In the following example, Duns Scotus has referred to a work by Boethius, but he
                  has not quoted it: <foreign xml:lang="lat">Probatio minoris per Boethium De
                     Trinitate: dicit quod septem praedicamenta non dicunt absolutas res, sed tantum
                     respectus</foreign>. That should be encoded as follows:</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <p>Probatio minoris per <app>
                        <lem xml:id="lem-12-boethius">
                           <cit>
                              <bibl>
                                 <author>Boethium</author>
                                 <title>De Trinitate</title>
                              </bibl>
                           </cit>
                        </lem>
                        <note type="fontium" target="#lem-12-boethius">
                           <bibl>
                              <author>Boethius</author>
                              <title>De Trin.</title>
                              <biblScope unit="part">c. 4</biblScope> (ed. R. Peiper 159; PL 64,
                              1353C)</bibl>
                        </note>
                     </app>: dicit quod septem praedicamenta non dicunt absolutas res, sed tantum
                     respectus.</p>
               </egXML>

               <p>In the edition text, the text would be displayed or printed without interruption:
                  Probatio minoris per Boethium <hi rend="italic">De Trinitate</hi>: dicit quod
                  septem praedicamenta non dicunt absolutas res, sed tantum respectus. The apparatus
                  fontium would include the following entry: Boethius <hi rend="italic">De
                     Trin.</hi> c. 4 (ed. R. Peiper 159; PL 64, 1353C). If variant readings exist
                  for the citation, they will appear in the apparatus criticus.</p>

               <p>If it is desirable to provide the text of the reference in the apparatus fontium,
                  it may be inserted in <gi>quote</gi> after <gi>bibl</gi> inside of the
                     <gi>note</gi>:</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <p>Probatio minoris per <app>
                        <lem xml:id="lem-12-boethius">
                           <cit>
                              <bibl>
                                 <author>Boethium</author>
                                 <title>De Trinitate</title>
                              </bibl>
                           </cit>
                        </lem>
                        <note type="fontium" target="#lem-12-boethius">
                           <bibl>
                              <author>Boethius</author>
                              <title>De Trin.</title>
                              <biblScope unit="part">c. 4</biblScope> (ed. R. Peiper 159; PL 64,
                              1353C)</bibl>
                           <quote>Iamne patet quae sit differentia praedicationum? Quod aliae quidem
                              quasi rem monstrant, aliae vero quasi circumstantias rei; quodque illa
                              quae ita praedicantur, ut esse aliquid rem ostendant, illa vero ut non
                              esse, sed potius extrinsecus aliquid quodam modo adfigant?</quote>
                        </note>
                     </app>: dicit quod septem praedicamenta non dicunt absolutas res, sed tantum
                     respectus.</p>
               </egXML>

               <p>The text of the quotation will be displayed in the apparatus fontium after the
                  bibliographical information.</p>

               <p>The following example from <ref target="#kaster-macrobius">Robert Kaster's edition
                     of <bibl><author>Macrobius’</author>
                        <title>Saturnalia</title> (3.16.1–5)</bibl></ref> demonstrates a more
                  complex entry that features other aspects of quotation of sources, including
                  direct speech, block quotations of prose and verse texts and an inline quotation
                  of a prose text:</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <said who="#Rufius">
                     <p>Nec acipenser, quem maria prodigis nutriunt, illius saeculi delicias evasit;
                        et ut liqueat secundo Punico bello celebre nomen huius piscis fuisse,
                        accipite ut meminerit eius <app>
                           <lem xml:id="lem-3.16-plautus"><bibl><author>Plautus</author> in fabula
                                 quae inscribitur <title>Baccaria</title></bibl> ex persona parasiti<cit>
                                 <quote rend="blockquote"><!-- Verse quotation to be displayed/printed on new line and indented -->
                                    <l>quis est mortalis tanta fortuna adfectus umquam</l>
                                    <l>qua ego nunc sum, cuius haec ventri portatur pompa?</l>
                                    <l>vel nunc, qui mihi in mari acipenser latuit antehac,</l>
                                    <l>cuius ego latus in latebras reddam meis dentibus et
                                       manibus.</l>
                                 </quote>
                              </cit></lem>
                           <note type="fontium" target="#lem-3.16-plautus"><bibl>
                                 <author>Plautus</author>
                                 <title>Baccar.</title> 16–20</bibl></note></app>.</p>
                     <p>et ne vilior sit testis poeta, accipite assertore Cicerone in quo honore
                        fuerit hic piscis apud P. Scipionem Africanum illum et Numantinum, haec sunt
                        in dialogo <app><lem xml:id="lem-3.16-Cicero"><bibl>de fato verba
                                    <author>Ciceronis</author></bibl><cit>
                                 <quote rend="blockquote"><!-- Prose quotation to be displayed/printed on new line and indented -->
                                    <p>nam cum esset apud se ad Lavernium Scipio unaque Pontius
                                       adlatus est forte Scipioni acipenser, qui admodum raro
                                       capitur, sed est piscis, ut ferunt, in primis nobilis. cum
                                       autem Scipio unum et alterum ex his qui eum salutatum
                                       venerant invitavisset pluresque etiam invitaturus videretur,
                                       in aurem Pontius, <said who="#Pontius">Scipio,</said> inquit,
                                          <said who="#Pontius">vide quid agas, acipenser iste
                                          paucorum hominum est.</said></p>
                                 </quote>
                              </cit></lem><note type="fontium" target="#lem-3.16-Cicero"
                                    ><bibl><author>Cicero</author>
                                 <title>De Fato</title> fr. 4</bibl></note></app></p>
                     <p>nec infitias eo temporibus Traiani hunc piscem in magno pretio non fuisse,
                        teste <bibl><author>Plinio Secundo</author>, qui in <title>Naturali
                              historia</title></bibl> cum de hoc pisce loqueretur sic ait: <app><lem><cit><!-- Prose quotation to be displayed/printed in line -->
                                 <quote>nullo nunc in honore est, quod equidem miror, cum sit rarus
                                    inventu.</quote></cit></lem><note type="fontium"
                                    ><bibl><author>Plin.</author>
                                 <title>HN</title> 9.60</bibl>.</note></app></p>
                  </said>
               </egXML>
            </div>




            <div xml:id="apparatus-fontium-no-attribution">
               <head>Source Supplied by Editor</head>

               <p>If the author has not identified the source of a direct or indirect quotation, the
                  editor may supply it in the apparatus fontium.</p>
               
               <p>For example, Cicero often mentions the name of the authors he quotes, but editors must supply more detailed citation information, as in this passage from <bibl><title>Orator</title> 157</bibl>:</p>
               
               <p>Quid quod sic loqui: nosse, iudicasse vetant, novisse iubent et iudicavisse? Quasi
                  vero nesciamus in hoc genere et plenum verbum recte dici et imminutum usitate.
                  Itaque utrumque Terentius:<quote rend="blockquote">eho tu, cognatum tuom non noras?</quote></p>
               <p>post idem: <quote rend="blockquote">Stilponem, inquam, noveras.</quote></p>
               <p>Sient plenum est, sint imminutum; licet utare utroque.</p>
               
               <p>To be sure that the citation information appears in the apparatus fontium, this is how that passage should be encoded:</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <p>Quid quod sic loqui: nosse, iudicasse vetant, novisse iubent et iudicavisse? Quasi
                  vero nesciamus in hoc genere et plenum verbum recte dici et imminutum usitate.
                  Itaque utrumque <app><lem xml:id="lem-157-terence1"
                              ><bibl><author>Terentius</author></bibl>: <cit><quote
                              rend="blockquote">eho tu, cognatum tuom non
                        noras?</quote></cit></lem><note type="fontium" target="#lem-157-terence1"
                              ><bibl><author>Ter.</author>
                           <title>Ph.</title>
                           <biblScope unit="line">384</biblScope></bibl></note></app></p>
               <p>post idem <app><lem xml:id="lem-157-terence2"><cit><quote rend="blockquote"
                              >Stilponem, inquam, noveras.</quote></cit></lem><note type="fontium"
                        target="#lem-157-terence2"><bibl><author>Ter.</author>
                           <title>Ph.</title>
                           <biblScope unit="line">390</biblScope></bibl></note></app> Sient plenum
                  est, sint imminutum; licet utare utroque.</p>
               </egXML>
            </div>

         </div>
         <!-- End section on apparatus fontium -->
         <div xml:id="parallel-passages">
            <head>Parallel Passages</head>

            <p>A register of parallel passages differs from an <ref target="#apparatus-fontium"
                  >apparatus fontium</ref> in that it reflects the editor's judgment about passages
               that might be of interest to readers, whereas an apparatus fontium provides
               information on passages quoted or cited by the author(s). For this reason, entries in
               the apparatus fontium are encoded within the edition text, but parallel passages are
               encoded as notes, similar to the way that an editor's textual notes are handled (see
               the section "<ref target="#apparatus-criticus-editorial-notes">Editorial
               Notes</ref>").</p>

            <p>
               <specList>
                  <specDesc key="note"/>
                  <specDesc key="listBibl"/>
                  <specDesc key="bibl"/>
                  <specDesc key="author"/>
                  <specDesc key="title"/>
                  <specDesc key="biblScope"/>
                  <specDesc key="quote"/>
               </specList>
            </p>

            <list>
               <item><gi>note</gi> contains a list of parallel passages related to the text. Each
                     <gi>note</gi> must have an <att>xml:id</att> and <att>target</att> pointing to
                  the <att>xml:id</att> related to the section of text referred to by the
                     <gi>note</gi>. Each <gi>note</gi> must also have <att>type</att>="parallel" to
                  distinguish it from other uses of <gi>note</gi>.</item>
               <item><gi>listBibl</gi> (citation list) contains references to parallel
                  passages.</item>
               <item><gi>bibl</gi> (bibliographic citation) contains the following bibliographic
                  information pertaining to an individual parallel passage.</item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item><gi>author</gi> contains the name of the author (or a standard
                        abbreviation) of a parallel passage.</item>
                     <item><gi>title</gi> contains the title of the work (or a standard
                        abbreviation) in which the parallel passage occurs.</item>
                     <item><gi>biblScope</gi> (scope of bibliographic reference) contains the
                        specific unit where the parallel passage may be found (e.g., book number,
                        section number, paragraph number, line number, etc.).</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item><gi>quote</gi> contains the quoted text of the passage, if desirable.</item>
            </list>

            <p>For example, Gelsomino includes an extensive list of parallel passages to individual
               entries in his <ref target="#gelsomino-sequester">edition of Vibius Sequester</ref>.
               If that edition were encoded according to these guidelines, each paragraph in the
               edition text would have an <att>xml:id</att> and <att>corresp</att> pointing to the
                  <att>xml:id</att> of the note with the parallel passages:</p>

            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
               <p n="1" xml:id="f1-achelous" corresp="p-f1-achelous">Achelous, Aetoliae, primus
                  erupisse terram dicitur.</p>
               <note type="parallel" target="#f1-achelous" xml:id="p-f1-achelous">
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl><author>Verg.</author>
                        <title>G</title>
                        <biblScope>1.9</biblScope></bibl>: <quote>poculaque … Acheloia"</quote> (cf.
                           <bibl><author>Serv. Auct.</author> ad loc.</bibl>);
                           <bibl><author>Macr.</author>
                        <title>Satur.</title>
                        <biblScope>5.18.1–2</biblScope> praesertim 9</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </note>
               <p n="2" xml:id="f2-arar">Arar, <app>
                     <lem>Germaniae</lem>
                     <rdg wit="#Tschu. #Siml.">Galliae</rdg>
                  </app>, e <app>
                     <lem>Vogeso</lem>
                     <rdg wit="#Sal." source="#Rie.">Vosego</rdg>
                  </app> monte. miscetur Rhodano. ita lene decurrit, ut vix intellegi possit
                  decursus eius.</p>
               <note type="parallel" target="#f2-arar" xml:id="p-f2-arar">
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl><author>Verg.</author>
                        <title>E</title>
                        <biblScope>1.62</biblScope></bibl>: <quote>aut Ararim Parthus bibet aut
                        Germania Tigrim</quote>; (cf. <bibl><author>Serv.</author></bibl>:
                        <quote>Ararim Germaniae flumen … Arar fluvius Galliae fluens in
                        Rhodanum</quote>
                     <bibl><title>Schol. Bern.</title></bibl>: <quote>Arar flumen Germaniae, tamen
                        alii dicunt Galliae, in Rhodanum iens</quote>
                     <bibl><author>Phil.</author>
                        <biblScope>II</biblScope></bibl>: <quote>fluvius Germaniae vel
                        Galliae</quote>
                     <bibl><author>Ansil.</author>
                        <title>AR</title>
                        <biblScope>35, 35, 36</biblScope></bibl>: <quote>Fluvius Germaniae</quote>;
                     cf. <bibl><author>Caes.</author>
                        <title>BG</title>
                        <biblScope>1.12</biblScope></bibl></listBibl>
               </note>
            </egXML>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
