<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>XML Patterns for Representing Critical Edition Data</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Developed by</resp>
               <name>Samuel J. Huskey</name>
               <name>Hugh Cayless</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Working guidelines for the Digital Latin Library</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital, with references to the Epidoc Guidelines</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="LDLT-edition-structure">
            <head>Structure of an LDLT Edition</head>
            <p>This section describes the basic structure of the file that contains an edition for
               the Digital Latin Library's <bibl><title>Library of Digital Latin
                  Texts</title></bibl> (LDLT). The structure of an LDLT edition resembles the
               structure of a traditional printed critical edition:</p>
            <list>
               <head>Parts of an LDLT Edition</head>
               <item>Publication Details</item>
               <item>Front Matter</item>
               <item>Critical Text (including apparatus)</item>
               <item>Indices</item>
            </list>
            <p>Since every text is unique, not every LDLT edition will have all of these sections.
               The nature of the text and the editor's judgment will determine the contents of an
               edition. The purpose of this section is to define the parts of an LDLT edition and
               provide guidelines for representing them in XML.</p>
            <p>These guidelines are based on the standard set by the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI),
               with modification and customization to accommodate the special characteristics of
               Latin texts.</p>
            <div xml:id="general-structure">
               <p>The following is an example of the general overall structure of an XML file for an
                  LDLT edition:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <teiHeader>
                     <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                           <title>Bucolica</title>
                           <author>Calpurnius Siculus</author>
                           <editor>Jane Doe</editor>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                           <edition>First Edition</edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                           <publisher>Society for Classical Studies</publisher>
                           <distributor>Digital Latin Library</distributor>
                           <date>2016</date>
                           <availability>
                              <license target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"
                                 >Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                 License.</license>
                           </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <seriesStmt>
                           <title level="s">Library of Digital Latin Texts</title>
                           <biblScope unit="vol">1</biblScope>
                        </seriesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                           <p>Born digital.</p>
                        </sourceDesc>
                     </fileDesc>
                  </teiHeader>
                  <text>
                     <front xml:id="front">
                        <div xml:id="preface">
                           <head>Preface</head>
                           <p>General introductory remarks about the edition.</p>
                           <div xml:id="preface-section-1">
                              <!--This is a subsection within the preface. Editors should use
                              subsections to organize the content of the edition's preface.-->
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div xml:id="bibliography">
                           <head>Bibliography</head>
                           <!--This is where the bibliography for the edition is listed.-->
                           <div xml:id="bibliography-manuscripts">
                              <head>Manuscripts</head>
                              <!--Descriptions of manuscripts, using <gi>listWit</gi>.-->
                           </div>
                           <div xml:id="bibliography-early-editions">
                              <head>Early Editions</head>
                              <!--Bibliographical details for early editions or editiones vetustiores, using
                                 <gi>listBibl</gi> with <att>type</att>="editions-witnesses".-->
                           </div>
                           <div xml:id="bibliography-modern-editions">
                              <head>Modern Editions</head>
                              <!--Bibliographical details for modern editions and commentaries, using
                                 <gi>listBibl</gi> with <att>type</att>="editions-sources".-->
                           </div>
                           <div xml:id="bibliography-secondary-sources">
                              <head>Secondary Sources</head>
                              <!--Bibliographical details for articles, notes, books, and other sources,
                              using <gi>listBibl</gi> with <att>type</att>="secondary-sources".-->
                           </div>
                           <div xml:id="bibliography-scholars">
                              <head>List of Scholars Referred to By Name</head>
                              <!-- A list of the names of individual scholars referred to by name in the 
                                 apparatus, if they are not listed elsewhere in the bibliography (e.g., 
                                 as the editor of an edition or author of an article). -->
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div xml:id="conspectus">
                           <head>Conspectus</head>
                           <!--A key to the special sigla and abbreviations used in the edition (drawn
                           from the <att>xml:id</att>'s assigned to the various items in the
                           bibliography).-->
                        </div>
                     </front>
                     <body>
                        <div type="edition" xml:id="edition-text" xml:space="preserve">
                        <div type="textpart" n="1" xml:id="part1">
                           <head>Title of First Part</head>
                           <!--Text goes here, according to the conventions laid out elsewhere in these guidelines.-->
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" n="2" xml:id="part2">
                           <head>Title of Second Part</head>
                           <!--Each new major section (e.g., book, volume) goes in a new <gi>div</gi>.-->
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     </body>
                     <back>
                        <!--The content of the back matter will be determined in consultation between
                        the editor and the staff of the DLL. Because LDLT editions are encoded, the
                        matter traditionally found in the back of a printed critical edition may be
                        generated by applications instead of having to be entered manually.
                        Nevertheless, there is space here for notes, indices, and other kinds of
                        information.-->
                     </back>
                  </text>
               </egXML>
            </div>

            <!-- Publication details -->

            <div xml:id="publication-details">
               <head>Publication Details</head>
               <p>A traditional critical edition in print has a title page announcing the title of
                  the work, its author, the editor(s), and details of publication. In an LDLT
                  edition, these details are presented as structured data within a TEI header
                     (<gi>teiHeader</gi>). For example:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <teiHeader>
                     <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                           <title>Bucolica</title>
                           <author>Calpurnius Siculus</author>
                           <editor>Jane Doe</editor>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                           <edition>First Edition</edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                           <publisher>Society for Classical Studies</publisher>
                           <distributor>Digital Latin Library</distributor>
                           <date>2016</date>
                           <availability>
                              <license target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"
                                 >Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                 License.</license>
                           </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <seriesStmt>
                           <title level="s">Library of Digital Latin Texts</title>
                           <biblScope unit="vol">1</biblScope>
                        </seriesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                           <p>Born digital.</p>
                        </sourceDesc>
                     </fileDesc>
                  </teiHeader>
               </egXML>
               <p>Since a critical edition is often based upon many sources (e.g., manuscripts,
                  previous editions, commentaries, etc.), the <gi>teiHeader</gi> for an LDLT edition
                  does not hew strictly to the TEI guidelines for <gi>sourceDesc</gi>. The sources
                  for an LDLT edition are documented and described in the edition's front
                  matter.</p>
               <p>Just as an editor is not expected to create the title page and document the
                  publication information, this section of an LDLT is the responsibility of the DLL
                  staff.</p>
            </div>

            <!-- Front matter -->

            <div xml:id="front-matter">
               <head>Front Matter</head>
               <p>The <gi>front</gi> contains divisions and subdivisions (using <gi>div</gi>)
                  corresponding to the preface, bibliography, and conspectus for the edition.</p>
               <p>The <hi rend="bold">preface</hi> lays out (in prose, using <gi>p</gi>) the
                  argument for the edition. It also describes the textual tradition and the major
                  sources for it, which is why it is recommended to compile the bibliography first,
                  to take advantage of the ability to link to individual entries in the
                  bibliography, so that users will be able to have the information available as they
                  read.</p>
               <p>The elements available in all TEI documents are available for use in the preface.
                  For example, an editor might want to make a table comparing the readings of
                  manuscript families. In that case, the editor would use <gi>table</gi> and its
                  related elements (see the TEI guidelines for <ref
                     target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-table.html"
                        ><gi>table</gi></ref> for more information).</p>
            </div>

            <!-- Bibliography -->

            <div xml:id="bibliography">
               <head>Bibliography</head>
               <!-- Issue: Should a consensus siglum be an xml:id on a <listBibl> containing the items, or a separate siglum listed elsewhere? -->
               <p>The bibliography presents opportunities for leveraging the digital nature of an
                  LDLT edition. For this reason, every item in the bibliography is encoded as
                  structured data (contained in <gi>msDesc</gi> or <gi>biblStruct</gi>), so that the
                  bibliography itself can become a useful tool for finding and using resources,
                  especially those that are available online.</p>
               <p>The bibliography is all the more useful as a tool if it is created and made
                  available via <ref target="http://www.zotero.org">Zotero</ref>, an open, online
                  resource for building and managing bibliographies. In addition to providing an
                  interface for compiling and managing a bibliography, Zotero can also export
                  bibliographies in a TEI XML format that requires little to no modification for
                  inclusion in an LDLT edition. Users can copy and paste Zotero information directly
                  into an LDLT edition file. It is highly recommended that all LDLT editions have a
                  corresponding Zotero repository for their bibliography.</p>
               <p>Unfortunately, Zotero does not currently provide a format for describing and
                  cataloging manuscripts, so that information must be entered manually. For that
                  reason, and for the sake of completeness, the following sections provide
                  information for encoding items in the bibliography, with examples.</p>

               <!-- Bibliography: structure -->

               <div xml:id="bibliography-structure">
                  <head>Structure of the Bibliography</head>
                  <p>The bibliography should be organized according to the following structure:</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>Structure of the Bibliography for an LDLT Edition</head>
                     <item>Manuscripts (<att>xml:id</att>="bibliography-manuscripts")</item>
                     <item>Editions<list>
                           <item>Early Editions
                              (<att>xml:id</att>="bibliography-editions-witnesses"</item>
                           <item>Modern Editions
                              (<att>xml:id</att>="bibliography-editions-sources")</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Secondary Sources
                        (<att>xml:id</att>="bibliography-secondary-sources")</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Additionally, there should be a list of the names of individual scholars
                        (<att>xml:id</att>="bibliography-scholars") referred to by name in the
                     apparatus, if they are not listed elsewhere in the bibliography (e.g., as the
                     editor of an edition or author of an article). It is common, for example, to
                     refer to a scholar whose unpublished notes appear in a commentary or who has
                     corresponded with the editor. For ease of reference, these sources should be
                     listed with information about where the information can be verified.</p>
               </div>

               <!-- Bibliography: sigla -->

               <div xml:id="bibliography-sigla">
                  <head>Human- and Machine-Readable Sigla, Symbols, and Abbreviations</head>
                  <p>Printed editions have long used a system of references for manuscripts and
                     other materials in the bibliography. For example, single letters, or <emph
                        rend="italic">sigla</emph>, stand for manuscripts, and the last names of
                     scholars stand for editions, commentaries, or other works of scholarship.
                     Centuries of use have demontrated that this system of sigla and other symbols
                     and abbreviations is an efficient, effective, and economical way of presenting
                     the complex information contained in critical editions. Although its
                     development was motivated by the constraints of the printed page, its virtues
                     for representing data commend it for other media, too. But just as the printed
                     page has limits, so too does the digital file, so the traditional system
                     requires an update to make it available in a digital context.</p>
                  <p>Given some guidance and experience, people can learn how to navigate the system
                     of letters, numbers, symbols, and other typographical conventions for referring
                     to the sources of a crticial edition. If one edition uses superscript numerals
                     to indicate the hands that wrote in a manuscript, but another uses superscript
                     numerals to signify the number of a manuscript in a collection, a human reader
                     can adjust to the difference in meaning without much effort. In contrast,
                     machines need clear instructions and a reliable set of rules for reading a
                     digital file. A human might see <hi rend="bold">N²</hi> and correctly interpret
                     it within a particular edition as meaning "text written by the second person in
                     a succession of people who wrote in the manuscript known as codex Neapolitanus
                     V A 8." Without explicit instructions, a machine will interpret the same
                     information as simply the letter "N" with a superscript numeral 2 next to it.
                     Indeed, a less experienced human reader might reach the same conclusion as the
                     machine.</p>
                  <p>Since the audience for LDLT editions includes an entirely new class of reader
                     (i.e., machines), it stands to reason that the reference system should be
                     adapted to accommodate the needs of the expanded readership. For this reason,
                     LDLT editions encode sigla and other aspects of the traditional reference
                     system in two ways: a machine-readable version (using <att>xml:id</att>) and a
                     human-readable version (using <gi>label</gi>, with special instructions for
                     rendering typographical conventions such as superscript and subscript
                     notation). In some cases, the values for both will be the same, but the <ref
                        target="https://www.w3.org/TR/xml-id/">strict rules of the XML specification
                        for <att>xml:id</att></ref> do not allow for the traditional system of
                     combining letters with superscript and/or subscript numerals. Nevertheless, the
                     values of <att>xml:id</att> and <gi>label</gi> should be similar, if not
                     identical, to each other, and they should be meaningful. Editors should follow
                     the conventions in previous editions of the same text, changing a siglum only
                     if it is important to the edition's argument to do so. If the text has never
                     been edited, the editor should choose sigla according to the principles
                     outlined by <ref target="#West">West</ref> (74–75). In brief, use sigla that
                     have mnemonic value (e.g., "V" for "Vaticanus" or "P" for "Parisinus").</p>
                  <p>Because the needs of editors will vary from edition to edition, the LDLT does
                     not have strict rules for representing manuscript hands or similar information.
                     Rather, we offer these suggestions:</p>
                  <table>
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell role="data">Information</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Example Value of <att>xml:id</att></cell>
                        <cell role="data">Example Value of <gi>label</gi></cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">A single manuscript</cell>
                        <cell role="data">"V"</cell>
                        <cell role="data">V</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Manuscript Hands</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Vh1, Vh2</cell>
                        <cell role="data">V<hi rend="super">1</hi>, V<hi rend="super">2</hi></cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Multiple manuscripts from one collection</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Vms1, Vms2</cell>
                        <cell role="data">V<hi rend="sub">1</hi>, V<hi rend="sub">2</hi></cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">One of many indistinguishable hands</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Vrec</cell>
                        <cell role="data">V<hi rend="super">rec</hi></cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Fragments of ancient copies</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Π1, Π2</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Π<hi rend="super">1</hi>, Π<hi rend="super">1</hi></cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Consensus of manuscripts</cell>
                        <cell role="data">ω</cell>
                        <cell role="data">ω</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">One or more late manuscripts</cell>
                        <cell role="data">ς</cell>
                        <cell role="data">ς</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Scholia</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Σ</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Σ</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Scholia in a certain manuscript</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Σa, Σb</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Σ<hi rend="super">a</hi>, Σ<hi rend="super">b</hi></cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Multiple editions</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Schenkl1, Schenkl2</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Schenkl<hi rend="super">1</hi>, Schenkl<hi rend="super"
                              >2</hi></cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data">Multiple books or articles by the same scholar</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Burm1731, Burm1759</cell>
                        <cell role="data">Burm. 1731, Burm. 1759</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <p>In short, <hi rend="bold">every entry, regardless of type, in the bibliography
                        of an LDLT edition must have values for both <att>xml:id</att> and
                           <gi>label</gi>.</hi> Otherwise, the edition will not be able to make full
                     use of the digital format. Morever, if an entry lacks a <gi>label</gi>, it will
                     not be available for a print version of the edition, should one be
                     produced.</p>
               </div>

               <!-- Bibliography: MS Description -->

               <div xml:id="bibliography-ms-description">
                  <head>Manuscripts</head>
                  <p>The description of manuscripts is a discipline unto itself, with
                     long-established conventions for capturing all of the details about not only a
                     manuscript's contents, but also its dimensions, provenance, material, and other
                     physical details. It is customary for critical editions to provide a brief
                     prose description of the major manuscripts used for establishing the text,
                     usually only enough to identify where the manuscript may be found for
                     consultation, but sometimes including information about its provenance and
                     other details relevant to the edition (e.g., manuscript hands).</p>
                  <p>The prose format for describing manuscripts is a predictable and efficient way
                     of conveying this information to human readers, but it is not useful for making
                     the information available to machines for processing. That is why the TEI
                     guidelines have an entire module for making manuscript descriptions available
                     as structured data for machine-readability (<ref
                        target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html">10
                        Manuscript Description</ref>). But just as editors often eschew the finer
                     points of manuscript description in prose, so too is it acceptable to omit many
                     of the elements of the TEI's module.</p>
                  <p>LDLT editions must include both structured data and prose descriptions of
                     manuscripts referred to in the apparatus criticus or elsewhere. It is possible
                     to combine the two types of description. Guidelines for structured data, prose,
                     and a combination of the two appear below. Above all, the point is to make the
                     information available to both human and machine readers, so it is up to
                     individual editors to decide which method is most appropriate.</p>
                  <p>Whatever the method, editors should use their best judgment regarding the
                     amount of information that will be relevant to those seeking to understand the
                     place of a manuscript in the tradition. The following guidelines present the
                     minimum requirements for both prose and structured data descriptions of
                     manuscripts used in LDLT editions.</p>

                  <!-- Bibliography: MS Description: TEI -->

                  <div xml:id="bibliography-ms-description-TEI">
                     <head>Structured Data</head>
                     <p>The TEI's <ref
                           target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html"
                           >module for manuscript description</ref> offers a model for presenting
                        nearly every imaginable detail about a manuscript as structured data.
                        Editors may wish to use more of the features of the module than are
                        described here, but the following are essential for making use of the
                        functionality of the LDLT viewer.</p>
                     <p>
                        <specList>
                           <specDesc key="listWit"/>
                           <specDesc key="witness"/>
                           <specDesc key="msDesc"/>
                           <specDesc key="msIdentifier"/>
                           <specDesc key="settlement"/>
                           <specDesc key="institution"/>
                           <specDesc key="repository"/>
                           <specDesc key="idno"/>
                           <specDesc key="altIdentifier"/>
                           <specDesc key="physDesc"/>
                           <specDesc key="objectDesc"/>
                           <specDesc key="supportDesc"/>
                           <specDesc key="handDesc"/>
                           <specDesc key="handNote"/>
                           <specDesc key="history"/>
                           <specDesc key="origin"/>
                        </specList>
                     </p>
                     <p><gi>listWit</gi> (list of witnesses) contains the descriptions of manuscript
                        witnesses for the edition. Separate <gi>listWit</gi> elements may be used to
                        distinguish families of manuscripts. If it is desirable to use a siglum to
                        refer to the consensus of manuscripts in that family, <gi>listWit</gi> must
                        have <att>xml:id</att> and <gi>label</gi> with values corresponding to that
                        siglum.</p>
                     <p><gi>witness</gi> (witness) groups the information about a single manuscript,
                        including the name used to refer to the manuscript in the edition (e.g.,
                        Codex Neapolitanus V A 8). Its <att>xml:id</att> is the unique
                        machine-readable identifier to be used when referring to the manuscript's
                        data (e.g., in the <att>wit</att> of a <gi>rdg</gi> in the apparatus
                        criticus).</p>
                     <p><gi>label</gi> contains the human-readable siglum that should be displayed
                        on screen or printed.</p>
                     <p><gi>msDesc</gi> (manuscript description) groups the elements that compose
                        the description of the manuscript:</p>
                     <list>
                        <head>Required Elements in <gi>msDesc</gi></head>
                        <item><gi>msIdentifier</gi> (manuscript identifier) groups information about
                           the location and inventory number of the manuscript.</item>
                        <item><gi>settlement</gi> contains the common English name of the place
                           (e.g., Florence, not Firenze) where the manuscript is located.</item>
                        <item><gi>institution</gi> contains the name of the institution that houses
                           the manuscript. Use the original name of the institution (e.g.,
                           Biblioteca Ambrosiana), not an English translation.</item>
                        <item><gi>repository</gi> contains the name of the collection to which the
                           manuscript belongs. Use the original name or common abbreviation of the
                           repository (e.g., Acquisti e Doni or Acq. e Doni).</item>
                        <item><gi>idno</gi> (identifier) contains the catalog or inventory
                           information for the manuscript.</item>
                        <item><gi>altIdentifier</gi> (alternative identifier) contains other
                           information (i.e., in addition to the <gi>idno</gi>) used to identify the
                           manuscript.</item>
                        <item><gi>phsyDesc</gi> (physical description) groups information about the
                           manuscript.</item>
                        <item><gi>objectDesc</gi> (object description) contains <gi>supportDesc</gi>
                           (support description). It may have <att>form</att> to identify whether
                           the manuscript is a codex, a set of unbound leaves, or other form.</item>
                        <item><gi>supportDesc</gi> (support description) is an empty element that
                           identifies (in <att>material</att>) the material upon which the
                           manuscript's text is written (e.g., "parchment").</item>
                        <item><gi>handDesc</gi> (hand description) groups information about the
                           distinct hands that wrote in the manuscript. Use <att>hands</att> with
                           the value of the number of hands detectable in the manuscript.</item>
                        <item><gi>handNote</gi> contains information about a hand that wrote in the
                           manuscript. Each <gi>handNote</gi> has an <att>xml:id</att> with a unique
                           identifier (based on the <att>xml:id</att> of the manuscript) and a
                              <gi>label</gi> with a human-readable version of the value of the
                           hand's <att>xml:id</att> (<ref target="#bibliography-sigla">see above for
                              more on sigla</ref>).</item>
                        <item><gi>history</gi> groups information about the date of the
                           manuscript.</item>
                        <item><gi>origin</gi> encloses <gi>origDate</gi>, which contains the roman
                           numeral for the century in which the manuscript was written, or the
                           arabic numeral for the year, if known. If century is used, include
                              <att>notBefore</att> and <att>notAfter</att> with appropriate values.
                           If year is used, it should be enclosed by <gi>date</gi>.</item>
                     </list>
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <listWit>
                           <witness xml:id="N">Codex Neapolitanus V A 8 <label>N</label>
                              <msDesc>
                                 <msIdentifier>
                                    <settlement>Naples</settlement>
                                    <repository>Biblioteca Nazionale di Napoli</repository>
                                    <idno>V.A.8</idno>
                                    <altIdentifier>
                                       <idno>380</idno>
                                    </altIdentifier>
                                 </msIdentifier>
                                 <physDesc>
                                    <objectDesc form="codex">
                                       <supportDesc material="parch"/>
                                    </objectDesc>
                                    <handDesc hands="3">
                                       <handNote xml:id="N1"><label>N<hi rend="super"
                                          >1</hi></label>: corrections or attempted corrections made
                                          by the original copyist</handNote>
                                       <handNote xml:id="N2"><label>N<hi rend="super">2</hi>:
                                             corrections or attempted corrections made by a later
                                             hand not easily distinguishable from the
                                          first.</label></handNote>
                                       <handNote xml:id="N3"><label>N<hi rend="super"
                                          >3</hi></label>: corrections or attempted corrections made
                                          in a few places by a third hand</handNote>
                                    </handDesc>
                                 </physDesc>
                                 <history>
                                    <origin>
                                       <origDate notAfter="1500" notBefore="1400">XV</origDate>
                                    </origin>
                                 </history>
                              </msDesc>
                           </witness>
                           <witness xml:id="G">Codex Gaddianus pl. 90, 12 inf. <label>G</label>
                              <msDesc>
                                 <msIdentifier>
                                    <settlement>Florence</settlement>
                                    <repository>Biblioteca Medicea Laurenziana</repository>
                                    <idno>plut. 90, 12 inf.</idno>
                                 </msIdentifier>
                                 <physDesc>
                                    <objectDesc form="codex">
                                       <supportDesc material="paper"/>
                                    </objectDesc>
                                    <handDesc hands="2">
                                       <handNote xml:id="G1"><label>G<hi rend="super">1</hi>:
                                             corrections or attempted corrections made by the
                                             original copyist.</label></handNote>
                                       <handNote xml:id="G2"><label>G<hi rend="super">2</hi>:
                                             corrections or attempted corrections made by a later
                                             hand.</label></handNote>
                                    </handDesc>
                                 </physDesc>
                                 <history>
                                    <origin>
                                       <origDate notAfter="1500" notBefore="1400" xml:id="witGdate"
                                          >XV</origDate>
                                       <note target="#witGdate">saec. XV ineunte scriptus</note>
                                    </origin>
                                 </history>
                              </msDesc>
                           </witness>
                        </listWit>
                     </egXML>
                     <p><gi>note</gi> may be used to specify the portion of the century in which a
                        manuscript was written, if known.</p>
                     <p>Example of <gi>listWit</gi> used to group a family of manuscripts
                        together:</p>
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <listWit xml:id="V" n="V">Family <label>V</label>
                           <witness xml:id="a"><label>a</label>
                              <!-- Identifying information about manuscript a -->
                           </witness>
                           <witness xml:id="b"><label>b</label>
                              <!-- Identifying information about manuscript b -->
                           </witness>
                           <witness xml:id="c"><label>c</label>
                              <!-- Identifying information about manuscript c -->
                           </witness>
                        </listWit>
                     </egXML>
                  </div>

                  <!-- Bibliography: MS Description: Prose -->

                  <div xml:id="bibliography-ms-description-prose">
                     <head>Prose Description</head>
                     <p>In general, nothing prohibits editors of a LDLT edition from describing
                        every last detail of the manuscripts they have used to establish the text,
                        but if the manuscript has been fully described to the editor's satisfaction
                        elsewhere, that work should be cited instead. What to describe depends to a
                        great degree on the nature of the text, the relevance of the information,
                        and the needs of the edition's readership. At the very least, the prose
                        description of a manuscript must include sufficient information for finding
                        the physical object. It must also include the siglum used to identify it in
                        the present edition, and a discussion of any deviation from previous
                        editions in this regard. A date, whether general or specific, is also
                        required. If images of the manuscript are available on the internet, the URL
                        and date of access should be included.</p>
                     <list>
                        <head>Required Elements of a Prose Description of a Manuscript</head>
                        <item>Siglum</item>
                        <item>Settlement (i.e., city or town)</item>
                        <item>Institution (i.e., library or museum), with the name of the collection
                           within the institution, if available</item>
                        <item>Identification number</item>
                        <item>Date (general or specific)</item>
                        <item>URL (if available) and date of access</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>In keeping with established practice, commonly used English names of towns
                        should be used (e.g., Florence, not Firenze), but the original name should
                        be used for institutions and repositories (e.g., Biblioteca Apostolica
                        Vaticana, Ottobonianus). Commonly used abbreviations may be used, especially
                        in cases of well known collections or libraries.</p>
                     <p>Prose descriptions of manuscripts should be in a section of the preface.
                        Each description should be in its own paragraph.</p>
                     <p>
                        <specList>
                           <specDesc key="p"/>
                           <specDesc key="ref"/>
                           <specDesc key="hi"/>
                           <specDesc key="quote"/>
                           <specDesc key="bibl"/>
                           <specDesc key="title"/>
                        </specList>
                     </p>
                     <p><gi>p</gi> (paragraph) contains the prose description of one manuscript. It
                        should have <att>corresp</att> pointing to the <att>xml:id</att> of the
                        structured data description of the manuscript in the bibliography.</p>
                     <p><gi>ref</gi> (reference) defines a reference to the URL of digital images of
                        the manuscript or to the structured data version of the manuscript
                        description in the bibliography of the edition (e.g., for references to the
                        manuscript hands).</p>
                     <p><gi>hi</gi> (highlighted) with <att>rend</att>="bold" distinguishes the
                        manuscript's siglum from the rest of the text.</p>
                     <p><gi>quote</gi> contains any text that is repeated from another source. If in
                        Latin, <att>xml:lang</att>="la" should be used.</p>
                     <p><gi>bibl</gi> (bibliographic citation) contains information about works
                        contained in the manuscript.</p>
                     <p><gi>title</gi> within <gi>bibl</gi> contains the title of a work contained
                        in the manuscript.</p>

                     <p>Example of the minimum required prose description:</p>
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <p corresp="#P"><hi rend="bold">P</hi>: Vatican City, BAV, Pal. lat. 1643.
                           XV. URL: <ref target="http://digi.vatlib.it/view/MSS_Pal.lat.1643"
                              >http://digi.vatlib.it/view/MSS_Pal.lat.1643</ref> (accessed
                           2016-08-04).</p>
                     </egXML>
                     <p>Example of a fuller manuscript description, with discussion of manuscript
                        hands:</p>
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <p corresp="#N"><hi rend="bold">N</hi>: Naples, Biblioteca Nazionale di
                           Napoli, V.A.8, formerly 380, parchment, 261 X 160 mm. It was written at
                           about the beginning of the fifteenth century. It consists of 116 leaves,
                           of which 1–36ʳ contain Cato's <bibl><title>De Agricultura</title></bibl>;
                           20–101ʳ, Varro's <bibl><title>De Re Rustica</title></bibl>; 101ʳ–115ᵛ,
                           the <bibl><title>Bucolica</title></bibl> of Calpurnius and Nemesianus.
                           The remaining leaves are blank. Each page has thirty-eight verses. With
                           respect to correcting hands, two in particular stand out. The <ref
                              target="#Nh1">first</ref> belongs to the original copyist. The
                           manuscript was corrected again around the same time, but here and there
                           the <ref target="#Nh2">second hand</ref> cannot easily be distinguished
                           from the first. A <ref target="#Nh3">third hand's</ref> emendations can
                           be discerned in only a few places. The individual poems lack titles, but
                           they are separated from each other by brief spaces. The following
                           subscription appears at the end of the whole work: <quote xml:lang="la"
                              >Aureliani Nemesiani Cartag&#773; bucol&#8217; explicit: Deo gratias
                              amen</quote>. Finally, another more recent hand, as <ref
                              target="#Bursian">Bursian</ref> and <ref target="#Schenkl"
                              >Schenkl</ref> recognized, wrote <quote xml:lang="la">Calpurnii
                              eclogae</quote> and <quote xml:lang="la">Nemesiani
                           eclogae</quote>.</p>
                     </egXML>
                     <p>For more information on manuscript description, including bibliography and
                        examples, see <bibl><author>Raymond Clemens</author> and <author>Timothy
                              Graham</author>, <title>Introduction to Manuscript Studies</title>
                           (Ithaca, Cornell University Press), 2007</bibl>.</p>
                  </div>

                  <!-- Bibliography: MS Description: Combined TEI and Prose -->

                  <div xml:id="bibliography-ms-description-combined">
                     <head>Combined Structured Data and Prose Description</head>
                     <p>To avoid duplication of effort, it is possible to include the prose version
                        in the structured data version of the manuscript description. In this
                        option, the TEI's <ref
                           target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html"
                           >module for manuscript description</ref> will determine the pattern and
                        structure of the description, and certain information will be encoded
                        according to the module's guidelines.</p>
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <witness xml:id="N"><label>N</label>
                           <msDesc>
                              <msIdentifier>
                                 <settlement>Naples</settlement>
                                 <repository>Biblioteca Nazionale di Napoli</repository>
                                 <idno>V.A.8</idno>
                                 <altIdentifier>
                                    <idno>380</idno>
                                 </altIdentifier>
                              </msIdentifier>
                              <msContents>
                                 <p>1–36ʳ contain Cato's <bibl><title>De Agricultura</title></bibl>;
                                    20–101ʳ, Varro's <bibl><title>De Re Rustica</title></bibl>;
                                    101ʳ–115ᵛ, the <bibl><title>Bucolica</title></bibl> of
                                    Calpurnius and Nemesianus. The individual poems lack titles, but
                                    they are separated from each other by brief spaces. The
                                    following subscription appears at the end of the whole work:
                                       <quote xml:lang="la">Aureliani Nemesiani Cartag&#773;
                                       bucol&#8217; explicit: Deo gratias amen</quote>. Finally,
                                    another more recent hand, as <ref target="#Bursian"
                                       >Bursian</ref> and <ref target="#Schenkl">Schenkl</ref>
                                    recognized, wrote <quote xml:lang="la">Calpurnii eclogae</quote>
                                    and <quote xml:lang="la">Nemesiani eclogae</quote>. The
                                    remaining leaves are blank.</p>
                              </msContents>
                              <physDesc>
                                 <p>
                                    <material>Parchment</material>: 261 X 160 mm.: 116 leaves: 38
                                    verses per page.</p>
                                 <handDesc hands="3">
                                    <p>With respect to correcting hands, two in particular stand
                                       out.</p>
                                    <handNote xml:id="N1"><label>N<hi rend="super">1</hi></label>
                                       belongs to the original copyist.</handNote>
                                    <handNote xml:id="N2"><label>N<hi rend="super">2</hi>: The
                                          manuscript was corrected again around the same time, but
                                          here and there the second hand cannot easily be
                                          distinguished from the first.</label></handNote>
                                    <handNote xml:id="N3"><label>N<hi rend="super">3</hi></label>: a
                                       third hand's emendations can be discerned in only a few
                                       places.</handNote>
                                 </handDesc>
                              </physDesc>
                              <history>
                                 <origin>
                                    <origDate notAfter="1500" notBefore="1400">XV</origDate>
                                 </origin>
                              </history>
                           </msDesc>
                        </witness>
                     </egXML>
                  </div>
               </div>

               <!-- Bibliography: Sources -->

               <div xml:id="bibliography-sources">
                  <head>Other Sources</head>
                  <div xml:id="bibliography-common-elements">
                     <head>Common Elements for All Entries</head>
                     <p>All entries for items other than manuscripts will have certain common
                        elements.</p>
                     <p>Entries should be contained in <gi>biblStruct</gi> with <att>xml:id</att>
                        and <gi>label</gi> as <ref target="#bibliography-sigla">described
                           above</ref>. Entries should also be classified with <att>type</att> and
                        encoded according to the guidelines and examples below.</p>
                     <p>Publication information for all types of entries should be handled with
                        these elements:</p>
                     <p><specList>
                           <specDesc key="imprint"/>
                           <specDesc key="pubPlace"/>
                           <specDesc key="publisher"/>
                           <specDesc key="date"/>
                        </specList></p>
                     <p><gi>imprint</gi> groups information pertaining to the publication of the
                        edition</p>
                     <p><gi>pubPlace</gi> (place of publication) contains the name of the place
                        where the edition was published, as it appears on the title page (e.g.,
                        Lipsiae instead of Leipzig). If the place is unknown, the value should be
                        "s.l." (<foreign xml:lang="la">sine loco</foreign>).</p>
                     <p><gi>publisher</gi> contains the name of the publisher, as it appears on the
                        title page. If the publisher's name is unknown, the value should be "s.n."
                           (<foreign xml:lang="la">sine nomine</foreign>)</p>
                     <p><gi>date</gi> contains the date in arabic numerals (e.g., 1504, not MDIV or
                        CIↃIↃIV). If the date is unknown, the value should be "s.d." (<foreign
                           xml:lang="la">sine die</foreign>).</p>
                     <p><gi>note</gi> with <att>type</att>="url" contains the URL for an online copy
                        of the edition, if available.</p>

                  </div>

                  <!-- Bibliography: editions -->

                  <div xml:id="bibliography-editions">
                     <head>Editions</head>
                     <p>Previous editions must be classified in one of two categories: early
                        editions based on a single manuscript and modern critical editions based on
                        more than one source. This will have ramifications for how the editions are
                        handled in the apparatus criticus (see below, <ref
                           target="apparatus-criticus-patterns">Apparatus Criticus</ref>). This
                        distinction should be preserved in the bibliography with the use of two
                           <gi>listBibl</gi> lists, with <att>type</att> "witness" and "source",
                        respectively. Editors may provide a <gi>head</gi> for each of the two lists
                        (e.g., "Ancient Editions" and "Modern Editions"), if they so desire. The
                        structure of the individual entries should be the same in both lists.</p>
                     <p>The individual entries in each <gi>listBibl</gi> should have
                        <att>type</att>="book".</p>
                     <p>
                        <specList>
                           <specDesc key="biblStruct"/>
                           <specDesc key="label"/>
                           <specDesc key="monogr"/>
                           <specDesc key="editor"/>
                           <specDesc key="name"/>
                           <specDesc key="forename"/>
                           <specDesc key="surname"/>
                           <specDesc key="addname"/>
                           <specDesc key="note"/>
                        </specList>
                     </p>
                     <p><gi>biblStruct</gi> (structured bibliographic citation) is the top-level
                        element for each edition. It should have <att>type</att> of "book". The
                        values for <att>xml:id</att> and <gi>label</gi> should be based on the
                        surname of the editor (e.g., Burm1731 and Burm. 1731, respectively for an
                        edition by Burman pubished in 1731). Additionally, if the bibliography has
                        been generated by Zotero, each entry should have <att>corresp</att> with the
                        URL for the entry in the online Zotero bibliography.</p>
                     <p><gi>monogr</gi> (monographic level) groups bibliographic elements describing
                        an edition.</p>
                     <p><gi>title</gi> contains a form of the title of the edition. Because of the
                        great variation in titles for editions, ranging from none at all to heavily
                        ornamented, and because it can be assumed that the editions listed in this
                        section contain the work in question, <gi>title</gi> may be shortened or
                        abbreviated at the discretion of the editor.</p>
                     <p><gi>editor</gi> contains information identifying the editor of the edition,
                        with <att>xml:id</att> if the editor will be mentioned by name in the
                        apparatus criticus or elsewhere in the edition. If the edition has more than
                        one editor, use one <gi>editor</gi> element for each editor.</p>
                     <p><gi>name</gi> contains the value "Anonymous" in cases where the name of the
                        editor is not known.</p>
                     <p><gi>forename</gi> contains the first and middle names, or initials, of an
                        editor in cases where that information is known.</p>
                     <p><gi>surname</gi> contains the last name of an editor, in cases where that
                        information is known.</p>
                     <p><gi>addname</gi> (additional name) contains a nickname or a Latin name by
                        which an editor might be known (e.g., "Ascensius").</p>
                     <p>Publication information is handled according to the guidelines in the <ref
                           target="#bibliography-pub">section above on publication</ref>.</p>
                     <p>If there is a digital copy of the work available, use two <gi>note</gi>
                        elements: one with <att>type</att>="accessed" to indicate the date when the
                        resource was retrieved, and one with <att>type</att>="url" and
                           <att>target</att> with the value of the URL to provide the address where
                        the resource was found.</p>

                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <biblStruct type="book" xml:id="s"
                           corresp="http://zotero.org/groups/542622/items/TXA4M9HA">
                           <label>s</label>
                           <monogr>
                              <title level="m">Buccolica, cum adnotatione Ascensiana, jam
                                 diligentius recognita</title>
                              <editor xml:id="Ascensius">
                                 <forename>Josse</forename>
                                 <surname>Badius</surname>
                                 <addname>Ascensius</addname>
                              </editor>
                              <imprint>
                                 <pubPlace>Parrhisiis in vico Maturinorum et regione domus
                                    Cluniacensis</pubPlace>
                                 <publisher>a M. Durando Gerlerio</publisher>
                                 <date>1503</date>
                                 <note type="accessed">2016-05-26T16:32:29Z</note>
                                 <note type="url"
                                    >http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k841539v</note>
                              </imprint>
                           </monogr>
                        </biblStruct>
                        <biblStruct type="book" xml:id="Burm1731"
                           corresp="http://zotero.org/groups/542622/items/HZKUF8VA">
                           <label>Burm. 1731</label>
                           <monogr>
                              <title>Poetae Latini Minores …</title>
                              <editor xml:id="Burman">
                                 <forename>Pieter</forename>
                                 <surname>Burman</surname>
                              </editor>
                              <imprint>
                                 <pubPlace>Leidae</pubPlace>
                                 <publisher>Conrad Wishoff et Daniel Goedval</publisher>
                                 <date>1731</date>
                                 <note type="accessed">2016-05-26T16:32:29Z</note>
                                 <note type="url"
                                    >https://books.google.com/books?id=uKZAAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PP9#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false</note>
                              </imprint>
                           </monogr>
                        </biblStruct>
                     </egXML>

                     <p>These will be rendered on screen and in print as follows:</p>
                     <p><hi rend="bold">s</hi> = Josse Badius ("Ascensius"). <hi rend="italic"
                           >Buccolica, cum adnotatione Ascensiana, jam diligentius recognita</hi>.
                        Parrhisiis in vico Maturinorum et regione domus Cluniacensis: a M. Durando
                        Gerlerio. 1503. URL: <ref
                           target="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k841539v"
                           >http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k841539v</ref> (accessed
                        2016-05-26T16:32:29Z).</p>
                     <p><hi rend="bold">Burm. 1731</hi> = Pieter Burman. <title>Poetae Latini
                           Minores …</title>. Leidae: Conrad Wishoff et Daniel Goedval. 1731. URL:
                           <ref
                           target="https://books.google.com/books?id=uKZAAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PP9#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                           >https://books.google.com/books?id=uKZAAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PP9#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false</ref>
                        (accessed 2016-05-26T16:32:29Z).</p>
                     <p/>
                  </div>

                  <!-- Bibliography: Books -->

                  <div xml:id="books">
                     <head>Books Other than Editions</head>
                     <p>The bibliographical information for monographs, commentaries, and other
                        books that are not editions should be handled using these elements and
                        attributes:</p>
                     <p>
                        <specList>
                           <specDesc key="biblStruct"/>
                           <specDesc key="label"/>
                           <specDesc key="monogr"/>
                           <specDesc key="title"/>
                           <specDesc key="author"/>
                           <specDesc key="name"/>
                           <specDesc key="forename"/>
                           <specDesc key="surname"/>
                           <specDesc key="note"/>
                        </specList>
                     </p>
                     <p><gi>biblStruct</gi> (structured bibliographic citation) is the top-level
                        element for each book. It should have <att>type</att> of "book". The values
                        for <att>xml:id</att> and <gi>label</gi> should be based on the surname of
                        the author. Additionally, if the bibliography has been generated by Zotero,
                        each entry should have <att>corresp</att> with the URL for the entry in the
                        online Zotero bibliography.</p>
                     <p><gi>monogr</gi> (monographic level) groups bibliographic elements describing
                        a book.</p>
                     <p><gi>title</gi> with <att>level</att>="m" (monographic) contains the full
                        title of the book.</p>
                     <p><gi>author</gi> contains information identifying the author of the book,
                        with <att>xml:id</att> if the author will be mentioned by name in the
                        apparatus criticus or elsewhere in the edition. If the book has more than
                        one author, use one <gi>author</gi> element for each author.</p>
                     <p><gi>name</gi> contains the value "Anonymous" in cases where the name of the
                        author is not known.</p>
                     <p><gi>forename</gi> contains the first and middle names (middle name
                        optional), or initials, of an author in cases where that information is
                        known.</p>
                     <p><gi>surname</gi> contains the last name of an author, in cases where that
                        information is known.</p>
                     <p><gi>addname</gi> (additional name) contains a nickname or Latin form of a
                        name, if one is commonly used.</p>
                     <p>Publication information is handled according to the guidelines in the <ref
                           target="#bibliography-pub">section above on publication</ref>.</p>
                     <p>If there is a digital copy of the work available, use two <gi>note</gi>
                        elements: one with <att>type</att>="accessed" to indicate the date when the
                        resource was retrieved, and one with <att>type</att>="url" and
                           <att>target</att> with the value of the URL to provide the address where
                        the resource was found.</p>


                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <biblStruct type="book" xml:id="Wilamowitz"
                           corresp="http://zotero.org/groups/542622/items/S2QGZ9FN">
                           <label>Wilamowitz</label>
                           <monogr>
                              <title level="m">Coniectanea</title>
                              <author>
                                 <forename>Ulrich von</forename>
                                 <surname>Wilamowitz-Moellendorff</surname>
                              </author>
                              <imprint>
                                 <pubPlace>Göttingen</pubPlace>
                                 <publisher>Dieterich'sche Druckerei</publisher>
                                 <date>1884</date>
                                 <note type="accessed">2016-05-26T16:32:29Z</note>
                                 <note type="url"
                                    >http://hdl.handle.net/2027/nnc2.ark:/13960/t8jd66k2f</note>
                              </imprint>
                           </monogr>
                        </biblStruct>
                     </egXML>

                     <p>This will be rendered on screen and in print as follows:</p>
                     <p><hi rend="bold">Wilamowitz</hi> = Wilamowitz-Moellendorff, Ulrich von. <hi
                           rend="italic">Coniectanea</hi>. Göttingen: Dieterich'sche Druckerei.
                        1884. URL: <ref
                           target="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/nnc2.ark:/13960/t8jd66k2f"
                           >http://hdl.handle.net/2027/nnc2.ark:/13960/t8jd66k2f</ref> (accessed
                        2016-05-26T16:32:29Z).</p>
                  </div>

                  <!-- Bibliography: Articles -->

                  <div xml:id="bibliography-articles">
                     <head>Articles</head>
                     <p>Bibliographic details for articles published in journals should be encoded
                        using the following elements and attributes:</p>
                     <p>
                        <specList>
                           <specDesc key="biblStruct"/>
                           <specDesc key="label"/>
                           <specDesc key="analytic"/>
                           <specDesc key="title"/>
                           <specDesc key="author"/>
                           <specDesc key="forename"/>
                           <specDesc key="surname"/>
                           <specDesc key="monogr"/>
                           <specDesc key="imprint"/>
                           <specDesc key="date"/>
                           <specDesc key="note"/>
                        </specList>
                     </p>
                     <p><gi>biblStruct</gi> (structured bibliographic citation) is the top-level
                        element for each article. It should have <att>type</att> of "journalArticle"
                        (note case). The values for <att>xml:id</att> and <gi>label</gi> should be
                        based on the surname of the author. Additionally, if the bibliography has
                        been generated by Zotero, each entry should have <att>corresp</att> with the
                        URL for the entry in the online Zotero bibliography.</p>
                     <p><gi>analytic</gi> (analytic level) groups items relating to an article
                        published within a journal volume.</p>
                     <list>
                        <head>Items Contained By <gi>analytic</gi></head>
                        <item><gi>title</gi> with <att>level</att>="a" contains the title of the
                           article.</item>
                        <item><gi>author</gi> contains information identifying the author of the
                           book, with <att>xml:id</att> if the author will be mentioned by name in
                           the apparatus criticus or elsewhere in the edition.. If the book has more
                           than one author, use one <gi>author</gi> element for each author.</item>
                        <item><gi>forename</gi> contains the first and middle names (middle name
                           optional), or initials, of an author in cases where that information is
                           known.</item>
                        <item><gi>surname</gi> contains the last name of an author, in cases where
                           that information is known.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p><gi>monogr</gi> (monographic level) groups bibliographic elements describing
                        the journal.</p>
                     <list>
                        <head>Items Contained by <gi>mongr</gi></head>
                        <item><gi>title</gi> with <att>level</att>="j" contains the title of the
                           journal.</item>
                        <item><gi>imprint</gi> groups several <gi>biblScope</gi> elements defining
                           publication information. All numbers should be arabic numerals.</item>
                        <item><gi>biblScope</gi> (scope of bibliographic reference) is used with
                              <att>unit</att> to indicate details of publication: <list>
                              <item><att>unit</att>="volume" contains the volume number of the
                                 journal in which the article has been published</item>
                              <item><att>unit</att>="issue" contains the number of the issue within
                                 the volume</item>
                              <item><att>unit</att>="page" contains the inclusive pages where the
                                 article may be found</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item><gi>date</gi> contains the year of publication</item>
                        <item><p>If there is a digital copy of the work available, use two
                                 <gi>note</gi> elements: one with <att>type</att>="accessed" to
                              indicate the date when the resource was retrieved, and one with
                                 <att>type</att>="url" and <att>target</att> with the value of the
                              URL to provide the address where the resource was found.</p></item>
                     </list>

                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <biblStruct type="journalArticle" xml:id="Postgate"
                           corresp="http://zotero.org/groups/542622/items/T9VQVNDS">
                           <label>Postgate</label>
                           <analytic>
                              <title level="a">Some Suggestions on Calpurnius Siculus</title>
                              <author>
                                 <forename>John Percival</forename>
                                 <surname>Postgate</surname>
                              </author>
                           </analytic>
                           <monogr>
                              <title level="j">The Classical Review</title>
                              <imprint>
                                 <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
                                 <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                                 <biblScope unit="page">213-214</biblScope>
                                 <date>1901</date>
                                 <note type="accessed">2016-05-26T16:32:29Z</note>
                                 <note type="url">http://www.jstor.org/stable/694806</note>
                              </imprint>
                           </monogr>
                        </biblStruct>
                     </egXML>
                     <p>Note that a review of an edition or other work should be handled in the same
                        way as a journal article, with the exception of the <gi>title</gi> in
                           <gi>analytic</gi>, which should begin with the words "Review of" followed
                        by the title of the work being reviewed.</p>
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <biblStruct type="journalArticle" xml:id="Mueller"
                           corresp="http://zotero.org/groups/542622/items/WJIX5IQM">
                           <label>L. Mueller</label>
                           <analytic>
                              <title level="a">"Calpurnii et Nemesiani Bucolica recensuit Henricus
                                 Schenkl, Lipsiae, G. Freytag, Pragae, F. Tempsky, 1885"</title>
                              <author>
                                 <forename>Lucian</forename>
                                 <surname>Müller</surname>
                              </author>
                           </analytic>
                           <monogr>
                              <title level="j">Berliner philologische Wochenschrift</title>
                              <imprint>
                                 <biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
                                 <biblScope unit="page">1065-1073</biblScope>
                                 <date>1885</date>
                                 <note type="accessed">2016-05-26T16:32:29Z</note>
                                 <note type="url"
                                    >http://hdl.handle.net/2027/uiug.30112023962282</note>
                              </imprint>
                           </monogr>
                        </biblStruct>
                     </egXML>

                     <p>The two examples will be rendered on screen or in print as follows:</p>
                     <p><hi rend="bold">Postgate</hi> = Postgate, John Percival, "Some Suggestions
                        on Calpurnius Siculus." <hi rend="italic">The Classical Review</hi> 15.4
                        (1901): 213–214. URL: http://www.jstor.org/stable/694806, accessed
                        2016-05-26T16:32:29Z.</p>
                     <p><hi rend="bold">L. Mueller</hi> = Müller, Lucian, "Calpurnii et Nemesiani
                        Bucolica recensuit Henricus Schenkl, Lipsiae, G. Freytag, Pragae, F.
                        Tempsky, 1885." <hi rend="italic">Berliner philologische Wochenschrift</hi>
                        5 (1885): 1065–1073. URL: http://hdl.handle.net/2027/uiug.30112023962282,
                        accessed accessed 2016-05-26T16:32:29Z.</p>
                  </div>

                  <!-- Bibliography: List of Scholars -->

                  <div xml:id="bibliography-list-of-scholars">
                     <head>List of Scholars</head>
                     <p>Occasionally it is necessary to refer to a scholar whose unpublished work
                        has been quoted or paraphrased elsewhere. For example, editors often cite
                        Nicolaas Heinsius' unpublished conjectures, found in books in his own
                        library. But "Heins." does not help a reader find more information. That is
                        why the bibliography of an LDLT edition includes a list of scholars
                        mentioned by name in the edition, with information about where to find their
                        remarks, if they are available.</p>
                     <p>
                        <specList>
                           <specDesc key="listPerson"/>
                           <specDesc key="person"/>
                           <specDesc key="persName"/>
                           <specDesc key="forename"/>
                           <specDesc key="surname"/>
                           <specDesc key="addname"/>
                           <specDesc key="ref"/>
                           <specDesc key="note"/>
                        </specList>
                     </p>
                     <p><gi>listPerson</gi> with <att>xml:id</att>="bibliography-scholars" groups
                        the information identifying the scholars.</p>
                     <!-- Use listPerson instead of just list? -->
                     <p><gi>person</gi> with <att>xml:id</att> and <att>n</att> as <ref
                           target="#bibliography-sigla">described above</ref>.</p>
                     <p><gi>persName</gi> (personal name) groups the information about the scholar's
                        name. Note that it is helpful, but not required, to use <att>ref</att> with
                        the <ref target="https://viaf.org">Virtual International Authorify File
                           (VIAF)</ref> permalink for that person.</p>
                     <p><gi>forename</gi> contains the scholar's first and middle names (middle name
                        optional), or initials, of the scholar. A separate <gi>forename</gi> should
                        be used for the first and middle names.</p>
                     <p><gi>surname</gi> contains the scholar's last name.</p>
                     <p><gi>addname</gi> (additional name) contains an additional or alternate name
                        by which a scholar is known.</p>
                     <p><gi>ref</gi> (reference) contains a reference to the entry in the
                        bibliography that has citations of the scholar. <att>target</att> with the
                        xml:id of the entry will cause the reference to point to that entry.</p>
                     <p><gi>note</gi> contains further information about the nature of the citation
                        (e.g., "personal correspondence with editor").</p>
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <listPerson xml:id="bibliography-scholars">
                           <person xml:id="CSchenkl" n="C. Schenkl">
                              <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12523146">
                                 <forename>Karl</forename>
                                 <surname>Schenkl</surname>
                              </persName>
                              <ref target="#Schenkl">H. Schenkl</ref>
                              <note>Unpublished opinions cited in Schenkl's editions.</note>
                           </person>
                           <person xml:id="Scriverius" n="Scriver.">
                              <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/121894458/">
                                 <forename>Pieter</forename>
                                 <surname>Schrijver</surname>
                                 <addname>Scriverius</addname>
                              </persName>
                              <ref target="#Burm.">Burman 1731</ref>
                           </person>
                        </listPerson>
                     </egXML>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="edition-text">
            <head>Edition Text</head>
            <p>The edition text corresponds to the text printed "above the line" of the critical
               apparatus in a traditional edition. It is composed of "accepted readings," that is,
               text judged by the editor to be authentic, accurate, or authoritative.</p>
            <p>There may be more than one authoritative version of a text, depending on the text and
               depending on the approach adopted by the editor. Authors sometimes edit and revise
               their work over time. Scribes often record the version of the text that makes sense
               in their context. Scholars and other readers offer conjectures for problematic
               passages. But an editor must make decisions about the text an edition presents to
               readers. Combined, those decision constitute the editor's argument about the text,
               and they are on display in the official edition text in its initial state.</p>
            <p>Since the online version of an LDLT allows readers to swap readings from the critical
               apparatus into the main text, it is possible to encounter many versions of the text
               in one viewing of it, but the official edition text is the starting point for those
               interactions.</p>
            <p>This section establishes guidelines for encoding the information typically found in
               the main text of a critical edition.</p>
            <div xml:id="edition-text-prose">
               <head>Prose</head>
               <p>The aim of this section is to provide guidance for marking up the structure of
                  prose texts, using the generic model of book, chapter, and paragraph for the main
                  components of a work.</p>
               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="div"/>
                     <specDesc key="milestone"/>
                     <specDesc key="p"/>
                     <specDesc key="seg"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>
               <p><gi>div</gi> (division) marks first-order (e.g., book) and second-order (e.g.,
                  chapter) sections of the prose text. <att>type</att> and <att>subtype</att> should
                  be used to describe the parts of the text; <att>n</att> must be used with
                  second-order divisions to indicate their order in the sequence of the work:</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <div type="edition">
                     <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1"> </div>
                  </div>
               </egXML>
               <p>For an LDLT edition, the top-level <gi>div</gi> has the <att>type</att> "edition";
                  this division contains the entire text of the edition. The next <gi>div</gi> will
                  normally have the <att>type</att> "textpart" with <att>subtype</att> "book" and
                     <att>n</att> "1" to indicate that this is the first book. If a different
                  division scheme is required, editors should consult the DLL staff.</p>
               <p><gi>milestone</gi> can be used to mark the sections of a canonical edition, if the
                  current edition uses a different scheme.</p>
               <p><gi>p</gi> (paragraph) contains the text of a chapter or other basic section in a
                  prose work. <att>n</att> must be used to reflect the numbering scheme of the
                  edition.</p>
               <p><gi>seg</gi> (segment) contains a segment of a paragraph (e.g., a sentence or a
                  more general "section"). If <gi>seg</gi> is used, <att>n</att> must be used to
                  reflect the numbering scheme of the edition.</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <div type="edition">
                     <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1">
                        <p n="1">
                           <seg n="1">Gallia est omnis divisa in partes tres, quarum unam incolunt
                              Belgae, aliam Aquitani, tertiam qui ipsorum lingua Celtae, nostra
                              Galli appellantur.</seg>
                           <seg n="2">Hi omnes lingua, institutis, legibus inter se differunt.
                              Gallos ab Aquitanis Garumna flumen, a Belgis Matrona et Sequana
                              dividit.</seg>
                           <seg n="3">Horum omnium fortissimi sunt Belgae, propterea quod a cultu
                              atque humanitate provinciae longissime absunt, minimeque ad eos
                              mercatores saepe commeant atque ea quae ad effeminandos animos
                              pertinent important, proximique sunt Germanis, qui trans Rhenum
                              incolunt, quibuscum continenter bellum gerunt.</seg>
                           <seg n="4">Qua de causa Helvetii quoque reliquos Gallos virtute
                              praecedunt, quod fere cotidianis proeliis cum Germanis contendunt, cum
                              aut suis finibus eos prohibent aut ipsi in eorum finibus bellum
                              gerunt.</seg>
                           <seg n="5">Eorum una, pars, quam Gallos obtinere dictum est, initium
                              capit a flumine Rhodano, continetur Garumna flumine, Oceano, finibus
                              Belgarum, attingit etiam ab Sequanis et Helvetiis flumen Rhenum,
                              vergit ad septentriones.</seg>
                           <seg n="6">Belgae ab extremis Galliae finibus oriuntur, pertinent ad
                              inferiorem partem fluminis Rheni, spectant in septentrionem et
                              orientem solem.</seg>
                           <seg n="7">Aquitania a Garumna flumine ad Pyrenaeos montes et eam partem
                              Oceani quae est ad Hispaniam pertinet; spectat inter occasum solis et
                              septentriones.</seg>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </egXML>
               <p>In a traditional critical edition, numbers are printed in the margin and/or in the
                  text itself. It is often unclear whether the numbers are meant to mark syntactic
                  units, reflect the numbering of pages or sections in a canonical edition, or
                  something else. When the numbers are printed in the text, it can be unclear</p>
               <p>Note that the TEI Guidelines define the paragraph as <quote
                     source="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html#COPA">the
                     fundamental organizational unit for all prose texts</quote>. The unique
                  characteristics of some texts may require a different approach. In those cases,
                  editors should work with DLL staff to identify the best way to encode the text in
                  question.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="edition-text-poetry">
               <head>Verse</head>
               <p>The <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/VE.html"
                     >verse module</ref> of the TEI Guidelines offers many possibilities for marking
                  up various aspects of prosody, but the LDLT is primarily concerned with the <ref
                     target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html#COVE">core
                     tags</ref> for encoding the structure of verse texts. This does not mean that
                  editors and others should avoid using the verse module. It means only that the
                  LDLT does not provide functionality for that level of detail.</p>
               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="div"/>
                     <specDesc key="lg"/>
                     <specDesc key="l"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>
               <p><gi>div1</gi> (level-1 text division) groups the parts of a book of verse, with
                     <att>type</att>="book" and <att>n</att> with the number of the book.</p>
               <p><gi>div2</gi> (level-2 text division) groups the parts of a single poem (e.g.,
                  stanzas or lines), with <att>type</att>="poem", <att>n</att> with the number of
                  the poem in the book, and <att>met</att> with the name of the meter.</p>
               <!-- Should we require usage of terms from a standard reference work? -->
               <p><gi>lg</gi> (line group) groups one or more verse lines that form a stanza or a
                  couplet, with <att>type</att> and "stanza" or "couplet".</p>
               <!-- Other values?-->
               <p><gi>l</gi> (line) contains the text of a single line of verse, with <att>n</att>
                  and the number of the line.</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <div type="book" n="2">
                     <div type="poem" n="1" met="Alcaic Strophe">
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l n="1">Motum ex Metello consule civicum</l>
                           <l n="2">bellique causas et vitia et modos</l>
                           <l n="3">ludumque Fortunae gravisque</l>
                           <l n="4">principum amicitias et arma</l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </egXML>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="dialogue">
               <head>Dialogue</head>
               <p>Texts that feature interlocutors (e.g., drama, dialogue) should be encoded using
                     <gi>sp</gi> and <gi>speaker</gi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="sp"/>
                     <specDesc key="speaker"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>
               <p><gi>sp</gi> (speech) groups elements related to a person or character's
                  speech.</p>
               <p><att>who</att> is used with <gi>sp</gi> to identify the speaker.</p>
               <p><gi>speaker</gi> contains a human-readable label identifying the person or
                  character speaking the text.</p>
               <p>These features can be used in verse and prose texts:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <sp who="Corydon">
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <l n="1">Nondum Solis equos declinis mitigat aestas,</l>
                     <l n="2">quamvis et madidis incumbant prela racemis</l>
                     <l n="3">et spument rauco ferventia musta susurro.</l>
                     <l n="4">cernis ut ecce pater quas tradidit, Ornyte, vaccae</l>
                     <l n="5">molle sub hirsuta latus explicuere genista?</l>
                     <l n="6">nos quoque vicinis cur non succedimus umbris?</l>
                     <l n="7">torrida cur solo defendimus ora galero?</l>
                  </sp>
               </egXML>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <sp who="Laelius">
                     <speaker>Laelius</speaker>
                     <p>Atqui, Cato, gratissimum nobis, ut etiam pro Scipione pollicear, feceris,
                        si, quoniam speramus, volumus quidem certe, senes fieri, multo ante a te
                        didicerimus quibus facillime rationibus ingravescentem aetatem ferre
                        possimus.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp who="Cato">
                     <speaker>Cato</speaker>
                     <p>Faciam vero, Laeli, praesertim si utrique vestrum, ut dicis, gratum futurum
                        est.</p>
                  </sp>
               </egXML>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="people">
               <head>People</head>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="places">
               <head>Places</head>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="edition-text-reference-scheme">
               <head>Reference Scheme</head>

            </div>
            <div xml:id="edition-text-symbols">
               <head>Symbols Commonly Used in the Text of a Critical Edition</head>
               <!-- Sam: do something about telling people who want to do diplomatic stuff to go look at EpiDoc -->
               <p>The symbols in this section have been gleaned from <bibl><author>Martin
                        West</author>, <title>Textual Criticism and Editorial Technique</title>
                        (<pubPlace>Stuttgart</pubPlace>, 1973), <biblScope unit="page"
                        >80–81</biblScope></bibl>.</p>
               <p>For the sake of uniformity, this section follows closely <bibl><author>Tom
                        Elliott</author>, <author>Gabriel Bodard</author>, <author>Elli
                        Mylonas</author>, <author>Simona Stoyanova</author>, <author>Charlotte
                        Tupman</author>, <author>Scott Vanderbilt</author>, et al.
                        <date>(2007-2014)</date>, <title>EpiDoc Guidelines: Ancient documents in TEI
                        XML (Version 8)</title>. Available: <ref
                        target="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest"
                        >http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest</ref></bibl>.</p>
               <!-- How should I cite individual sections? By author in the "Responsibility" section of the Epidoc guidelines? -->
               <div xml:id="abbreviation-expansion"
                  corresp="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-abbrevfully.html">
                  <head>Abbreviation Fully Expanded</head>
                  <p>The LDLT follows the Epidoc guidelines for encoding fully expanded
                     abbreviations <ptr
                        target="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-abbrevfully.html"/>:</p>
                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="expan"/>
                        <specDesc key="abbr"/>
                        <specDesc key="ex"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>
                  <p><gi>expan</gi> (expansion) contains the full expansion of an abbreviation.</p>
                  <p><gi>abbr</gi> (abbreviation) contains the abbreviated part, i.e. the letters
                     actually on the page.</p>
                  <p><gi>ex</gi> (editorial expansion) contains a sequence of letters added by an
                     editor or transcriber when expanding an abbreviation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <quote>a(bc)</quote>
                  </p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <expan>
                        <abbr>a</abbr>
                        <ex>bc</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </egXML>

                  <p>Multiple &lt;abbr&gt; elements within a single &lt;expan&gt; compose a single
                     abbreviation between them. For example, e.g. is one abbreviation for the phrase
                     "exempli gratia."</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <expan>
                        <abbr>e</abbr>
                        <ex>xempli</ex>
                        <abbr>g</abbr>
                        <ex>ratia</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </egXML>
                  <!-- Need discussion of values for @cert on <expan>. Note that different sections in Epidoc guidelines for abbreviations are based on value of @cert  -->
               </div>
               <div xml:id="add-conjecture"
                  corresp="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-restored.html">
                  <head>Text added by emendation</head>
                  <p>An editor supplies text believed to be missing from the original source. (Cf.
                     Epidoc guidelines "Editorial Restoration: Characters Lost But Restored By
                     Modern Editor" <ptr
                        target="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-restored.html"/>) </p>
                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="supplied"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>
                  <p><gi>supplied</gi> signifies text believed by the transcriber or editor to be
                     missing.</p>
                  <p><att>reason</att> indicates that text has been omitted, but supplied by
                     emendation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <quote>&lt;abc&gt;</quote>
                  </p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <supplied reason="omitted">abc</supplied>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="undetermined-loss"
                  corresp="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-lostcharunknown.html">
                  <head>Undetermined Amount Of Text Lost</head>
                  <p>Text has been lost from one or more witnesses. (Cf. Epidoc guidelines, "Lost
                     Characters, Quantity Unknown" <ptr
                        target="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-lostcharunknown.html"
                     />)</p>
                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="gap"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>
                  <p><gi>gap</gi> signifies text missing because of damage.</p>
                  <p><att>reason</att> with value "lost" indicates that the text has been lost.</p>
                  <p><att>extent</att> with value "unknown" indicates that an undetermined amount of
                     text has been lost.</p>
                  <p><att>unit</att> with value "characters" indicates that an unspecified number of
                     characters (whether single characters or words or larger groups of text) have
                     been lost.</p>
                  <p>
                     <quote>[ ]</quote>
                  </p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="known-loss"
                  corresp="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-lostcharknown.html">
                  <head>Known Amount Of Text Lost</head>
                  <p>The editor or transcriber knows from context and/or observation how much text
                     has been lost. (Cf. Epidoc guidelines, "Lost Characters, Quantity Known" <ptr
                        target="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-lostcharknown.html"
                     />)</p>
                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="gap"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>
                  <p><gi>gap</gi> signifies text missing.</p>
                  <p><att>reason</att> with value "lost" indicates that the text has been lost.</p>
                  <p><att>quantity</att> indicates the amount of text has been lost.</p>
                  <p><att>unit</att> indicates the unit measured in <att>quantity</att>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <quote>[ ... ]</quote>
                  </p>
                  <p>Note that each dot represents a missing character.</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <gap reason="lost" quantity="3" unit="character"/>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="lost-lines-known"
                  corresp="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-lostlineknown.html">
                  <head>Known Number of Lines Lost</head>
                  <p>A known quantity of lines has been lost, or is conjectured to have been lost
                     from the text of all witnesses. (Cf. Epidoc guidelines, "Lost Lines, Quantity
                     Known" <ptr
                        target="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-lostlineknown.html"
                     />)</p>
                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="gap"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>
                  <p><gi>gap</gi> signifies that text is missing.</p>
                  <p><att>reason</att> with value "lost" indicates that the text has been lost.</p>
                  <p><att>quantity</att> indicates the number of lines missing.</p>
                  <p><att>unit</att> with value "line" indicates the unit measured in
                        <att>quantity</att>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <quote>[------]</quote>
                  </p>
                  <p>Note that the brackets and the dashes represent one missing line. The number in
                        <att>quantity</att> will determine the number of instances of that group of
                     characters, one per line.</p>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <gap reason="lost" quantity="3" unit="line"/>
                  </egXML>
                  <!-- How is this handled differently in prose and verse texts? -->
               </div>
               <div xml:id="lost-lines-unknown"
                  corresp="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-lostlineunknown.html">
                  <head>Unknown Number of Lines Lost</head>
                  <p>An unknown quantity of lines has been lost, or is conjectured to have been lost
                     from the text of all witnesses. (Cf. Epidoc guidelines, "Lost Lines, Quantity
                     Unknown" <ptr
                        target="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-lostlineunknown.html"
                     />)</p>
                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="gap"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>
                  <p><gi>gap</gi> signifies that text is missing.</p>
                  <p><att>reason</att> with value "lost" indicates that the text has been lost.</p>
                  <p><att>extent</att> with value "unknown" indicates that nothing more is known
                     about the amount of text that has been lost.</p>
                  <p><att>unit</att> with value "line" indicates the unit measured in
                        <att>extent</att>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <quote>- - - - - -</quote>
                  </p>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="line"/>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="editorial-deletion"
                  corresp="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-superfluous.html">
                  <!-- NEED TO EXPLAIN THAT THIS IS WEST'S SUGGESTION AND WE'RE FOLLOWING IT -->
                  <head>Editorial Deletion</head>
                  <p>Text suspected by the editor to be superfluous, but retained in the main text
                     to indicate its traditional attribution to the author. (Cf. Epidoc guidelines,
                     "Superfluous Text" <ptr
                        target="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-superfluous.html"/>)</p>
                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="surplus"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>
                  <p><gi>surplus</gi> signifies text identified by the editor as added by someone
                     other than the original author.</p>
                  <p>
                     <quote>{lorem ipsum}</quote>
                  </p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <surplus reason="interpolation">lorem ipsum</surplus>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="crux"
                  corresp="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-ambiguous.html">
                  <!-- Doesn't really correspond to http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-ambiguous.html, but it's close. -->
                  <head>Crux</head>
                  <p>Text deemed by the editor to be irredeemably corrupt. (Cf. Epidoc guidelines,
                     "Ambiguous Characters" <ptr
                        target="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-ambiguous.html"/>)</p>
                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="unclear"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>
                  <p><gi>unclear</gi> indicates that the text is readable but not
                     understandable.</p>
                  <p>
                     <quote>†lorem ipsum†</quote>
                  </p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <sic>lorem
                     ipsum</sic><!-- How to indicate that this is an editor's determination? -->
                  </egXML>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-patterns">
            <head>Apparatus Criticus</head>
            <p>This section provides models for handling the different kinds of data that occur in
               the apparatus criticus.</p>
            <p>
               <specList>
                  <specDesc key="app"/>
                  <specDesc key="lem"/>
                  <specDesc key="rdg"/>
                  <specDesc key="witDetail"/>
                  <specDesc key="note"/>
               </specList>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="app"><gi>app</gi> (apparatus entry) contains the lemma and readings for a
               single entry in the apparatus criticus, though it and its contents may be nested
               inside of another <gi>app</gi></p>
            <p xml:id="lem"><gi>lem</gi> (lemma) contains a reading judged by the editor to be what
               the author wrote, or as close as possible. This type of reading constitutes the text
               printed in the main portion of a critical edition.</p>
            <p xml:id="rdg"><gi>rdg</gi> (reading) contains some text (or absence of text) witnessed
               by a manuscript or found in an early printed edition where it is not expressly
               proposed, but judged by the editor to be unsatisfactory or corrupt for linguistic
               and/or stylistic reasons. This text is printed in the apparatus criticus.</p>
            <p xml:id="wit"><att>wit</att> (witness) indicates any manuscript(s) or early printed
               edition(s) (esp. without an apparatus or commentary; i.e., <foreign xml:lang="la"
                  >editiones vetustiores</foreign>)</p>
            <p xml:id="source"><att>source</att> (source) indicates any printed edition(s) or other
               scholarly work(s) (e.g., article, textual note, commentary) addressing an aspect of
               the text.</p>
            <p><att>ana</att> (analysis) indicates that a reading belongs to at least one category
               in the LDLT's taxonomy of readings. More than one value is possible.</p>
            <p xml:id="witDetail"><gi>witDetail</gi> (witness detail) contains information about a
               particular witness (<att>wit</att>) to a lemma (<gi>lem</gi>) or reading
                  (<gi>rdg</gi>).</p>
            <p xml:id="note"><gi>note</gi> (note) contains editorial comments, bibliographical
               references, or other information pertaining to the apparatus entry.</p>
            <div>
               <p>Need discussion about the order in which information is presented.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="basic-app-entry">
               <head>Basic reporting of a variant reading</head>
               <p>A <ref target="#wit">witness</ref> or <ref target="#source">source</ref> has a
                  reading that varies from the lemma in some way. For example, if the editor has
                  accepted the text <quote xml:lang="la">Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet</quote> into the
                  main text of the edition, but manuscript <hi rend="bold">A</hi> has <quote
                     xml:lang="la">larem</quote> instead of <quote xml:lang="la">lorem</quote>, the
                  variant reading would be reported in a printed edition as follows:</p>
               <p>
                  <quote>18 larem <hi rend="bold">A</hi></quote>
               </p>
               <p>Since the lemma is not typically printed in an apparatus criticus (unless there is
                  a chance for confusion), it is up to the reader to recognize that <quote
                     xml:lang="la">larem</quote> is a variant for <quote xml:lang="la"
                  >lorem</quote>.</p>
               <p>In this model, an <gi>app</gi> contains both the lemma and the variant reading,
                  reducing the need for guesswork, at least when looking at the XML code.</p>
               <p>The patterns displayed below are designed to handle the various kinds of
                  information conveyed in a typical apparatus criticus, including readings <foreign
                     xml:lang="la">ante correctionem</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="la">in
                     rasura</foreign>, among other paleographical and editorial details.</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <p>
                     <app>
                        <lem>Lorem</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#A">larem</rdg>
                     </app> ipsum dolor sit amet </p>
               </egXML>
               <p>If an editor deems it important to indicate that a <gi>rdg</gi> also appears in a
                     <ref target="source"><att>source</att></ref>, the same pattern applies, but
                     <att>source</att> is added after <att>wit</att>:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <p>
                     <app>
                        <lem>Lorem</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#A" source="#Jones">larem</rdg>
                     </app> ipsum dolor sit amet </p>
               </egXML>
               <p>If there are multiple variant readings, another <gi>rdg</gi> should be added for
                  each one.</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <p>
                     <app>
                        <lem>Lorem</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#A" source="#Jones">larem</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#B">lurum</rdg>
                     </app> ipsum dolor sit amet </p>
               </egXML>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="additions">
               <head>Additions</head>
               <p>A <ref target="#witness">witness</ref> or <ref target="#source">source</ref> adds
                  text (e.g., in the margin) that an editor deems worthy of notice.</p>
               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="add"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>
               <p><gi>add</gi> (addition) contains text that has been added.</p>
               <p><att>place</att> indicates the placed where the text has been added. Possible
                  values: <list>
                     <item><hi rend="bold">above</hi>: above the line (<hi rend="italic">suprascr. =
                           superscriptum/a</hi>)</item>
                     <item><hi rend="bold">below</hi>: below the line (<hi rend="italic">subscr. =
                           subscriptum/a</hi>)</item>
                     <item><hi rend="bold">bottom</hi>: bottom of the page (<hi rend="italic">ad
                           fin. = ad finem</hi></item>
                     <item><hi rend="bold">inline</hi>: within the body of the original text (<hi
                           rend="italic">in textu</hi>)</item>
                     <item><hi rend="bold">inRas</hi>: in the space where text has been erased. (<hi
                           rend="italic">in ras. = in rasura</hi>)</item>
                     <!-- Note that this is in addition to TEI spec. -->
                     <item><hi rend="bold">margin</hi>: right, left, or both (<hi rend="italic">in
                           mg. = in margine</hi>)</item>
                     <item><hi rend="bold">top</hi>: at the top of the page (<hi rend="italic">ad
                           init. = ad initium</hi></item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p><att>hand</att> indicates the manuscript hand that added the text. See the section
                  on manuscript hands for more information about encoding that information.</p>
               <!-- To be added -->
               <p>For example, the copyist of manuscript <hi rend="bold">N</hi> has the <ref
                     target="#lem">lemma</ref>, but a second hand has added a variant reading in the
                  margin.</p>
               <p>
                  <quote>89 certare] certate <hi rend="bold">G</hi>
                     <hi rend="italic">in mg.</hi></quote>
               </p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app>
                     <lem>certare</lem>
                     <rdg wit="#G" xml:id="rdg89certate"><add hand="#G1" place="margin"
                           >certate</add></rdg>
                  </app>
               </egXML>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="deletions">
               <head>Deletions</head>
               <p>A <ref target="#witness">witness</ref> or <ref target="#source">source</ref> has
                  deleted some text, and an editor deems it worthy of notice.</p>
               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="del"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>
               <p><gi>del</gi> (deletion) contains text that has been deleted.</p>
               <p><att>rend</att> (rendition) indicates the method of deletion. Possible values: <list>
                     <item>erasure: text has been physically removed from the page or lines have
                        been drawn through it (<hi rend="italic">del. =
                        delevit/deleverunt</hi>)</item>
                     <item>expunction: text has been marked for deletion with dots underneath (<hi
                           rend="italic">exp. = expunxit/expunxerunt</hi>)</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>For example, the copyist of manuscript <hi rend="bold">N</hi> has printed the <ref
                     target="#lem">lemma</ref>
                  <foreign xml:lang="la">tristique</foreign>, but a later hand has deleted the
                  letters <hi rend="italic">que</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <quote>tristi (que <hi rend="ital">del.</hi>
                     <hi rend="bold">N²</hi>)</quote>
               </p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app ana="#subtractive">
                     <lem>tristique</lem>
                     <rdg wit="#N">tristi<del hand="#N2" rend="erasure">que</del></rdg>
                  </app>
               </egXML>
               <p>Note that <att>ana</att> with value "subtractive" is on the <gi>app</gi> to
                  indicate that the entire entry concerns a reading that takes away something from
                  the lemma. If there are several <gi>rdg</gi> elements and not all of them are
                  subtractive in nature, <att>ana</att> would be applied to the relevant
                     <gi>rdg</gi>.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="omissions">
               <head>Omissions</head>
               <p>A <ref target="#wit">witness</ref> or <ref target="#source">source</ref> omits
                  some text and the editor deems it important to report the omission.</p>
               <p>For example, the witness known as "P" has omitted the word <foreign xml:lang="la"
                     >pecus</foreign> from the following text: <foreign xml:lang="la">securo custode
                     pecus nocturnaque pastor</foreign>. The traditional apparatus criticus
                  indicates the omission as follows:</p>
               <p>
                  <quote>pecus <hi rend="italic">om.</hi>
                     <hi rend="bold">P</hi></quote>
               </p>
               <p>In this model, the omission is represented by a "self-closing" <gi>rdg</gi>:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <l>securo custode <app ana="#subtractive">
                        <lem>pecus</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#P"/>
                     </app> nocturnaque pastor</l>
               </egXML>
               <p>Note that <att>ana</att> is used with the value "subtractive" to enable querying
                  for this type of data. If there is only one <gi>rdg</gi>, then
                  <att>ana</att>="subtractive" is attached to <gi>app</gi> to indicate that the
                  entire entry in the apparatus concerns an omission. If an omission is to be
                  reported among other readings, <att>ana</att>="subtractive" is applied to the
                     <gi>rdg</gi> that reports the omission:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <l>securo custode <app>
                        <lem>pecus</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#B">pecore</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#P" ana="#subtractive"/>
                     </app> nocturnaque pastor</l>
               </egXML>
               <p>The same model applies to the omission of an entire line of verse, but in that
                  case <gi>app</gi> (with <att>type</att>="lineOmission") and <gi>lem</gi> contain
                  the entire line, and the omission is marked by a self-closing <gi>rdg</gi>:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app type="lineOmission">
                     <lem>
                        <l n="3">et spument rauco ferventia musta susurro.</l>
                     </lem>
                     <rdg wit="#κ #χ"/>
                  </app>
               </egXML>
               <p>This is displayed in the apparatus criticus as <quote><hi rend="italic">vers.
                        om.</hi>
                     <hi rend="italic">κχ</hi></quote></p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="lacuna"
               corresp="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html#TCAPMI">
               <head>Lacuna</head>
               <p>A <ref target="#wit">witness</ref> is missing a portion of the text.</p>
               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="lacunaStart"/>
                     <specDesc key="lacunaEnd"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>
               <p><gi>lacunaStart</gi> is a self-closing tag with <att>wit</att> indicating where in
                  a witness the lacuna begins.</p>
               <p><gi>lacunaEnd</gi> is a self-closing tag with <att>wit</att> indicating where in a
                  witness the lacuna ends.</p>
               <p>For example, witness <hi rend="bold">N</hi> has a lacuna that begins after the
                  word <foreign xml:lang="la">metus</foreign> and ends before the word <foreign
                     xml:lang="la">arcu</foreign> in the following passage: <quote>Mauris ut mauris
                     et metus pharetra dictum et risus. Suspendisse ut maximus diam. Suspendisse
                     luctus diam non libero pellentesque, et aliquam ex congue. Suspendisse vitae
                     lacinia urna, nec egestas arcu. Quisque eget.</quote></p>
               <p>A traditional apparatus criticus might have the following to indicate the
                  lacuna:</p>
               <p>
                  <quote>pharetra … arcu <hi rend="italic">deest</hi>
                     <hi rend="bold">N</hi></quote>
               </p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <p>Mauris ut mauris et metus <app>
                        <lem>pharetra</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#N"><lacunaStart/></rdg>
                     </app> dictum et risus. Suspendisse ut maximus diam. Suspendisse luctus diam
                     non libero pellentesque, et aliquam ex congue. Suspendisse vitae lacinia urna,
                     nec <app>
                        <lem>egestas</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#N"><lacunaEnd/></rdg>
                     </app> arcu. Quisque eget.</p>
               </egXML>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="corrections">
               <head>Corrections</head>
               <p>A variant <ref target="#rdg">reading</ref> has been corrected to the value of the
                     <ref target="#lem">lemma</ref>, but the editor deems the reading prior to
                  correction worthy of notice.</p>
               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="rdgGrp"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>
               <p><gi>rdgGrp</gi> (reading group) contains the readings before and after correction,
                  but since the emphasis is on the original, uncorrected, reading, <att>type</att>
                  is applied with the value "anteCorr" (i.e., <foreign xml:lang="la">ante
                     correctionem</foreign>)</p>
               <p><att>varSeq</att> (variant sequence) indicates the order of the readings (e.g., 1
                  for the first reading, 2 for the correction.</p>
               <p><att>copyOf</att> indicates that the correction is a copy of the <ref
                     target="#lem">lemma</ref>. Instead of copying the value of the lemma, we point
                  to it to indicate that they are the same.</p>
               <p>For example, manuscript <hi rend="bold">N</hi> originally had <foreign
                     xml:lang="la">quaedam</foreign> for the lemma <foreign xml:lang="la"
                     >quidem</foreign>. The editor wishes to note the reading <foreign xml:lang="la"
                     >ante correctionem</foreign>.</p>
               <p>In a traditional critical edition, this would be handled in the apparatus criticus
                  as follows: <quote>quaedam N (ante corr. N¹).</quote> There is no need to print
                  the result of the correction, since "correction" implies the editor's accepted
                  reading (i.e., lemma).</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app>
                     <lem xml:id="lem1.33quidem">quidem</lem>
                     <rdgGrp type="anteCorr">
                        <rdg wit="#N" varSeq="1">quaedam</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#N1" varSeq="2" copyOf="#lem1.33quidem"/>
                     </rdgGrp>
                  </app>
               </egXML>
               <p>Note that the <gi>lem</gi> must have an <att>xml:id</att> to be a target for
                     <att>copyOf</att></p>
               <p>This pattern is the basis for a number of other representations of reading
                  sequences.</p>
               <div xml:id="correction-margin">
                  <head>Correction in the Margin</head>
                  <p>A manuscript hand has corrected a variant reading to the lemma by writing it in
                     the margin.</p>
                  <p>For example, manuscript <hi rend="bold">G</hi> has <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >iantabimur</foreign> in the text, but a second hand has added the accepted
                     reading <foreign xml:lang="la">mactabimus</foreign> in the margin. This would
                     be handled in a traditional apparatus as follows: <quote>iantabimur G (corr. G²
                        in mg.)</quote>.</p>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app>
                        <lem xml:id="lem4.166mactabimus">mactabimus</lem>
                        <rdgGrp type="anteCorr">
                           <rdg wit="#G" varSeq="1">iantabimur</rdg>
                           <rdg wit="#G" varSeq="2"><add place="margin" copyOf="#lem4.166mactabimus"
                              /></rdg>
                        </rdgGrp>
                     </app>
                  </egXML>
                  <p>A self-closing <gi>add</gi> is used here with <att>place</att> and
                        <att>copyOf</att> to indicate that the marginal reading is identical to the
                     accepted reading.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="correction-omission">
                  <head>Correction of an Omission</head>
                  <p>The original copyist has omitted a reading from the text, but another hand (or
                     the original copyist) has supplied the missing text.</p>
                  <p>For example, manuscript <hi rend="bold">G</hi> has omitted the lemma <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">tandem</foreign>, but the original copyist has supplied it. In
                     a traditional critical edition, that would be represented as follows:
                        <quote>tandem] om. G (corr. G¹)</quote>.</p>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app>
                        <lem xml:id="lem1.43tandem">tandem</lem>
                        <rdgGrp type="corrOmission">
                           <rdg wit="#G" varSeq="1"/>
                           <rdg wit="#G1" varSeq="2" copyOf="#lem1.43tandem"/>
                        </rdgGrp>
                     </app>
                  </egXML>
                  <p>If the corrector has added the reading in the margin or elsewhere (e.g.,
                        <quote>tandem] om. G (corr. G¹ in mg.)</quote>, <gi>add</gi> with
                        <att>place</att> and <att>copyOf</att> can be used:</p>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app ana="#subtractive">
                        <lem xml:id="lem1.43tandem">tandem</lem>
                        <rdgGrp type="corrOmission">
                           <rdg wit="#G" varSeq="1"/>
                           <rdg wit="#G" varSeq="2"><add place="margin" copyOf="#lem1.43tandem"
                              /></rdg>
                        </rdgGrp>
                     </app>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="correction-addition">
                  <head>Correction by Addition</head>
                  <p>A variant reading differs from the <ref target="lem">lemma</ref> by one or more
                     characters, which have been supplied by the original copyist or another hand at
                     a later time.</p>
                  <p>For example, manuscript <hi rend="bold">N</hi> has <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >insidia</foreign>, which differs from the lemma <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >insidia</foreign>by a single letter "s". A later hand has added the missing
                     "s". That might be handled as follows in a traditional apparatus criticus:
                     insidia N (<hi rend="italic">s</hi> add. N²).</p>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app>
                        <lem xml:id="lem3.2insidias">insidias</lem>
                        <rdgGrp type="anteCorr">
                           <rdg wit="#N" varSeq="1">insidia</rdg>
                           <rdg wit="#N2" varSeq="2">insidia<add place="inline">s</add></rdg>
                           <!-- Or should this be handled by a <witDetail>? Or both? -->
                        </rdgGrp>
                     </app>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="correction-deletion">
                  <head>Correction by Deletion</head>
                  <p>A variant reading differs from the <ref target="lem">lemma</ref> by one or more
                     characters, which have been deleted by the original copyist or another hand at
                     a later time.</p>
                  <p>For example, manuscript <hi rend="bold">N</hi> has the reading <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">cogaudete</foreign> where the lemma is just <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">gaudete</foreign>. The original copyist has deleted the
                     letters "co" from the beginning of the word. In a traditional apparatus
                     criticus, that might be printed as follows: <quote>cogaudete <hi rend="bold"
                           >N</hi> (<hi rend="italic">corr.</hi> N¹, co <hi rend="italic"
                        >exp.</hi>)</quote>.</p>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app>
                        <lem xml:id="lem2.5gaudete">gaudete</lem>
                        <rdgGrp type="anteCorr">
                           <rdg wit="#N" varSeq="1">cogaudete</rdg>
                           <rdg wit="#N1" varSeq="2" xml:id="rdg2.5gaudete"><del rend="expunction"
                                 >co</del>gaudete</rdg>
                        </rdgGrp>
                     </app>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="correction-with-witDetail">
                  <head>One Witness Among Many Has Been Corrected</head>
                  <p>A variant reading has several witnesses, but only one of them has been
                     corrected, and the editor believes it is important to make that clear.</p>
                  <p>For example, manuscripts <hi rend="bold">P Q R S T U V</hi> have the variant
                     reading <foreign xml:lang="la">flore</foreign> where the lemma is <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">Flora</foreign>. Only manuscript <hi rend="bold">T</hi> has
                     been corrected. In a traditional apparatus criticus, that might be handled as
                     follows: <quote>flore <hi rend="bold">PQRST</hi> (<hi rend="italic">corr.</hi>
                        <hi rend="bold">T¹</hi>) <hi rend="bold">UV</hi></quote>.</p>
                  <p>Since only one witness has been corrected, <gi>rdgGrp</gi> with
                     <att>type</att>="anteCorr" cannot contain the reading of all of the
                     manuscripts, so we must use <att>copyOf</att> on both the lemma and the variant
                     reading.</p>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app>
                        <lem xml:id="lem1.2Flora">Flora</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#P #Q #R #S #U #V" xml:id="rdg1.2">flore</rdg>
                        <rdgGrp>
                           <rdg wit="#T" varSeq="1" copyOf="#rdg1.2flore"/>
                           <rdg wit="#T1" varSeq="2" copyOf="#lem1.2Flora"/>
                        </rdgGrp><!-- Need to consider whether this should be done with <witDetail> instead or in addition to it. -->
                     </app>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="mutation">
                  <head>Mutation</head>
                  <p>Sometimes the copyist or a later hand "corrects" a variant reading to another
                     variant reading. Although the motivation may have been to correct, the action
                     results in mutation.</p>
                  <p>For example, manuscript <hi rend="bold">N</hi> has <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >dipicta</foreign> for lemma <foreign xml:lang="la">descripta</foreign>, and
                     the original copyist has "corrected" the reading to <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >depicta</foreign>.</p>
                  <p>A traditional apparatus criticus might handle that as follows: <quote>dipicta
                           <hi rend="bold">N</hi> (<hi rend="italic">mut. in</hi> depicta <hi
                           rend="bold">N¹</hi>)</quote>.</p>
                  <p>The same pattern for the <foreign xml:lang="la">ante correctionem</foreign>
                     scenarios can be used here, with a different value for <att>type</att>
                     ("mutation") on <gi>rdgGrp</gi>:</p>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app>
                        <lem wit="#P #V #N2">descripta</lem>
                        <rdgGrp type="mutation">
                           <rdg wit="#N" varSeq="1">dipicta</rdg>
                           <rdg wit="#N1" varSeq="2">depicta</rdg>
                        </rdgGrp>
                     </app>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="conjecture">
               <head>Conjecture</head>
               <p>A conjecture is some portion of text (or absence of text) proposed by some person
                  (ancient or modern) and determined by an editor to be worthy of consideration in
                  establishing the text, but not to be printed in the main text of the edition.</p>
               <p>In a traditional critical edition, a conjecture might be noted as follows:
                     <quote>rapidoque] rabidoque <hi rend="italic">conj.</hi> Baehrens</quote>.</p>
               <p>Although conjectures are more common in modern editions and other scholarship,
                  they are not unheard of in manuscripts, where a hand has written a reading (e.g.,
                  in the margin) that does not resemble any other variant readings and cannot be
                  attributed to a recognizable error. Therefore, conjecture is not limited to those
                  materials identified in <att>source</att>. For this reason, <att>type</att> with
                  value "conjecture" must be used to identify a reading as a conjecture.</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app type="conjecture">
                     <lem>rapidoque</lem>
                     <rdg source="#Baehrens">rabidoque</rdg>
                  </app>
               </egXML>
               <p>In this example, <att>type</att> is attached to <gi>app</gi> because the entire
                  entry concerns a conjecture. If the conjecture is just one among many readings,
                     <att>type</att> must be used on the individual <gi>rdg</gi> that contains the
                  conjecture.</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app>
                     <lem>bullantes</lem>
                     <rdg wit="#ε #δ #e #d2">bullentes</rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#η #ν #φ #ρ2 #r #s">bullantis</rdg>
                     <rdg source="#Heins." type="#conjecture">palantes</rdg>
                  </app>
               </egXML>
               <p>If a single scholar has proposed multiple conjectures for a single lemma,
                     <gi>rdgGrp</gi> with <att>type</att> contains all of the conjectures as
                  individual readings:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app>
                     <lem>nullos ducet</lem>
                     <rdgGrp type="conjecture">
                        <rdg source="#Heins.">nullosque sui</rdg>
                        <rdg source="#Heins.">nullosque ducis</rdg>
                        <rdg source="#Heins.">nullosque ducum</rdg>
                     </rdgGrp>
                  </app>
               </egXML>
               <p>That should be displayed as: <quote>nullosque sui <hi rend="italic">vel</hi>
                     nullosque duics <hi rend="italic">vel</hi> nullosque ducum <hi rend="italic"
                        >conj.</hi> Heins.</quote></p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="emendation">
               <head>Emendation</head>
               <p>An emendation is a "successful" <ref target="#conjecture">conjecture</ref>. That
                  is, an emendation is some portion of text (or absence of text) expressly proposed
                  by some person through the application of critical judgment, accepted by the
                  editor in place of the transmitted readings, and printed in the main text of an
                  edition. For this reason, only a <ref target="#lem">lemma</ref> can be classified
                  as an emendation.</p>
               <p>The following example illustrates the difference between an emendation and a
                  conjecture by virtue of the fact that the <gi>lem</gi> has
                  <att>type</att>="emendation" and <gi>rdg</gi> has
                  <att>type</att>="conjecture":</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app>
                     <lem source="#Ulit." type="emendation">niteat</lem>
                     <rdg wit="#N #G #β #κ #π #ρ1 #λ1">mutat</rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#P #δ" source="#p #t #h #Kempfer #Burm.">mittat</rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#μ" ana="#lexical">micat</rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#θ #ν #α #η #r #s"
                        source="#o #n #l2 #i2 #Guid. #Wernsd. #Beck #Glaeser #Keene">nutet</rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#ε #χ #γ #ρ2 #λ2 #d #e #u #b" source="#i1 #l1 #Tig. #Vienn."
                        >nutat</rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#φ">mutet</rdg>
                     <rdg source="#Leo" type="conjecture">micet ac</rdg>
                     <rdg source="#Barth" type="conjecture">nictat</rdg>
                  </app>
               </egXML>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="notes">
               <head>Notes</head>
               <p>An editor wishes to comment on a reading, include bibliographical information, or
                  note something else about the passage in question.</p>
               <p>For example, the editor has recorded a variant reading that another scholar has
                  supported in a textual note. That would be handled in a traditional edition as
                  follows: molle sub] molliter Glaeser, def. Jacoby (Wochenschrift für klassische
                  Philologie III, 1886, p. 1290).</p>
               <p>We handle this with <gi>note</gi> with <att>target</att> pointing at the value of
                     <att>xml:id</att> on the <gi>lem</gi> or <gi>rdg</gi> in question.</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app>
                     <lem wit="#P #V" source="#edd.">molle sub</lem>
                     <rdg wit="#N #G #A #H" source="#Glaeser #Keene" xml:id="rdg1.5molliter"
                        >molliter</rdg>
                     <rdg source="#Schenkl2">molle per</rdg>
                     <note target="#rdg1.5molliter"><ref target="#Jacoby">Jacoby</ref> defendit
                           (<ref
                           target="https://books.google.de/books?id=q5blAAAAMAAJ&amp;hl=de&amp;pg=PA128#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                           >Wochenschrift für klassische Philologie</ref> III, 1886, p. 1290)</note>
                  </app>
               </egXML>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
