<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>XML Patterns for Representing Critical Edition Data</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Developed by</resp>
               <name>Samuel J. Huskey</name>
               <name>Hugh Cayless</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Working guidelines for the Digital Latin Library</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital, with references to the Epidoc Guidelines</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="LDLT-edition-structure">
            <head>Structure of an LDLT Edition</head>

            <p>This section describes the basic structure of the file containing an edition for the
               Digital Latin Library's <bibl><title>Library of Digital Latin Texts</title></bibl>
               (LDLT). The structure of an LDLT edition resembles the structure of a traditional
               printed critical edition:</p>
            <list>
               <head>Parts of an LDLT Edition</head>
               <item>Publication Details</item>
               <item>Front Matter</item>
               <item>Critical Text (including apparatus)</item>
               <item>Indices</item>
            </list>
            <p>Since every text is unique, not every LDLT edition will have all of these sections.
               The nature of the text and the editor's judgment will determine the contents of an
               edition. The purpose of this section is to define the parts of an LDLT edition and
               provide guidelines for representing them in XML.</p>
            <p>These guidelines are based on the standard established by the <ref target="#TEI">Text
                  Encoding Initiative (TEI)</ref>, with modification and customization to
               accommodate the special characteristics of Latin texts.</p>

            <div xml:id="general-structure">
               <head>General Structure of an LDLT Edition</head>

               <p>The following is an example of the general overall structure of an XML file for an
                  LDLT edition:</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <teiHeader>
                     <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                           <title>Bucolica</title>
                           <author>Calpurnius Siculus</author>
                           <editor>Jane Doe</editor>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                           <edition>First Edition</edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                           <publisher>Society for Classical Studies</publisher>
                           <distributor>Digital Latin Library</distributor>
                           <date>2016</date>
                           <availability>
                              <license target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"
                                 >Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                 License.</license>
                           </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <seriesStmt>
                           <title level="s">Library of Digital Latin Texts</title>
                           <biblScope unit="vol">1</biblScope>
                        </seriesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                           <p>Born digital.</p>
                        </sourceDesc>
                     </fileDesc>
                  </teiHeader>
                  <text>
                     <front xml:id="front">
                        <div xml:id="preface">
                           <head>Preface</head>
                           <p>General introductory remarks about the edition.</p>
                           <div xml:id="preface-section-1">
                              <!--This is a subsection within the preface. Editors should use
                              subsections to organize the content of the edition's preface.-->
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div xml:id="bibliography">
                           <head>Bibliography</head>
                           <!--This is where the bibliography for the edition is listed.-->
                           <div xml:id="bibliography-manuscripts">
                              <head>Manuscripts</head>
                              <!--Descriptions of manuscripts, using <gi>listWit</gi>.-->
                           </div>
                           <div xml:id="bibliography-early-editions">
                              <head>Early Editions</head>
                              <!--Bibliographical details for early editions or editiones vetustiores, using
                                 <gi>listBibl</gi> with <att>type</att>="editions-witnesses".-->
                           </div>
                           <div xml:id="bibliography-modern-editions">
                              <head>Modern Editions</head>
                              <!--Bibliographical details for modern editions and commentaries, using
                                 <gi>listBibl</gi> with <att>type</att>="editions-sources".-->
                           </div>
                           <div xml:id="bibliography-secondary-sources">
                              <head>Secondary Sources</head>
                              <!--Bibliographical details for articles, notes, books, and other sources,
                              using <gi>listBibl</gi> with <att>type</att>="secondary-sources".-->
                           </div>
                           <div xml:id="bibliography-scholars">
                              <head>List of Scholars Referred to By Name</head>
                              <!-- A list of the names of individual scholars referred to by name in the 
                                 apparatus, if they are not listed elsewhere in the bibliography. -->
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div xml:id="conspectus">
                           <head>Conspectus</head>
                           <!--A key to the special sigla and abbreviations used in the edition (drawn
                           from the <att>xml:id</att>'s assigned to the various items in the
                           bibliography).-->
                        </div>
                     </front>
                     <body>
                        <div type="edition" xml:id="edition-text" xml:space="preserve">
                        <div type="textpart" n="1" xml:id="part1">
                           <head>Title of First Part</head>
                           <!--Text goes here, according to the conventions laid out elsewhere in these guidelines.-->
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" n="2" xml:id="part2">
                           <head>Title of Second Part</head>
                           <!--Each new major section (e.g., book, volume) has a new <div.-->
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     </body>
                     <back>
                        <!--The content of the back matter will be determined in consultation between
                        the editor and the staff of the DLL. Because LDLT editions are encoded, the
                        matter traditionally found in the back of a printed critical edition may be
                        generated by applications instead of having to be entered manually.
                        Nevertheless, there is space here for notes, indices, and other kinds of
                        information.-->
                     </back>
                  </text>
               </egXML>
            </div>
            <!-- End of section on general structure -->

            <!-- Publication details -->

            <div xml:id="publication-details">
               <head>Publication Details</head>
               <p>A traditional critical edition in print has a title page announcing the title of
                  the work, its author, the editor(s), and details of publication. In an LDLT
                  edition, these details are presented as structured data within a TEI header
                     (<gi>teiHeader</gi>). For example:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <teiHeader>
                     <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                           <title>Bucolica</title>
                           <author>Calpurnius Siculus</author>
                           <editor>Jane Doe</editor>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                           <edition>First Edition</edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                           <publisher>Society for Classical Studies</publisher>
                           <distributor>Digital Latin Library</distributor>
                           <date>2016</date>
                           <availability>
                              <license target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"
                                 >Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                 License.</license>
                           </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <seriesStmt>
                           <title level="s">Library of Digital Latin Texts</title>
                           <biblScope unit="vol">1</biblScope>
                        </seriesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                           <p>Born digital.</p>
                        </sourceDesc>
                     </fileDesc>
                  </teiHeader>
               </egXML>
               <p>Since a critical edition is often based upon many sources (e.g., manuscripts,
                  previous editions, commentaries, etc.), the <gi>teiHeader</gi> for an LDLT edition
                  does not hew strictly to the TEI guidelines for <gi>sourceDesc</gi>. The sources
                  for an LDLT edition are documented and described in the edition's front
                  matter.</p>
               <p>Just as an editor is not expected to create the title page and document the
                  publication information, this section of an LDLT is the responsibility of the DLL
                  staff.</p>
            </div>
            <!-- End of section on publication details -->

            <!-- Front matter -->

            <div xml:id="front-matter">
               <head>Front Matter</head>
               <p>The <gi>front</gi> contains divisions and subdivisions (using <gi>div</gi>)
                  corresponding to the preface, bibliography, and conspectus for the edition.</p>
               <p>The <hi rend="bold">preface</hi> lays out (in prose, using <gi>p</gi>) the
                  argument for the edition. It also describes the textual tradition and its major
                  sources, which is why it is recommended to compile the bibliography first, to
                  facilitate linking to the individual entries as they are mentioned in the
                  preface.</p>
               <p>The elements available in all TEI documents are available for use in the preface.
                  For example, an editor might want to make a table comparing the readings of
                  manuscript families. In that case, the editor would use <gi>table</gi> and its
                  related elements (see the TEI guidelines for <ref
                     target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-table.html"
                        ><gi>table</gi></ref> for more information).</p>
            </div>
            <!-- End of section on front-matter -->
         </div>
         <!-- End of section on general structure -->

         <!-- Bibliography -->

         <div xml:id="bibliography">
            <head>Bibliography</head>

            <p>The bibliography presents opportunities for leveraging the digital nature of an LDLT
               edition. For this reason, every item in the bibliography is encoded as structured
               data (contained in <gi>witness</gi> or <gi>bibl</gi>), so that the bibliography
               itself can become a useful tool for finding and using resources, especially those
               that are available online.</p>

            <p xml:id="zotero">The bibliography is all the more useful as a tool if it is created
               and made available via <ref target="http://www.zotero.org">Zotero</ref>, an open,
               online resource for building and managing bibliographies. It is highly recommended,
               but not required, that all LDLT editions have a corresponding Zotero repository for
               their bibliography. Editors should consult with LDLT staff about setting up and
               sharing a Zotero repository.</p>

            <!-- Bibliography: structure -->

            <div xml:id="bibliography-structure">
               <head>Structure of the Bibliography</head>
               <p>The bibliography should be organized according to the following structure: <list>
                     <item>Manuscripts (<att>xml:id</att>="bibliography-manuscripts")</item>
                     <item>Editions<list>
                           <item>Early Editions
                              (<att>xml:id</att>="bibliography-editions-witnesses"</item>
                           <item>Modern Editions
                              (<att>xml:id</att>="bibliography-editions-sources")</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Secondary Sources
                        (<att>xml:id</att>="bibliography-secondary-sources")</item>
                  </list></p>

               <p>Additionally, there should be a <ref target="#bibliography-list-of-scholars">list
                     of the names of individual scholars</ref>
                  (<att>xml:id</att>="bibliography-scholars") referred to by name in the apparatus,
                  if they are not listed elsewhere in the bibliography (e.g., as the editor of an
                  edition or author of an article). It is common, for example, to refer to a scholar
                  whose unpublished notes appear in a commentary or who has corresponded with the
                  editor. For ease of reference, these sources should be listed with information
                  about where the information can be verified.</p>
            </div>

            <!-- Bibliography: sigla -->

            <div xml:id="bibliography-sigla">
               <head>Human- and Machine-Readable Sigla, Symbols, and Abbreviations</head>

               <p>Printed editions have long used a system of references for manuscripts and other
                  materials in the bibliography. For example, single letters, or <emph rend="italic"
                     >sigla</emph>, stand for manuscripts, and the last names of scholars stand for
                  editions, commentaries, or other works of scholarship. Centuries of use have
                  demontrated that this system of sigla and other symbols and abbreviations is an
                  efficient, effective, and economical way of presenting the complex information
                  contained in critical editions. Although its development was motivated by the
                  constraints of the printed page, its virtues for representing data commend it for
                  other media, too. But just as the printed page has limits, so too does the digital
                  file, which means that the traditional system requires an update to make it useful
                  in a digital context.</p>

               <p>Given some guidance and experience, people can learn how to navigate the system of
                  letters, numbers, symbols, and other typographical conventions for referring to
                  the sources of a crticial edition. If one edition uses superscript numerals to
                  indicate the hands that wrote in a manuscript, but another uses superscript
                  numerals to signify the number of a manuscript in a collection, a human reader can
                  adjust to the difference in meaning without much effort. In contrast, machines
                  need clear instructions and a reliable set of rules for reading a digital file.
                  For example, a human might see <hi rend="bold">N<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></hi>
                  and correctly interpret it within a particular edition as meaning "text written by
                  the second in a succession of people who wrote in the manuscript known as codex
                  Neapolitanus V A 8." Without explicit instructions, a machine will interpret the
                  same information as simply the letter "N" with a superscript numeral 2 next to it.
                  A less experienced human reader might reach the same conclusion as the
                  machine.</p>

               <p>Since the audience for LDLT editions includes an entirely new class of reader
                  (i.e., machines), it stands to reason that the reference system should be adapted
                  to accommodate the needs of the expanded readership. For this reason, LDLT
                  editions encode sigla and other aspects of the traditional reference system in two
                  ways: a machine-readable version (using <att>xml:id</att>) and a human-readable
                  version (using <gi>abbr</gi>, with special instructions for rendering
                  typographical conventions such as superscript and subscript notation). In some
                  cases, the values for both will be the same, but the <ref target="#xml-id">strict
                     rules of the XML specification for <att>xml:id</att></ref> do not allow for the
                  traditional system of combining letters with superscript and/or subscript
                  numerals. Nevertheless, the values of <att>xml:id</att> and <gi>abbr</gi> should
                  be similar, if not identical, to each other, and they should be meaningful.
                  Editors should follow the conventions in previous editions of the same text,
                  changing a siglum only if it is important to the edition's argument to do so. If
                  the text has never been edited, the editor should choose sigla according to the
                  principles outlined by <ref target="#West">West</ref> (74–75). In brief, sigla
                  should have mnemonic value (e.g., "V" for "Vaticanus" or "P" for "Parisinus").</p>

               <p>Because the needs of editors will vary from edition to edition, the LDLT does not
                  have strict rules for representing manuscript hands or similar information. The
                  following suggestion might be useful:</p>

               <table>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell role="data">Information</cell>
                     <cell role="data">Example Value of <att>xml:id</att></cell>
                     <cell role="data">Example Value of <gi>abbr</gi></cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data">A single manuscript</cell>
                     <cell role="data">"V"</cell>
                     <cell role="data">V</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data">Manuscript Hands</cell>
                     <cell role="data">Vh1, Vh2</cell>
                     <cell role="data">V<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>, V<hi rend="superscript"
                           >2</hi></cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data">Multiple manuscripts from one collection</cell>
                     <cell role="data">Vms1, Vms2</cell>
                     <cell role="data">V<hi rend="subscript">1</hi>, V<hi rend="subscript"
                        >2</hi></cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data">One of many indistinguishable hands</cell>
                     <cell role="data">Vrec</cell>
                     <cell role="data">V<hi rend="superscript">rec</hi></cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data">Fragments of ancient copies</cell>
                     <cell role="data">Π1, Π2</cell>
                     <cell role="data">Π<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>, Π<hi rend="superscript"
                           >1</hi></cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data">Consensus of manuscripts</cell>
                     <cell role="data">ω</cell>
                     <cell role="data">ω</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data">One or more late manuscripts</cell>
                     <cell role="data">Ϛ</cell>
                     <cell role="data">ϛ</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data">Scholia</cell>
                     <cell role="data">Σ</cell>
                     <cell role="data">Σ</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data">Scholia in a certain manuscript</cell>
                     <cell role="data">Σa, Σb</cell>
                     <cell role="data">Σ<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>, Σ<hi rend="superscript"
                           >b</hi></cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data">Multiple editions</cell>
                     <cell role="data">Schenkl1, Schenkl2</cell>
                     <cell role="data">Schenkl<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>, Schenkl<hi
                           rend="superscript">2</hi></cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell role="data">Multiple books or articles by the same scholar</cell>
                     <cell role="data">Burm1731, Burm1759</cell>
                     <cell role="data">Burm. 1731, Burm. 1759</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>

               <p>In short, <hi rend="bold">every entry, regardless of type, in the bibliography of
                     an LDLT edition must have values for both <att>xml:id</att> and
                     <gi>abbr</gi>.</hi> Otherwise, the edition will not be able to make full use of
                  the digital format. Morever, if an entry lacks <gi>abbr</gi>, it will not be
                  available for a print version of the edition, should one be required.</p>

               <div xml:id="bibliography-sigla-catch-all">
                  <head>Catch-all References</head>

                  <p>Sometimes it is necessary to use a siglum to stand for the consensus of a
                     particular group of manuscripts (e.g., ω or ϛ). Consensus sigla should be
                     defined in the <gi>listWit</gi> as described in the section "<ref
                        target="#bibliography-manuscripts">Manuscripts</ref>."</p>

                  <p>"Catch-all" references can also be useful: <hi rend="italic">codd.</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">mss.</hi> for "the manuscripts," <hi rend="italic">cett.</hi>
                     for "the other manuscripts," <hi rend="italic">edd.</hi> for "the editions,"
                     etc. It might also be necessary to indicate that, in general, all editions
                     before or after one in particular have a certain reading (e.g., <hi
                        rend="italic">edd. ante </hi>Burm., Burm. <hi rend="italic">sqq.</hi>).</p>

                  <p>It is customary to define catch-all references in the <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                        >conspectus siglorum</foreign> or elsewhere in the preface. Since the
                     conspectus will be generated automatically based on information provided in the
                     bibliography, catch-all abbreviations and phrases must be defined in a simple
                     list at the end of the bibliography.</p>

                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="list"/>
                        <specDesc key="item"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>

                  <list>
                     <item><gi>list</gi> with <att>xml:id</att> with a value of
                        "bibliography-catch-all" contains the catch-all references as items.</item>
                     <item><gi>item</gi> with <gi>abbr</gi>contains a single abbreviation or phrase
                        used as a catch-all reference in the edition. <gi>item</gi> should have an
                           <att>xml:id</att> based on the abbreviation or phrase in
                        <gi>abbr</gi>.</item>
                  </list>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <list xml:id="bibliography-catch-all">
                        <head>General References</head>
                        <item xml:id="codd"><abbr type="siglum">codd.</abbr> = The manuscripts (<hi
                              rend="italic">codices</hi>) not otherwise mentioned.</item>
                        <item xml:id=""><abbr type="siglum">edd.</abbr> = The editions not otherwise
                           mentioned.</item>
                     </list>
                  </egXML>

                  <p>See the section "<ref target="#apparatus-criticus-catch-all-references">Use of
                        Catch-all References in the Critical Apparatus</ref>" for guidelines on
                     usage.</p>
               </div>
               <!-- End of section on catch-all references -->
            </div>
            <!-- End of section on sigla -->

            <!-- Bibliography: MS Description -->

            <div xml:id="bibliography-manuscripts">
               <head>Manuscripts</head>
               <p>The description of manuscripts is a discipline unto itself, with long-established
                  conventions for capturing all of the details about not only a manuscript's
                  contents, but also its dimensions, provenance, material, and other physical
                  details. It is customary for critical editions to provide a brief prose
                  description of the major manuscripts used for establishing the text, usually only
                  enough to identify where the manuscript may be found for consultation, but
                  sometimes including information about its provenance and other details relevant to
                  the edition (e.g., manuscript hands).</p>
               <p>The prose format for describing manuscripts is a predictable and efficient way of
                  conveying this information to human readers, but it is not useful for making the
                  information available to machines for processing. That is why the TEI guidelines
                  have an entire module (<ref
                     target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html">10
                     Manuscript Description</ref>) for making manuscript descriptions available as
                  structured data for machine-readability. The following guidelines are a
                  customization of that module for LDLT editions.</p>
               <p>These guidelines establish a minimum requirement for describing a manuscript for
                  an LDLT edition so that the information can be processed and displayed as
                  expected. They also include instructions for encoding a finer degree of detail.
                  Above all, the point is to make the information available to both human and
                  machine readers, so it is up to individual editors to use their best judgment
                  regarding the amount of information that will be relevant to those seeking to
                  understand the place of a manuscript in the tradition.</p>

               <!-- Bibliography: Manuscript Description -->

               <div xml:id="bibliography-manuscript-description">
                  <head>Manuscript Description</head>

                  <p>The TEI's <ref
                        target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html">module
                        for manuscript description</ref> offers a model for presenting nearly every
                     imaginable detail about a manuscript as structured data. Editors may wish to
                     use more of the features of the module than are described here, but LDLT viewer
                     will display only the following:</p>
                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="listWit"/>
                        <specDesc key="witness"/>
                        <specDesc key="abbr"/>
                        <specDesc key="msDesc"/>
                        <specDesc key="msIdentifier"/>
                        <specDesc key="settlement"/>
                        <specDesc key="repository"/>
                        <specDesc key="idno"/>
                        <specDesc key="altIdentifier"/>
                        <specDesc key="msContents"/>
                        <specDesc key="physDesc"/>
                        <specDesc key="objectDesc"/>
                        <specDesc key="handDesc"/>
                        <specDesc key="handNote"/>
                        <specDesc key="history"/>
                        <specDesc key="origin"/>
                        <specDesc key="provenance"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item><gi>listWit</gi> (list of witnesses) contains the descriptions of
                        manuscript witnesses for the edition. Separate <gi>listWit</gi> elements may
                        be used to distinguish families of manuscripts (see section "<ref
                           target="bibliography-manuscripts-families">Manuscript
                        Families</ref>").</item>
                     <item><gi>witness</gi> groups the information about a single manuscript,
                        archetype, or hyparchetype. The <att>xml:id</att> of each <gi>witness</gi>
                        is the unique machine-readable identifier to be used when referring to the
                        manuscript's data (e.g., in the <att>wit</att> of a <gi>rdg</gi> in the
                        apparatus criticus).</item>
                     <item><gi>abbr</gi> contains the human-readable siglum that should be displayed
                        on screen or printed. Any superscript or subscript characters should be
                        encoded using <gi>hi</gi>.</item>
                     <item><gi>msDesc</gi> (manuscript description) groups the elements that compose
                        the description of the manuscript: <list>
                           <item><gi>msIdentifier</gi> (manuscript identifier) groups information
                              about the location and inventory number of the manuscript.</item>
                           <item><gi>settlement</gi> contains the common English name of the place
                              (e.g., Florence, not Firenze) where the manuscript is located.</item>
                           <item><gi>repository</gi> contains the name of the library or other
                              institution that houses the manuscript. Use the original name of the
                              institution (e.g., Biblioteca Ambrosiana), not an English
                              translation.</item>
                           <item><gi>idno</gi> (identifier) contains the catalog or inventory
                              information for the manuscript, including the name of the collection
                              (e.g., Ottobonianus 1466). The point is to give enough information for
                              a reader to be able to request more information about it.</item>
                           <item><gi>altIdentifier</gi> (alternative identifier) contains other
                              information (i.e., in addition to the <gi>idno</gi>) used to identify
                              the manuscript. For example, the manuscript may have been recataloged,
                              but its old number is still used.</item>
                           <item><gi>msContents</gi> (manuscript contents) contains a prose
                              description (using <gi>p</gi>) of the manuscript's contents, including
                              incipits and explicits. Encode each work with <gi>bibl</gi> with
                                 <gi>author</gi> and <gi>title</gi>.</item>
                           <item><gi>phsyDesc</gi> (physical description) groups information about
                              the manuscript.</item>
                           <item><gi>objectDesc</gi> (object description) contains a prose
                              description (using <gi>p</gi>) of the manuscript's physical
                              characteristics (e.g., material(s), size, pagination, lines per page,
                              etc.). It is up to the editor to decide how to present this
                              information, but it is recommended to adopt a pattern and use it
                              consistently (e.g., "Parchment: 261 X 160 mm.: 116 leaves: 38 verses
                              per page"). Note that the TEI module for manuscript description has
                              tags for these details. Editors may use them, but they will not affect
                              the display or functionality of the LDLT edition.</item>
                           <item><gi>handDesc</gi> (hand description) groups information about the
                              distinct hands that wrote in the manuscript. <att>hands</att> may be
                              used to indicate the number of hands detectable in the
                              manuscript.</item>
                           <item><gi>handNote</gi> contains a prose description (using <gi>p</gi>)
                              of a hand that wrote in the manuscript. Each <gi>handNote</gi> has
                                 <att>xml:id</att> with a unique identifier (based on the
                                 <att>xml:id</att> of the manuscript) and <gi>abbr</gi> with a
                              human-readable version of the value of the hand's <att>xml:id</att>
                              (see the section "<ref target="#bibliography-sigla">Human- and
                                 Machine-Readable Sigla, Symbols, and Abbreviations</ref>" for more
                              information).</item>
                           <item><gi>history</gi> groups information about the date of the
                              manuscript.</item>
                           <item><gi>origin</gi> contains a prose description (using <gi>p</gi>) of
                              the manuscript's date. Enclose the date with <gi>origDate</gi> with
                                 <att>notAfter</att> and <att>notBefore</att>.</item>
                           <item><gi>provenance</gi> contains a prose description (using <gi>p</gi>)
                              of the manuscript's provenance, if available.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>

                  <p>The absolute minimum required for LDLT editions can be met with
                        <gi>listWit</gi>, <gi>witness</gi>, and <gi>abbr</gi>:</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <listWit>
                        <witness xml:id="N"><abbr type="siglum">N</abbr> = Codex Neapolitanus V A 8,
                           saec. XV</witness>
                        <witness xml:id="G"><abbr type="siglum">G</abbr> = Codex Gaddianus pl. 90,
                           12 inf., saec. XV</witness>
                     </listWit>
                  </egXML>

                  <p>That example provides enough human- and machine-readable information to
                     identify the manuscripts in the apparatus criticus, but it leaves much to be
                     desired by anyone hoping to learn more about the manuscripts or locate them for
                     private study.</p>

                  <p>The following example uses all of the elements listed above to provide rich
                     human- and machine-readable information about the same manuscripts:</p>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <listWit>
                        <witness xml:id="N"><abbr type="siglum">N</abbr> = Codex Neapolitanus V A 8 <msDesc>
                              <msIdentifier>
                                 <settlement>Naples</settlement>
                                 <repository>Biblioteca Nazionale di Napoli</repository>
                                 <idno>V A 8</idno>
                                 <altIdentifier>
                                    <idno>380</idno>
                                 </altIdentifier>
                              </msIdentifier>
                              <msContents>
                                 <p>1–36ʳ contain Cato's <bibl><title>De Agricultura</title></bibl>;
                                    20–101ʳ, Varro's <bibl><title>De Re Rustica</title></bibl>;
                                    101ʳ–115ᵛ, the <bibl><title>Bucolica</title></bibl> of
                                    Calpurnius and Nemesianus.</p>
                                 <p>The individual poems lack titles, but they are separated from
                                    each other by brief spaces. The following subscription appears
                                    at the end of the whole work: <quote xml:lang="lat">Aureliani
                                       Nemesiani Cartag&#773; bucol&#8217; explicit: Deo gratias
                                       amen</quote>. Finally, another more recent hand, as <ref
                                       target="#Bursian">Bursian</ref> and <ref target="#Schenkl"
                                       >Schenkl</ref> recognized, wrote <quote xml:lang="lat"
                                       >Calpurnii eclogae</quote> and <quote xml:lang="lat"
                                       >Nemesiani eclogae</quote>. The remaining leaves are
                                    blank.</p>
                              </msContents>
                              <physDesc>
                                 <objectDesc>
                                    <p>Parchment: 261 X 160 mm.: 116 leaves: 38 verses per page.</p>
                                    <p>With respect to correcting hands, two in particular stand
                                       out:</p>
                                 </objectDesc>
                                 <handDesc hands="3">
                                    <handNote xml:id="N1"><abbr type="siglum">N<hi
                                             rend="superscript">1</hi></abbr> belongs to the
                                       original copyist. See <ref target="#Ndesc-firsthand"
                                          >above</ref> for a detailed description of this hand's
                                       activity.</handNote>
                                    <handNote xml:id="N2"><abbr type="siglum">N<hi
                                             rend="superscript">2</hi></abbr>: The manuscript was
                                       corrected again around the same time, but here and there the
                                       second hand cannot easily be distinguished from the
                                       first.</handNote>
                                    <handNote xml:id="N3"><abbr type="siglum">N<hi
                                             rend="superscript">3</hi></abbr>: a third hand's
                                       emendations can be discerned in only a few places.</handNote>
                                 </handDesc>
                              </physDesc>
                              <history>
                                 <origin>
                                    <p>The manuscript was written at about the beginning of the
                                          <origDate notAfter="1500" notBefore="1400">fifteenth
                                          century</origDate>.</p>
                                 </origin>
                                 <provenance>
                                    <p>We know nothing about the origin and provenance of this
                                       manuscript except what is understood from the following
                                       passages written on the last leaf: <quote xml:lang="lat"
                                          >Joannes Antonius Perillus patric. neap. ac iuvenis
                                          apprime litteratus Jacobum Perillum hoc libro donavit
                                          MDCVII, Klis Juniis</quote> ("Joannes Antonius Perillus, a
                                       nobleman of Naples and most learned gentleman, gave this book
                                       to Jacob Perillus in 1667 on the first of June"), and a
                                       little below, <quote xml:lang="lat">Antonii Seripandi ex
                                          Jacobi Perilli amici opt. munere</quote> ("This book
                                       belongs to Antonius Seripandus, received as a gift from his
                                       best friend Jacob Perillus"). Later it was brought to the
                                       library of San Giovanni a Carbonara, and from there it came
                                       to the greatest library in Naples, formerly known as the
                                          <orgName>Reale biblioteca borbonica</orgName>, (now the
                                          <orgName ref="http://www.bnnonline.it">Biblioteca
                                          nazionale Vittorio Emanuele III</orgName>).</p>
                                 </provenance>
                              </history>
                           </msDesc>
                        </witness>
                        <witness xml:id="G"><abbr type="siglum">G</abbr> = Codex Gaddianus pl. 90,
                           12 inf. <msDesc>
                              <msIdentifier>
                                 <settlement>Florence</settlement>
                                 <repository>Biblioteca Medicea Laurenziana</repository>
                                 <idno>plut. 90, 12 inf.</idno>
                              </msIdentifier>
                              <msContents>
                                 <p>It contains the twelve eclogues of Francesco Petrarch (ff.
                                    1–44), the <bibl><title>Culex</title></bibl> of Vergilius Maro,
                                    the <bibl><title>Dirae</title></bibl> of Vergilius Maro (ff.
                                    52–55), and Calpurnius and Nemesianus (ff. 55–74). A very brief,
                                    unattributed eclogue follows with the interlocutors Daphnis,
                                    Tityrus, Mopsus, and Meliboeus.</p>
                                 <p>The following inscription has been added to the eclogues of
                                    Calpurnius: <quote xml:lang="lat">Egloge Calfurnii ad nemesianum
                                       cartaginiensem.</quote> (<quote>The Eclogues of Calfurnius to
                                       Nemesianus of Carthage</quote>). Nemesianus follows
                                    Calpurnius with the following title prefixed: <quote
                                       xml:lang="lat">Aureliani nemesiani cartaginiensis egloghe
                                       incipiunt</quote> (<quote>Here begin the eclogues of
                                       Aurelianus Nemesianus of Carthage</quote>). At the end of
                                    each eclogue there appears an <hi rend="italic">explicit</hi>
                                    with the number of each eclogue, but Calpurnius' sixth eclogue
                                    lacks a subscription, and the following is written at the end of
                                    the seventh: <quote xml:lang="lat">explicit sexta egloga
                                       Calphurnii</quote> (<quote>Here ends the sixth eclogue of
                                       Calphurnius</quote>). This is explained by the fact that the
                                    seventh eclogue follows the sixth without any break, with the
                                    result that only six eclogues are attributed to Calpurnius in
                                    this manuscript. But in the margin, where the sixth eclogue
                                    ought to end, the copyist has added the following: <quote
                                       xml:lang="lat">aliqui volunt dicere quod ista sit alia et
                                       diversa egloga ubi incipit "lentus," aliqui dicunt quod est
                                       una etc.</quote> (<quote>Some wish to say that the eclogue
                                       that begins <hi rend="italic">lentus</hi> is a completely
                                       different eclogue; others say that it is the same,
                                       etc.</quote>).</p>
                              </msContents>
                              <physDesc>
                                 <objectDesc>
                                    <p>Paper: 294 X 225 mm.: 74 leaves. Individual pages generally
                                       have 29 verses, but some vary, with the shorter ones having
                                       26 and the longer ones haveing 32 verses.</p>
                                 </objectDesc>
                                 <handDesc hands="2">
                                    <handNote xml:id="G1"><abbr type="siglum">G<hi
                                             rend="superscript">1</hi></abbr>: The copyist himself
                                       added almost all of the corrections either by removing
                                       scribal errors in the verses or adding variant readings to
                                       the margin. See <ref target="#Gdesc-hand">above</ref> for a
                                       more detailed description of this hand's activity.</handNote>
                                    <handNote xml:id="G2"><abbr type="siglum">G<hi
                                             rend="superscript">2</hi></abbr>: Some corrections seem
                                       to have been made by another hand.</handNote>
                                 </handDesc>
                              </physDesc>
                              <history>
                                 <origin>
                                    <p>Written at the <origDate notAfter="1500" notBefore="1400"
                                          >beginning of the fifteenth century</origDate>.</p>
                                 </origin>
                              </history>
                           </msDesc>
                        </witness>
                     </listWit>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <!-- End of section on structured data manuscript description -->

               <div xml:id="bibliography-manuscripts-families-archetypes">
                  <head>Manuscript Families, Archetypes, and Hyparchetypes</head>

                  <p>Sigla may be assigned to families of manuscripts, archetypes, and hyparchetypes
                     so that they may be referred to in the apparatus criticus or elsewhere. As
                     indicated in the section "<ref target="#bibliography-sigla">Human- and
                        Machine-Readable Sigla, Symbols, and Abbreviations</ref>," each family,
                     archetype, and hyparchetype must have both a unique <att>xml:id</att>
                     (machine-readable siglum) and an <gi>abbr</gi> (human-readable siglum).</p>

                  <div xml:id="bibliography-manuscripts-families">
                     <head>Manuscript Families</head>

                     <p>Since the family is not itself a physical object, but a concept (i.e., a
                        group of related manuscripts), its siglum is assigned to <gi>listWit</gi> as
                        the container of the individual <gi>witness</gi> elements that describe the
                        manuscripts in the family.</p>

                     <p>In the following example, <gi>listWit</gi> has the <att>xml:id</att> V for
                        the machine-readable siglum; <gi>head</gi> contains the name of the family
                        and the human-readable siglum in <gi>abbr</gi>.</p>

                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <listWit xml:id="V">
                           <head>First Family (<abbr type="siglum">V</abbr></head>
                           <witness xml:id="A">
                              <!-- Description of manuscript A -->
                           </witness>
                           <witness xml:id="B">
                              <!-- Description of manuscript B -->
                           </witness>
                           <!-- Et cetera -->
                        </listWit>
                     </egXML>
                  </div>
                  <!-- End of section on manuscript families -->

                  <div xml:id="bibliography-manuscripts-hyparchetypes-archetypes">
                     <head>Archetypes and Hyparchetypes</head>

                     <p>An archetype is the "lowest common ancestor of the known manuscripts" (<ref
                           target="#West">West</ref> 32). A hyparchetype is the ancestor of a branch
                        of a family of manuscripts. In editions of Latin texts, both archetypes and
                        hyparchetypes are commonly represented with lower case Greek letters.</p>

                     <p>For example, <ref target="#kaster-suetonius">Robert Kaster</ref> assigns the
                        siglum ω to the archetype of the manuscripts of Suetonius' <bibl><title>De
                              Vita Caesarum</title></bibl>. The manuscripts can be analyzed into two
                        families that stem from two hyparchetypes, to which Kaster has assigned the
                        sigla α and β. The two families have branches, each with their own
                        hyparchetype (α<hi rend="subscript">1</hi> α<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> β<hi
                           rend="subscript">1</hi> β<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>).</p>

                     <p>Kaster lists the sigla as follows:<list>
                           <item>ω archetypus codicum αβ <list>
                                 <item>α hyparchetypus codicum α<hi rend="subscript">1</hi>Vα<hi
                                       rend="subscript">2</hi><list>
                                       <item>α<hi rend="subscript">1</hi> hyparchetypus codicum MG<list>
                                             <item>M Paris. lat. 6115 s. IX<hi rend="superscript"
                                                  >1/2</hi> (an. c. 820?)</item>
                                             <item>G Guelf. 4573 (Gud. lat. 268), s. XI<hi
                                                  rend="superscript">3/4</hi></item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>etc.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>

                     <p>Though no longer extant, archetypes and hyparchetypes can be referred to as
                        witnesses to readings. Therefore, they are encoded with <gi>witness</gi>.
                        The following example demonstrates how Kaster's list should be encoded:</p>

                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <listWit>
                           <witness xml:id="ω"><abbr type="siglum">ω</abbr> = archetypus codicum αβ <listWit>
                                 <witness xml:id="a"><abbr type="siglum">α</abbr> = hyparchetypus
                                    codicum α<hi rend="subscript">1</hi>Vα <listWit>
                                       <witness xml:id="α1"><abbr type="siglum">α<hi
                                                rend="subscript">1</hi></abbr> = hyparchetypus
                                          codicum MG <listWit>
                                             <witness xml:id="M"><abbr type="siglum"
                                                >M</abbr><!-- Description of witness M -->
                                             </witness>
                                             <witness xml:id="G"><abbr type="siglum"
                                                >G</abbr><!-- Description of witness G --></witness>
                                          </listWit>
                                       </witness>
                                    </listWit>
                                 </witness>
                              </listWit>
                           </witness>
                        </listWit>
                     </egXML>
                  </div>
                  <!-- End of section on archetypes and hyparchetypes -->
               </div>
               <!-- End of section on families, archetypes, and hyparchetypes -->
            </div>
            <!-- End of section on manuscript description in general -->

            <!-- Bibliography: Sources -->

            <div xml:id="bibliography-sources">
               <head>Sources</head>

               <p>The bibliography for early editions, modern editions, commentaries, translations,
                  articles, notes, and other materials cited in the edition should be formatted
                  according to latest edition of <ref target="#Chicago"><hi rend="italic">The
                        Chicago Manual of Style</hi></ref>. As noted <ref target="#zotero">elsewhere
                     in these guidelines</ref>, it is recommended that editors use <ref
                     target="https://www.zotero.org/">Zotero</ref> to manage the bibliography for
                  LDLT editions, not least because Zotero can export the bibliography in Chicago
                  style.</p>

               <p>Items should be categorized and listed in groups for ease of reference. For
                  example, previous editions should be listed separately from commentaries and
                  articles. Depending on the nature of the material, it may be useful to subdivide
                  previous editions into early and modern editions.</p>

               <p>In keeping with the goal of human- and machine-readability, individual items in
                  the bibliography should also be encoded in XML. To meet the <hi rend="bold"
                     >minimum requirement</hi> for LDLT editions, individual items in the
                  bibliography should be enclosed with <gi>bibl</gi> and they should have human- and
                  machine-readable abbreviations (sigla), using <gi>abbr</gi> and <att>xml:id</att>
                  respectively. See the section "<ref target="#bibliography-sigla">Human- and
                     Machine-Readable Sigla, Symbols, and Abbreviations</ref>" for more
                  information.</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <listBibl>
                     <head>Previous Editions</head>
                     <bibl xml:id="Barth1613"><abbr type="siglum">Barth 1613</abbr> = Barthius,
                        Casparus. Venatici et Bucolici Poetae Latini: Gratius, Nemesianus,
                        Calpurnius. Hanoviae: In Bibliopolio Willieriano, 1613.</bibl>
                     <bibl xml:id="Ulit."><abbr type="siglum">Ulit.</abbr> = Ulitius, Ianus. Venatio
                        Novantiqua. Leidae: Ex Officina Elzeveriana, 1645.</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </egXML>

               <p>For maximum functionality, it is strongly recommended to encode a greater degree
                  of bibliographical detail, using the following: <list>
                     <item><gi>editor</gi> or <gi>author</gi></item>
                     <item><gi>title</gi></item>
                     <item><gi>pubPlace</gi> (place of publication)</item>
                     <item><gi>publisher</gi></item>
                     <item><gi>date</gi></item>
                     <item><gi>ptr</gi> (pointer, for the URL of a digital copy, if
                        available)</item>
                  </list></p>

               <p>The following sections demonstrate the recommended encoding for common types of
                  records in a bibliography.</p>


               <!-- Bibliography: editions -->

               <div xml:id="bibliography-editions">
                  <head>Editions</head>
                  <p>To make the most of the functionality supported by the LDLT and to remain true
                     to its data model, previous editions should be classified in one of two
                     categories: early editions based on a single manuscript, and modern critical
                     editions based on more than one source. This will have consequences for how the
                     editions are handled in the apparatus criticus (see the section "<ref
                        target="#apparatus-criticus">Apparatus Criticus</ref>"). The distinction
                     should be preserved in the bibliography with the use of two different kinds of
                     lists: <gi>listWit</gi> for early editions, and <gi>listBibl</gi> for modern
                     editions. In both types of list, the items should be presented in chronological
                     order.</p>

                  <div xml:id="bibliography-editions-early">
                     <head>Early Editions</head>

                     <p>Since it is often the case that an early edition is a witness to a single
                        manuscript that might otherwise be lost, early editions should be encoded in
                        the bibliography with <gi>witness</gi>. Accordingly, they must be grouped in
                           <gi>listWit</gi>. Since they are also printed books, they also require
                        the use of <gi>bibl</gi> and its related elements.</p>

                     <p>
                        <specList>
                           <specDesc key="listWit"/>
                           <specDesc key="witness"/>
                           <specDesc key="abbr"/>
                           <specDesc key="bibl"/>
                           <specDesc key="editor"/>
                           <specDesc key="title"/>
                           <specDesc key="pubPlace"/>
                           <specDesc key="publisher"/>
                           <specDesc key="date"/>
                           <specDesc key="ptr"/>
                        </specList>
                     </p>

                     <list>
                        <item><gi>listWit</gi> (list of witnesses) contains bibliographical records
                           for early editions.</item>
                        <item><gi>witness</gi> groups the information about an individual edition.
                              <att>xml:id</att> provides the machine-readable abbreviation for the
                           edition.</item>
                        <item><gi>abbr</gi> (abbreviation) with <att>type</att>="siglum" contains
                           the human-readable abbreviation for the record, i.e., how the edition is
                           referred to in the apparatus criticus.</item>
                        <item><gi>bibl</gi> (bibliographic citation) contains the following
                           bibliographical information about the edition: <list>
                              <item><gi>editor</gi> contains the name of the editor in the form
                                 "Last name, First name," if known. If the name is in Latin, it
                                 should not be translated. If the name is not known, <gi>editor</gi>
                                 contains the word "Anonymous."</item>
                              <item><gi>title</gi> contains either the name by which the edition is
                                 commonly known (e.g., <foreign xml:lang="lat">editio
                                    Romana</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="lat">editio
                                    Aldina</foreign>) and/or the actual title of the edition.</item>
                              <item><gi>pubPlace</gi> (place of publication) contains the name of
                                 the place where the edition was published, as it appears on the
                                 title page (e.g., Lipsiae instead of Leipzig). If the place is
                                 unknown, the value should be "s.l." (<foreign xml:lang="lat">sine
                                    loco</foreign>). If the place is known, but not explicitly
                                 printed in the edition, the place name should be enclosed in square
                                 brackets.</item>
                              <item><gi>publisher</gi> contains the name of the publisher, as it
                                 appears on the title page. If the publisher's name is unknown, the
                                 value should be "s.n." (<foreign xml:lang="lat">sine
                                    nomine</foreign>). If the publisher is known, but not explicitly
                                 printed in the edition, the publisher's name should be enclosed in
                                 square brackets.</item>
                              <item><gi>date</gi> contains the date in arabic numerals (e.g., 1504,
                                 not MDIV or CIↃIↃIV). If the date is unknown, the value should be
                                 "s.d." (<foreign xml:lang="lat">sine die</foreign>). If the date is
                                 known, but not explicitly printed in the edition, the date should
                                 be enclosed in square brackets.</item>
                              <item><gi>ptr</gi> (pointer) has <att>target</att> with the URL of a
                                 digital copy of the edition, if one exists.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>

                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <listWit xml:id="early-editions">
                           <head>Early Editions</head>
                           <witness xml:id="r">
                              <abbr type="siglum">r</abbr> =
                                    <bibl><editor><name>Anonymous</name></editor>. <title>editio
                                    Romana</title>. <pubPlace>[Romae]</pubPlace>:
                                    <publisher>Schweynheim et Pannartz</publisher>,
                                    <date>1471</date></bibl>.</witness>
                           <witness xml:id="e"><abbr type="siglum">e</abbr> =
                                       <bibl><editor><name>Anonymous</name>. </editor><title>editio
                                    Veneta</title>. <pubPlace>[Venetiis]</pubPlace>:
                                    <publisher>Ausonius et Giradinus</publisher>,
                                 <date>1472</date></bibl>.</witness>
                           <witness xml:id="u"><abbr type="siglum">u</abbr> =
                                    <bibl><editor>Anonymous</editor>. <title>editio Ang.
                                    Ugoleti</title>. <pubPlace>Parmae</pubPlace>: <publisher>Angelus
                                    Ugoletus</publisher>, <date>1492</date></bibl>.</witness>
                           <witness xml:id="c"><abbr type="siglum">c</abbr> =
                                    <bibl><editor>Anonymous</editor>. <title>editio Coloniensis
                                    (Buccolica canori poetae Titi Calphurnii Siculi undecim Aeglogis
                                    iucunditer decantata)</title>. <pubPlace>Coloniae</pubPlace>:
                                    <publisher>[Henricus Quintell]</publisher>,
                                 <date>1505(?)</date></bibl>. URL: <ptr
                                 target="http://digitale.bibliothek.uni-halle.de/vd16/content/titleinfo/1000626"
                              />.</witness>
                           <witness xml:id="Nordh."><abbr type="siglum">Nordh.</abbr> =
                                 <bibl><editor/>. <title>ed. Nordheimensis</title>.
                                    <pubPlace>[Nordheim]</pubPlace>: <publisher>s.n.</publisher>,
                                    <date>s.d.</date></bibl>.</witness>
                           <witness xml:id="s"><abbr type="siglum">s</abbr> = <bibl><title>editio
                                    Ascensiana</title> = <editor>Badius, Josse
                                    (“Ascensius”)</editor>. <title>Buccolica, cum adnotatione
                                    Ascensiana</title>. <pubPlace>Parhisiis, in vico
                                    Maturinorum</pubPlace>: <publisher>a Durando
                                    Gerlerio</publisher>, <date>1503</date></bibl>. URL: <ptr
                                 target="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k841539v"/>.</witness>
                           <witness xml:id="b"><abbr type="siglum">b</abbr> = <bibl><title>editio
                                    Bononiensis</title> = <editor>Guidalottus Bononiensis,
                                    Diomedes</editor>. <title>Calpurnii et Nemesiani Poetarum
                                    Buccolicum Carmen</title>. <pubPlace>Bononiae</pubPlace>:
                                    <publisher>per Caligulam Bazalerium</publisher>,
                                    <date>1504</date></bibl>. URL: <ptr
                                 target="https://books.google.com/books?id=B1RrV7ciP6gC&amp;pg=PT3#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                              />.</witness>
                        </listWit>
                     </egXML>
                  </div>
                  <!-- End of section on early editions -->


                  <div xml:id="bibliography-editions-modern">
                     <head>Modern Editions</head>

                     <p>The bibliography for modern editions follows the same pattern as that for
                        early editions, except <gi>listBibl</gi> is used instead of
                        <gi>listWit</gi>.</p>

                     <p>
                        <specList>
                           <specDesc key="listBibl"/>
                           <specDesc key="bibl"/>
                           <specDesc key="abbr"/>
                           <specDesc key="editor"/>
                           <specDesc key="title"/>
                           <specDesc key="pubPlace"/>
                           <specDesc key="publisher"/>
                           <specDesc key="date"/>
                           <specDesc key="ptr"/>
                        </specList>
                     </p>

                     <list>
                        <item><gi>listBibl</gi> (citation lists) contains bibliographical records
                           for modern editions.</item>
                        <item><gi>bibl</gi> (bibliographic citation) has <att>xml:id</att> with the
                           machine-readable abbreviation for the edition. It contains the following
                           bibliographical information about the edition: <list>
                              <item><gi>abbr</gi> (abbreviation) contains the human-readable
                                 abbreviation for the record, i.e., how the edition is referred to
                                 in the apparatus criticus.</item>
                              <item><gi>editor</gi> contains the name of the editor in the form
                                 "Last name, First name," if known. If the name is in Latin, it
                                 should not be translated. If the name is not known, <gi>editor</gi>
                                 contains the word "Anonymous."</item>
                              <item><gi>title</gi> contains either the name by which the edition is
                                 commonly known (e.g., editio Romana, editio Aldina) and/or the
                                 actual title of the edition.</item>
                              <item><gi>pubPlace</gi> (place of publication) contains the name of
                                 the place where the edition was published, as it appears on the
                                 title page (e.g., Lipsiae instead of Leipzig). If the place is
                                 unknown, the value should be "s.l." (<foreign xml:lang="lat">sine
                                    loco</foreign>). If the place is known, but not explicitly
                                 printed in the edition, the place name should be enclosed in square
                                 brackets.</item>
                              <item><gi>publisher</gi> contains the name of the publisher, as it
                                 appears on the title page. If the publisher's name is unknown, the
                                 value should be "s.n." (<foreign xml:lang="lat">sine
                                    nomine</foreign>). If the publisher is known, but not explicitly
                                 printed in the edition, the publisher's name should be enclosed in
                                 square brackets.</item>
                              <item><gi>date</gi> contains the date in arabic numerals (e.g., 1504,
                                 not MDIV or CIↃIↃIV). If the date is unknown, the value should be
                                 "s.d." (<foreign xml:lang="lat">sine die</foreign>). If the date is
                                 known, but not explicitly printed in the edition, the date should
                                 be enclosed in square brackets.</item>
                              <item><gi>ptr</gi> (pointer) has <att>target</att> with the URL of a
                                 digital copy of the edition, if one exists.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>

                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <listBibl xml:id="modern-editions">
                           <head>Modern Editions</head>
                           <bibl xml:id="n"><abbr type="siglum">n</abbr> = <editor>Brassicanus,
                                 Johannes Alexander</editor>. <title>editio Brassicani</title>.
                                 <pubPlace>Argentorati (Strasbourg)</pubPlace>: <publisher>Iohannis
                                 Knoblochus</publisher>, <date>1519</date>. URL: <ptr
                                 target="https://books.google.com/books?id=n8JSAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                              />.</bibl>
                           <bibl xml:id="Vienn."><abbr type="siglum">Vienn.</abbr> =
                                 <editor>Anonymous</editor>. <title>ed. Viennensis</title>.
                                 <pubPlace>s.l.</pubPlace>, <date>s.d.</date></bibl>
                           <bibl xml:id="g"><abbr type="siglum">g</abbr> = <editor>Logus,
                                 Georgius</editor>. <title>editio Augustana</title>.
                                 <pubPlace>Augustae Vindelicorum</pubPlace>: <publisher>in officina
                                 Henrici Steyner</publisher>), <date>1534</date>. URL: <ptr
                                 target="http://daten.digitale-sammlungen.de/~db/0003/bsb00038602/images/"
                              /></bibl>
                           <bibl xml:id="Tig."><abbr type="siglum">Tig.</abbr> =
                                 <editor>Anonymous</editor>. <title>editio Tigurina</title>
                              <pubPlace>Tiguri</pubPlace>: <pubPlace>apud Christophorum
                                 Froschouerum</pubPlace>, <date>1537</date>. URL: <ptr
                                 target="http://reader.digitale-sammlungen.de/resolve/display/bsb11088503.html"
                              />.</bibl>
                           <bibl xml:id="Gryph."><abbr type="siglum">Gryph.</abbr> =
                                 <editor>Anonymous</editor>. <title>editio Gryph.</title>
                              <pubPlace>Lugduni</pubPlace>: <publisher>apud Seb.
                                 Gyrphium</publisher>, <date>1537</date>. URL: <ptr
                                 target="https://books.google.com/books?id=JpJXAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                              />.</bibl>
                           <bibl xml:id="o"><abbr type="siglum">o</abbr> =
                                 <editor>Anonymous</editor>. <title>ed. Oporiniana</title>
                              <pubPlace>Basileae</pubPlace>: <publisher>Johannes
                                 Oporinus</publisher>, <date>1546</date>.URL: <ptr
                                 target="https://books.google.com/books?id=cKqCwvkRiTgC&amp;pg=PP5#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                              /></bibl>
                           <bibl xml:id="p"><abbr type="siglum">p</abbr> = <title>ed.
                                 Pithoeana</title> = <editor>Pithoeus, Petrus</editor>.
                                 <title>Epigrammata et poematia vetera</title>.
                                 <pubPlace>Parisiis</pubPlace>: <publisher>Dionysius
                                 Duvallius</publisher>, <date>1590</date>. URL: <ptr
                                 target="https://books.google.com/books?id=F_E6AAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PR6#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                              /></bibl>
                           <bibl xml:id="edAurel"><abbr type="siglum">Aurel.</abbr> =
                                 <editor>Anonymous</editor>. <title>Corpus omnium veterum poetarum
                                 latinorum (Volumen Secundum)</title>. <pubPlace>Aureliae
                                 Allobrogum</pubPlace>: <publisher>Samuel Crispinus</publisher>,
                                 <date>1611</date>. URL: <ptr
                                 target="https://books.google.com/books?id=Q-EPAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PP5#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                              /></bibl>
                           <bibl xml:id="Barth1613"><abbr type="siglum">Barth 1613</abbr> =
                                 <title>ed. Barthii</title> = <editor>Barthius, Casparus</editor>.
                                 <title>Venatici et Bucolici Poetae Latini: Gratius, Nemesianus,
                                 Calpurnius</title>. <pubPlace>Hanoviae</pubPlace>: <publisher>In
                                 Bibliopolio Willieriano</publisher>, <date>1613</date>. URL: <ptr
                                 target="https://books.google.com/books?id=SEVXAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PP7#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                              /></bibl>
                           <bibl xml:id="Ulit."><abbr type="siglum">Ulit.</abbr> = <title>ed.
                                 Ulitii</title> = <editor>Ulitius, Ianus</editor>. <title>Venatio
                                 Novantiqua</title>. <pubPlace>Leidae</pubPlace>: <publisher>Ex
                                 Officina Elzeveriana</publisher>, <date>1645</date>. URL: <ptr
                                 target="https://books.google.com/books?id=Yb09AAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PR4#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                              /></bibl>
                           <bibl xml:id="h"><abbr type="siglum">h</abbr> = ed. Haverkampi et Brucii
                              = <editor>Anonymous</editor>. <title>Poetae Latini Rei Venaticae
                                 Scriptores et Bucolici Antiqui</title>. <pubPlace>Lugduni Batavorum
                                 et Hagae Comitum</pubPlace>: apud Johannem Arnoldum Langerak, P.
                              Gosse, et J. Neaulme; Rutg. Christoph. Alberts, J. Vander Kloot,
                                 <date>1728</date>. URL: <ptr
                                 target="https://books.google.com/books?id=nJVAAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PP9#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                              /></bibl>
                           <bibl xml:id="Burm1731"><abbr type="siglum">Burm. 1731</abbr> =
                                 <title>editio Burmanni</title> = <editor>Burmannus, Petrus (Pieter
                                 Burman)</editor>. <title>Poetae Latini Minores, Tom. I</title>.
                                 <pubPlace>Leidae</pubPlace>: <publisher>apud Conradum Wishoff et
                                 Danielem Goedval</publisher>, <date>1731</date>. URL: <ptr
                                 target="https://books.google.com/books?id=uKZAAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PP9#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                              /></bibl>
                           <bibl xml:id="t"><abbr type="siglum">t</abbr> = <title>ed.
                                 Mitaviensis</title> = <editor>Anonymous</editor>. <title>M. Aurelii
                                 Olympii Nemesiani Eclogae IV et T. Calpurnii Siculi Eclogae VII ad
                                 Nemesianum Carthaginiensem, cum notis selectis Titii, Martelli,
                                 Ulitii, et Petri Burmanni integris.</title>
                              <pubPlace>Mitaviae</pubPlace>: <publisher>apud Jacob. Frider.
                                 Hinzium</publisher>, <date>1774</date>. URL: <ptr
                                 target="https://books.google.com/books?id=eNUpAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PP11#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                              />.</bibl>
                           <bibl xml:id="Wernsd."><abbr type="siglum">Wernsd.</abbr> = <title>ed.
                                 Wernsdorfii</title> = <editor>Wernsdorf, Iohannes
                                 Christianus.</editor>
                              <title>Poetae Latini Minores, Tomus Primus</title>.
                                 <pubPlace>Altenburgi</pubPlace>: <pubPlace>ex officina
                                 Richteria</pubPlace>, <date>1780</date>. URL: <ptr
                                 target="https://books.google.com/books?id=A8w9AAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PR1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                              /></bibl>
                           <bibl xml:id="Beck"><abbr type="siglum">Beck</abbr> = <editor>Beck,
                                 Christian Daniel</editor>. <title>T. Calpurnii Siculi Eclogae
                                 XI</title>. <pubPlace>Lipsiae</pubPlace>: <publisher>in libraria
                                 Weidmannia</publisher>, <date>1803</date>. URL: <ptr
                                 target="https://books.google.com/books?id=w6QBAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PR2#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                              /></bibl>
                           <bibl xml:id="Glaeser"><abbr type="siglum">Glaeser</abbr> =
                                 <editor>Glaeser, C. E.</editor>
                              <title>T. Calpurnii Siculi Eclogae</title>.
                                 <pubPlace>Gottingae</pubPlace>: <publisher>sumptibus
                                 Dieterichianis</publisher>, <date>1842</date>. URL: <ptr
                                 target="https://books.google.com/books?id=4sdEAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PP5#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                              /></bibl>
                           <bibl xml:id="Baehr."><abbr type="siglum">Baehr.</abbr> = ed. Baehrensii
                              = <editor>Baehrens, Aemilius</editor>. <title>Poetae Latini Minores,
                                 Volumen III</title>. <pubPlace>Lipsiae</pubPlace>: <publisher>in
                                 aedibus B. G. Teubneri</publisher>, 1881. URL: <ptr
                                 target="https://books.google.com/books?id=CjUOAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                              /></bibl>
                           <listBibl xml:id="Schenkl">
                              <head>utriusque edition. Schenkl. consensus</head>
                              <bibl xml:id="Schenkl1"><abbr type="siglum">Schenkl<hi rend="super"
                                       >1</hi></abbr> = <editor>Schenkl, Henricus</editor>.
                                    <title>Calpurnii et Nemesiani Bucolica</title>.
                                    <pubPlace>Lipsiae</pubPlace>: sumptus fecit G. Freytag,
                                    <date>1885</date>. URL <ptr
                                    target="https://books.google.com/books?id=kuVGAQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PR1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                                 /></bibl>
                              <bibl xml:id="Schenkl2"><abbr type="siglum">Schenkl<hi rend="super"
                                       >2</hi></abbr> = <editor>Schenkl, Henricus</editor>.
                                    <title>T. Calpurni Siculi Bucolica</title> in <ref
                                    target="Postgate1905">Postgate 1905</ref>: 197–205. URL: <ptr
                                    target="https://books.google.com/books?id=_DMOAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=RA1-PA194#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                                 /></bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                           <bibl xml:id="Keene"><abbr type="siglum">Keene</abbr> = <editor>Keene,
                                 Charles Haines</editor>. <title>The Eclogues of Calpurnius Siculus
                                 and M. Aurelius Olympius Nemesianus</title>.
                                 <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>: <publisher>Bell</publisher>, 1887.
                              URL: <ptr
                                 target="https://archive.org/details/ecloguesofcalpur00calpuoft"
                              /></bibl>
                           <bibl xml:id="Giarratano"><abbr type="siglum">Giarratano</abbr> =
                                 <editor>Giarratano, Caesar</editor>. <title>Calpurnii et Nemesiani
                                 Bucolica</title>. <pubPlace>Neapoli</pubPlace>: apud Detken et
                              Rocholl, <date>1910</date>.</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                     </egXML>

                     <p>If it is necessary to group two or more editions together (e.g., first and
                        second editions), another <gi>listBibl</gi> should enclose the group:</p>

                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <listBibl>
                           <head>Modern Editions</head>
                           <listBibl xml:id="i">
                              <head><abbr type="siglum">i</abbr> = utriusque ed. Florent.
                                 consensus</head>
                              <bibl xml:id="i1"><abbr type="siglum">i<hi rend="super">1</hi></abbr>
                                 = <editor>Anonymous</editor>. <title>editio Florentina
                                    prior</title>. <pubPlace>Florentiae</pubPlace>:
                                    <publisher>Philippi de Giunta</publisher>, <date>1504</date>.
                                 URL: <ptr
                                    target="https://books.google.com/books?id=LVJmAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PP7#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                                 /></bibl>
                              <bibl xml:id="i2"><abbr type="siglum">i<hi rend="super">2</hi></abbr>
                                 = <editor>Anonymous</editor>. <title>editio Florentina
                                    posterior</title> = Titius, Robertus. <title>M. Aurelii Olympii
                                    Nemesiani Carthaginiensis, T. Calphurnii Siculi
                                 Bucolica</title>. <pubPlace>Florentiae</pubPlace>: <publisher>apud
                                    Philippum Iunctam</publisher>, <date>1590</date>. URL: <ptr
                                    target="https://books.google.com/books?id=9SEvnoZgKe4C&amp;pg=PR1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                                 /></bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                           <listBibl xml:id="l">
                              <head><abbr type="siglum">l</abbr> = utriusque ed. Ald.
                                 consensus</head>
                              <bibl xml:id="l1"><abbr type="siglum">l<hi rend="super">1</hi></abbr>
                                 = <editor>Anonymous</editor>. <title>editio Aldina prior</title>.
                                    <pubPlace>Venetiis</pubPlace>: <publisher>in aedibus Aldi, et
                                    Andreae Soceri</publisher>
                                 <date>1518</date>. URL: <ptr
                                    target="http://gateway.proquest.com/openurl?url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;res_dat=xri:eurobo:&amp;rft_dat=xri:eurobo:rec:ita-bnc-ald-00000030-001"
                                 /></bibl>
                              <bibl xml:id="l2"><abbr type="siglum">l<hi rend="super">2</hi></abbr>
                                 = <editor>Anonymous</editor>. <title>editio Aldina
                                    posterior</title>. <pubPlace>Venetiis</pubPlace>: <publisher>in
                                    aedibus heredum Aldi Manutii, et Andreae Soceri</publisher>,
                                    <date>1519</date>. URL: <ptr
                                    target="https://books.google.com/books?id=EYg6AAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                                 /></bibl>
                           </listBibl>
                        </listBibl>
                     </egXML>
                  </div>
                  <!-- End of section on modern editions -->
               </div>
               <!-- End of section on editions in general -->

               <!-- Bibliography: Other -->

               <div xml:id="bibliography-other">
                  <head>Other Sources</head>

                  <p>Bibliographical information for items other than editions should gathered in a
                     general bibliography (using <gi>listBibl</gi>), formatted according to the most
                     recent edition of <ref target="#Chicago"><hi rend="italic">The Chicago Manual
                           of Style</hi></ref>, and presented in alphabetical order.</p>

                  <p>The following sections provide instructions for encoding different types of
                     resources commonly found in the bibliographies of critical editions.</p>

                  <div xml:id="bibliography-other-books">
                     <head>Books</head>

                     <p>The following information about books, commentaries, monographs, collections
                        of essays, etc., should be encoded:</p>

                     <p>
                        <specList>
                           <specDesc key="bibl"/>
                           <specDesc key="abbr"/>
                           <specDesc key="author"/>
                           <specDesc key="editor"/>
                           <specDesc key="title"/>
                           <specDesc key="pubPlace"/>
                           <specDesc key="publisher"/>
                           <specDesc key="date"/>
                           <specDesc key="ptr"/>
                        </specList>
                     </p>

                     <list>
                        <item><gi>bibl</gi> (bibliographic citation) has <att>xml:id</att> with the
                           machine-readable abbreviation for the book. It contains the following
                           bibliographical information about the book: <list>
                              <item><gi>abbr</gi> (abbreviation) contains the human-readable
                                 abbreviation for the record, i.e., how the book is referred to in
                                 the apparatus criticus.</item>
                              <item><gi>author</gi> contains the name of the author in the form
                                 "Last name, First name," if known. If the name is in Latin, it
                                 should not be translated. If the name is not known, <gi>author</gi>
                                 should contain the word "Anonymous."</item>
                              <item><gi>title</gi> contains either the name by which the edition is
                                 commonly known (e.g., <foreign xml:lang="lat">editio
                                    Romana</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="lat">editio
                                    Aldina</foreign>) and/or the actual title of the edition.</item>
                              <item><gi>pubPlace</gi> (place of publication) contains the name of
                                 the place where the edition was published, as it appears on the
                                 title page (e.g., Lipsiae instead of Leipzig). If the place is
                                 unknown, the value should be "s.l." (<foreign xml:lang="lat">sine
                                    loco</foreign>). If the place is known, but not explicitly
                                 printed in the edition, the place name should be enclosed in square
                                 brackets.</item>
                              <item><gi>publisher</gi> contains the name of the publisher, as it
                                 appears on the title page. If the publisher's name is unknown, the
                                 value should be "s.n." (<foreign xml:lang="lat">sine
                                    nomine</foreign>). If the publisher is known, but not explicitly
                                 printed in the edition, the publisher's name should be enclosed in
                                 square brackets.</item>
                              <item><gi>date</gi> contains the date in arabic numerals (e.g., 1504,
                                 not MDIV or CIↃIↃIV). If the date is unknown, the value should be
                                 "s.d." (<foreign xml:lang="lat">sine die</foreign>). If the date is
                                 known, but not explicitly printed in the edition, the date should
                                 be enclosed in square brackets.</item>
                              <item><gi>ptr</gi> (pointer) has <att>target</att> with the URL of a
                                 digital copy of the edition, if one exists.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>

                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <bibl xml:id="Haupt1854"><abbr type="siglum">Haupt 1854</abbr>.
                              <author>Haupt, Moriz</author>. <title>De Carminibus Bucolicis
                              Calpurnii et Nemesiani</title>. <pubPlace>Berolini</pubPlace>:
                              <publisher>Typis Academicis</publisher>, <date>1854</date>. URL: <ptr
                              target="https://books.google.com/books?id=8SwUAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PP5#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                           />.</bibl>
                     </egXML>
                     <p>This will be rendered as follows: <hi rend="bold">Haupt 1854</hi> = Haupt,
                        Moriz. <hi rend="italic">De Carminibus Bucolicis Calpurnii et
                        Nemesiani</hi>. Berolini: Typis Academics, 1854. URL:
                        https://books.google.com/books?id=8SwUAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PP5#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false</p>
                  </div>
                  <!-- End of sub-section on books -->

                  <!-- Bibliography: Articles -->

                  <div xml:id="bibliography-other-articles">
                     <head>Articles</head>

                     <p>As with other items in the bibliography, articles in journals and
                        periodicals should be formatted according to the latest edition of <ref
                           target="#Chicago"><hi rend="italic">The Chicago Manual of
                           Style</hi></ref>. The minimum required encoding for articles is as
                        follows:</p>
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <bibl xml:id="Lucas"><abbr type="siglum">Lucas</abbr> = Lucas, Hans. "Zu
                           Calpurnius." Wiener Studien 22 (1901): 139–40. URL:
                           https://books.google.com/books?id=gbmMVZEcoGMC&amp;pg=PA139#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false.</bibl>
                     </egXML>

                     <p>However, it is strongly recommended to encode more details.</p>

                     <p>
                        <specList>
                           <specDesc key="bibl"/>
                           <specDesc key="abbr"/>
                           <specDesc key="author"/>
                           <specDesc key="title"/>
                           <specDesc key="date"/>
                           <specDesc key="ptr"/>

                        </specList>
                     </p>

                     <list>
                        <item><gi>bibl</gi> (bibliographic citation) has <att>xml:id</att> with the
                           machine-readable abbreviation for the book. It contains the following
                           bibliographical information about the book: <list>
                              <item><gi>abbr</gi> (abbreviation) contains the human-readable
                                 abbreviation for the record, i.e., how the article is referred to
                                 in the apparatus criticus.</item>
                              <item><gi>author</gi> contains the name of the author in the form
                                 "Last name, First name."</item>
                              <item><gi>title</gi> with <att>level</att>="a" contains the title of
                                 the article. Quotation marks for the title should be outside of
                                    <gi>title</gi> (e.g., "&lt;title&gt;Article
                                 Title&lt;/title&gt;", not &lt;title&gt;"Article
                                 Title"&lt;/title&gt;).</item>
                              <item><gi>title</gi> with <att>level</att>="j" contains the title of
                                 the journal or periodical.</item>
                              <item><gi>biblScope</gi> (scope of bibliographic reference) is used
                                 with <att>unit</att> to indicate details of publication: <list>
                                    <item><att>unit</att>="volume" contains the volume number of the
                                       journal in which the article has been published.</item>
                                    <item><att>unit</att>="page" contains the inclusive pages where
                                       the article may be found.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item><gi>date</gi> contains the year of publication.</item>
                              <item><gi>ptr</gi> with <att>target</att> provide the URL of a digital
                                 copy of the article, if available.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>

                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <bibl xml:id="Lucas"><abbr type="siglum">Lucas</abbr> = <author>Lucas,
                              Hans</author>. "<title level="a">Zu Calpurnius</title>." <title
                              level="j">Wiener Studien</title>
                           <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope> (<date>1901</date>): <biblScope
                              unit="page">139–40</biblScope>. URL: <ptr
                              target="https://books.google.com/books?id=gbmMVZEcoGMC&amp;pg=PA139#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                           />.</bibl>
                     </egXML>

                     <div xml:id="bibliography-other-articles-reviews">
                        <head>Reviews</head>
                        <p>A review of an edition or other work should be handled in the same way as
                           a journal article, with the exception that the title should begin with
                           the words "Review of" followed by the title of the work being
                           reviewed.</p>

                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                           <bibl xml:id="Jacoby"><abbr type="siglum">Jacoby</abbr> = <author>Jacoby,
                                 Karl</author>. <title level="a">Review of 'Calpurnii et Nemesiani
                                 Bucolica recensuit Henricus Schenkl, Lipsiae, G. Freytag, Pragae,
                                 F. Tempsky, 1885'</title>. <title level="j">Wochenschrift für
                                 klassiche Philologie</title>
                              <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope> (<date>1886</date>): <biblScope
                                 unit="page">1287–94</biblScope>. URL: <ptr
                                 target="https://books.google.de/books?id=q5blAAAAMAAJ&amp;hl=de&amp;pg=RA7-PA41#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                              />.</bibl>
                        </egXML>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <!-- End of section on articles -->
               </div>
               <!-- End of section "Other" -->

               <!-- Bibliography: List of Scholars -->

               <div xml:id="bibliography-list-of-scholars">
                  <head>List of Scholars</head>

                  <p>Occasionally it is necessary to refer to a scholar whose unpublished work has
                     been quoted or paraphrased elsewhere. For example, editors often cite Heinsius'
                     unpublished conjectures, found in books in his own library. But "Heins." does
                     not help a reader find more information, which is why the bibliography of an
                     LDLT edition includes a list of scholars mentioned by name in the edition, with
                     information about where to find more information, if it is available.</p>
                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="listPerson"/>
                        <specDesc key="person"/>
                        <specDesc key="abbr"/>
                        <specDesc key="persName"/>
                        <specDesc key="forename"/>
                        <specDesc key="surname"/>
                        <specDesc key="addname"/>
                        <specDesc key="ref"/>
                        <specDesc key="note"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>

                  <list>
                     <item><gi>listPerson</gi> with <att>xml:id</att>="bibliography-scholars" groups
                        the information identifying the scholars.</item>
                     <item><gi>person</gi> groups information about an individual. It has a
                        machine-readable siglum in <att>xml:id</att> as described in the section
                           "<ref target="#bibliography-sigla">Human- and Machine-Readable Sigla,
                           Symbols, and Abbreviations</ref>."</item>
                     <item><gi>persName</gi> (personal name) groups the information about an
                        individuals's name. For identification purposes, it is helpful, but not
                        required, to use <att>ref</att> with the <ref target="https://viaf.org"
                           >Virtual International Authorify File (VIAF)</ref> permalink for that
                        person. The following information is contained by <gi>persName</gi>
                        <list>
                           <item><gi>abbr</gi> with <att>type</att>="siglum" contains the name or
                              abbreviated name used to refer to the person in the edition (e.g.,
                              Heins.), as described in the section "<ref
                                 target="#bibliography-sigla">Human- and Machine-Readable Sigla,
                                 Symbols, and Abbreviations</ref>."</item>
                           <item><gi>forename</gi> contains the scholar's first and middle names
                              (middle name optional), or initials, of the scholar. A separate
                                 <gi>forename</gi> should be used for the first and middle
                              names.</item>
                           <item><gi>surname</gi> contains the scholar's last name.</item>
                           <item><gi>addname</gi> (additional name) contains an additional or
                              alternate name by which a scholar is known. If a scholars is commonly
                              known by a Latinized form of his or her name, that name should be
                              inserted in <gi>addname</gi>.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item><gi>note</gi> contains further information about the nature of the
                        citation (e.g., "personal correspondence with editor"), with <gi>ref</gi>
                        (reference) containing a reference to the entry in the bibliography that has
                        citations of the scholar. <att>target</att> with the xml:id of that entry
                        will point the reader to that entry.</item>
                  </list>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <person xml:id="Heins.">
                        <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/24651364">
                           <abbr type="siglum">Heins.</abbr> = <forename>Nicolaus</forename>
                           <surname>Heinsius</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <note>Cited in <ref target="#Burm1731">Burman 1731</ref>.</note>
                     </person>
                  </egXML>

                  <p>These references will be rendered on a display and in print as follows:</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>Scholars Cited in this Edition</head>
                     <item><hi rend="bold">Heins.</hi> = Nicolaus Heinsius. Cited in <ref
                           target="#Burm1731">Burman 1731</ref>.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <!-- End of section on list of scholars -->
            </div>
            <!-- End of section on sources -->
         </div>
         <!-- End of section on bibliography -->

         <!-- Begin section on edition text -->

         <div xml:id="edition-text">
            <head>Edition Text</head>

            <p>The edition text corresponds to the text printed "above the line" of the critical
               apparatus in a traditional edition. It is composed of lemmata, that is, text judged
               by the editor to be authentic, accurate, and/or authoritative.</p>

            <p>There may be more than one authoritative version of a text, depending on the text
               and/or the approach adopted by the editor. Authors sometimes edit and revise their
               work over time. Scribes often record the version of the text that makes sense in
               their context. Scholars and other readers offer conjectures for problematic passages.
               But an editor must make decisions about the text an edition presents to readers.
               Those decisions are part of the editor's argument about the text, and they are on
               display in the official edition text in its initial state.</p>

            <p>"Initial state" is an important phrase. Since the digital version of an LDLT allows
               readers to swap readings from the critical apparatus into the main text, it is
               possible to encounter many versions of the text in one viewing of it, but the
               official edition text in its default initial state (i.e., what is displayed when the
               edition is opened for the first time) is the starting point for those
               interactions.</p>

            <p>This section establishes guidelines for encoding the information typically found in
               the edition text.</p>

            <div xml:id="edition-text-prose">
               <head>Prose</head>

               <p>The aim of this section is to provide guidance for marking up the structure of
                  prose texts, using the generic model of book, chapter, and paragraph for the main
                  components of a work. Individual texts may have different structures, so editors
                  should consult with LDLT staff about the best way to encode the structure.</p>

               <p>In a traditional critical edition, numbers are printed in the margin and/or in the
                  text itself. It is often unclear whether the numbers are meant to mark syntactic
                  units, reflect the numbering of pages or sections in a canonical edition, or
                  signify something else entirely. An advantage to semantically encoding the
                  reference scheme is that it makes the scheme's significance explicit. For that
                  reason, a human- and machine-readable reference scheme is essential for an LDLT
                  edition. Moreover, if the structure is not encoded according to these guidelines,
                  search and browse functionality will not be supported.</p>

               <div xml:id="edition-text-prose-structure">
                  <head>Prose: Structure of the Work</head>

                  <p>For an LDLT edition of a prose text, the top-level <gi>div</gi> has the
                        <att>type</att> "edition"; this division contains the entire text of the
                     edition. The next <gi>div</gi> will normally have the <att>type</att>
                     "textpart" with <att>subtype</att> "book" and <att>n</att> to indicate the
                     number of the book.</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <div type="edition">
                        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1">
                           <!-- Text goes here. -->
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </egXML>

                  <p>If a different division scheme is required, editors should consult LDLT
                     staff.</p>
               </div>
               <!-- End of section on prose work structure. -->

               <div xml:id="edition-text-prose-paragraphs">
                  <head>Prose: Structure of Paragraphs</head>

                  <p>The individual sections of a prose work should be encoded as follows:</p>
                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="milestone"/>
                        <specDesc key="p"/>
                        <specDesc key="seg"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>

                  <list>
                     <item><gi>milestone</gi> may be used to mark the sections of a canonical
                        edition, if the current edition uses a different scheme.</item>
                     <item><gi>p</gi> (paragraph) contains the text of a chapter or other basic
                        section in a prose work. <att>n</att> must be used to reflect the numbering
                        scheme of the edition. Note that the TEI Guidelines define the paragraph as
                           <quote
                           source="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html#COPA"
                           >the fundamental organizational unit for all prose texts</quote>. The
                        unique characteristics of some texts may require a different approach. In
                        those cases, editors should work with LDLT staff to identify the best way to
                        encode the text in question.</item>
                     <item><gi>seg</gi> (segment) contains a segment of a paragraph (e.g., a
                        sentence or a more general "section"). If <gi>seg</gi> is used, <att>n</att>
                        must be used to reflect the numbering scheme of the edition.</item>
                  </list>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <div type="edition">
                        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1">
                           <p n="1">
                              <seg n="1">Gallia est omnis divisa in partes tres, quarum unam
                                 incolunt Belgae, aliam Aquitani, tertiam qui ipsorum lingua Celtae,
                                 nostra Galli appellantur.</seg>
                              <seg n="2">Hi omnes lingua, institutis, legibus inter se differunt.
                                 Gallos ab Aquitanis Garumna flumen, a Belgis Matrona et Sequana
                                 dividit.</seg>
                              <seg n="3">Horum omnium fortissimi sunt Belgae, propterea quod a cultu
                                 atque humanitate provinciae longissime absunt, minimeque ad eos
                                 mercatores saepe commeant atque ea quae ad effeminandos animos
                                 pertinent important, proximique sunt Germanis, qui trans Rhenum
                                 incolunt, quibuscum continenter bellum gerunt.</seg>
                              <seg n="4">Qua de causa Helvetii quoque reliquos Gallos virtute
                                 praecedunt, quod fere cotidianis proeliis cum Germanis contendunt,
                                 cum aut suis finibus eos prohibent aut ipsi in eorum finibus bellum
                                 gerunt.</seg>
                              <seg n="5">Eorum una, pars, quam Gallos obtinere dictum est, initium
                                 capit a flumine Rhodano, continetur Garumna flumine, Oceano,
                                 finibus Belgarum, attingit etiam ab Sequanis et Helvetiis flumen
                                 Rhenum, vergit ad septentriones.</seg>
                              <seg n="6">Belgae ab extremis Galliae finibus oriuntur, pertinent ad
                                 inferiorem partem fluminis Rheni, spectant in septentrionem et
                                 orientem solem.</seg>
                              <seg n="7">Aquitania a Garumna flumine ad Pyrenaeos montes et eam
                                 partem Oceani quae est ad Hispaniam pertinet; spectat inter occasum
                                 solis et septentriones.</seg>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </egXML>

                  <p>That text will be rendered as follows:</p>

                  <p>Liber I</p>

                  <p><hi rend="bold">1</hi>
                     <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>Gallia est omnis divisa in partes tres, quarum
                     unam incolunt Belgae, aliam Aquitani, tertiam qui ipsorum lingua Celtae, nostra
                     Galli appellantur. <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>Hi omnes lingua, institutis,
                     legibus inter se differunt. Gallos ab Aquitanis Garumna flumen, a Belgis
                     Matrona et Sequana dividit. <hi rend="superscript">3</hi>Horum omnium
                     fortissimi sunt Belgae, propterea quod a cultu atque humanitate provinciae
                     longissime absunt, minimeque ad eos mercatores saepe commeant atque ea quae ad
                     effeminandos animos pertinent important, proximique sunt Germanis, qui trans
                     Rhenum incolunt, quibuscum continenter bellum gerunt. <hi rend="superscript"
                        >4</hi>Qua de causa Helvetii quoque reliquos Gallos virtute praecedunt, quod
                     fere cotidianis proeliis cum Germanis contendunt, cum aut suis finibus eos
                     prohibent aut ipsi in eorum finibus bellum gerunt. <hi rend="superscript"
                        >5</hi>Eorum una, pars, quam Gallos obtinere dictum est, initium capit a
                     flumine Rhodano, continetur Garumna flumine, Oceano, finibus Belgarum, attingit
                     etiam ab Sequanis et Helvetiis flumen Rhenum, vergit ad septentriones. <hi
                        rend="superscript">6</hi>Belgae ab extremis Galliae finibus oriuntur,
                     pertinent ad inferiorem partem fluminis Rheni, spectant in septentrionem et
                     orientem solem. <hi rend="superscript">7</hi>Aquitania a Garumna flumine ad
                     Pyrenaeos montes et eam partem Oceani quae est ad Hispaniam pertinet; spectat
                     inter occasum solis et septentriones.</p>
               </div>
               <!-- End of section on prose paragraph structure -->
            </div>
            <!-- End of section on prose -->

            <div xml:id="edition-text-verse">
               <head>Verse</head>

               <p>The <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/VE.html"
                     >verse module</ref> of the TEI Guidelines offers many possibilities for marking
                  up various aspects of prosody, but the LDLT is primarily concerned with the <ref
                     target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html#COVE">core
                     tags</ref> for encoding the structure of verse texts. This does not mean that
                  editors and others should avoid using the verse module. It means only that the
                  LDLT does not provide functionality for that level of detail.</p>

               <div xml:id="edition-text-verse-structure">
                  <head>Verse: Structure of the Collection</head>

                  <p>For an LDLT edition of a verse text, the top-level <gi>div</gi> has the
                        <att>type</att> "edition"; this division contains the entire text of the
                     edition. The next <gi>div</gi> will normally have the <att>type</att>
                     "textpart" with <att>subtype</att> "book" and <att>n</att> to indicate the
                     number of the book. <gi>div</gi> with <att>type</att>="poem" contains the parts
                     of a single poem (e.g., stanzas or lines). If there is more than one poem in a
                     book, <att>n</att> should be used to number the poems. <att>met</att> with the
                     name of the meter may also be used, if the editor wishes to identify the meter.
                     If a different division scheme is required, editors should consult the DLL
                     staff.</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <div type="edition">
                        <div type="textpart" subtype="book">
                           <div type="poem" n="1" met="First Asclepiadean">
                              <!-- Text of poem goes here -->
                           </div>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </egXML>
               </div>

               <div xml:id="edition-text-verse-lines">
                  <head>Verse: Structure of a Poem</head>

                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="div"/>
                        <specDesc key="lg"/>
                        <specDesc key="l"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>

                  <list>
                     <item><gi>lg</gi> (line group) groups one or more verse lines that form a
                        stanza or a couplet; <att>type</att> may be used to identify the grouping
                        (e.g., "stanza" or "couplet").</item>
                     <item><gi>l</gi> (line) contains the text of a single line of verse, with
                           <att>n</att> and the number of the line.</item>
                  </list>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <div type="book" n="2">
                        <div type="poem" n="1" met="Alcaic Strophe">
                           <lg type="stanza">
                              <l n="1">Motum ex Metello consule civicum</l>
                              <l n="2">bellique causas et vitia et modos</l>
                              <l n="3">ludumque Fortunae gravisque</l>
                              <l n="4">principum amicitias et arma</l>
                           </lg>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
            </div>
            <!-- End of section on verse -->

            <div xml:id="edition-text-foreign-languages">
               <head>Text in Languages Other than Latin</head>

               <p>If text in languages other than Latin is encoded, language becomes available as a
                  criterion for searching and filtering.</p>

               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="foreign"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>

               <list>
                  <item><gi>foreign</gi> contains text in any language other than Latin.</item>
                  <item><att>xml:lang</att> identifies the language by <ref
                        target="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/php/English_list.php">ISO
                        639-2 code</ref>.</item>
               </list>

               <p>For example, authors of Latin texts often use Greek words and phrases, as
                  Macrobius does at <bibl><title>Saturnalia</title> 1.17.64</bibl>: <quote>Ἀπόλλωνα
                     Διδυμαῖον vocant, quod geminam speciem sui niminis praefert ipse inluminando
                     formandoque lunam</quote>. That should be encoded as follows:</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <p><foreign xml:lang="grc">Ἀπόλλωνα Διδυμαῖον</foreign> vocant, quod geminam
                     speciem sui numinis praefert ipse inluminando formandoque lunam.</p>
               </egXML>
            </div>


            <div xml:id="edition-text-speech">
               <head>Speech</head>

               <p>This section discusses how to encode the following kinds of speech:<list>
                     <item>direct speech</item>
                     <item>dialogue in a play or other setting</item>
                  </list>
               </p>

               <div xml:id="edition-text-speech-direct-speech">
                  <head>Direct Speech</head>
                  <p>Quotation of direct speech may be handled in two ways: with punctuation or with
                     semantic markup.</p>

                  <p>If an editor wishes to use standard punctuation to represent direct speech, the
                     current edition of <ref target="#Chicago"><hi rend="italic">The Chicago Manual
                           of Style</hi></ref> should be the guide.</p>

                  <p>The following rules apply to the semantic markup of direct speech:</p>

                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="said"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>

                  <p><gi>said</gi> (speech) contains text spoken by real people or fictional
                     characters.</p>
                  <p><att>who</att> identifies the speaker (optional). Values for <att>who</att>
                     should be recorded elsewhere (e.g., preface, appendix) in a <gi>list</gi> with
                        <att>type</att>="speakers". They can also be incorporated into
                        <gi>listPerson</gi> as described below in the section "<ref
                        target="#edition-text-people">People</ref>."</p>

                  <p>For example, Julius Caesar's famous words before crossing the Rubicon, as
                     reported by Suetonius, should be encoded as follows:</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <p>tunc Caesar, <said who="#Caesar">eatur,</said> inquit, <said who="#Caesar"
                           >quo deorum ostenta et inimicorum iniquitas uocat: iacta alea
                           esto.</said></p>
                  </egXML>

                  <p><gi>said</gi> may be nested inside <gi>said</gi> to indication quotation within
                     a quotation.</p>
               </div>

               <div xml:id="edition-text-speech-dialogue">
                  <head>Dialogue</head>

                  <p>Texts that feature interlocutors (e.g., drama, dialogue) should be encoded
                     using <gi>sp</gi> and <gi>speaker</gi>.</p>

                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="sp"/>
                        <specDesc key="speaker"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>

                  <list>
                     <item><gi>sp</gi> (speech) groups elements related to a person or character's
                        speech.</item>
                     <item><att>who</att> is used with <gi>sp</gi> to identify the speaker.</item>
                     <item><gi>speaker</gi> contains a human-readable label identifying the person
                        or character speaking the text.</item>
                  </list>

                  <p>These features can be used in verse and prose texts:</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <sp who="Corydon">
                        <speaker>C.</speaker>
                        <l n="1">Nondum Solis equos declinis mitigat aestas,</l>
                        <l n="2">quamvis et madidis incumbant prela racemis</l>
                        <l n="3">et spument rauco ferventia musta susurro.</l>
                        <l n="4">cernis ut ecce pater quas tradidit, Ornyte, vaccae</l>
                        <l n="5">molle sub hirsuta latus explicuere genista?</l>
                        <l n="6">nos quoque vicinis cur non succedimus umbris?</l>
                        <l n="7">torrida cur solo defendimus ora galero?</l>
                     </sp>
                  </egXML>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <sp who="Laelius">
                        <speaker>Laelius</speaker>
                        <p>Atqui, Cato, gratissimum nobis, ut etiam pro Scipione pollicear, feceris,
                           si, quoniam speramus, volumus quidem certe, senes fieri, multo ante a te
                           didicerimus quibus facillime rationibus ingravescentem aetatem ferre
                           possimus.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp who="Cato">
                        <speaker>Cato</speaker>
                        <p>Faciam vero, Laeli, praesertim si utrique vestrum, ut dicis, gratum
                           futurum est.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="edition-text-quotation">
               <head>Quotation of Literature</head>

               <p>Quotations of literature should be encoded according to the guidelines set forth
                  in the section "<ref target="#apparatus-fontium">Apparatus Fontium</ref>."</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="edition-text-people">
               <head>People</head>

               <p>It can be useful to encode names of people mentioned in the text of an edition,
                  whether to facilitate the creation of an index or to support digital search
                  functionality. It is up to the editor to decide which names, if any, should be
                  encoded. If names are to be encoded, the following guidelines should be
                  observed.</p>

               <p>
                  <specDesc key="listPerson"/>
                  <specDesc key="person"/>
                  <specDesc key="persName"/>
               </p>

               <list>
                  <item><gi>listPerson</gi> (list of persons) contains a list of names of people
                     mentioned in the text.</item>
                  <item><gi>person</gi> contains the nominative form of the name of a person
                     mentioned in the text. It must also have <att>xml:id</att> with a
                     machine-readable version of the name to serve as a reference for instances of
                     the name in the text.</item>
                  <item><gi>persName</gi> contains the name of a person as it is mentioned in the
                     edition text, regardless of case.</item>
                  <item><gi>note</gi> contains further identifying information about the person
                     (e.g., dates, the ID number in a reference work or prosopography), if the name
                     is not enough to make the distinction.</item>
               </list>

               <p>Since names may appear in different cases in the text, it is vital to have a
                  reference list of names in the nominative form. While working on a text, editors
                  should establish a working list of names, in an XML document, using
                     <gi>listPerson</gi>, <gi>person</gi>, and <gi>persName</gi> as described
                  above:</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <listPerson>
                     <person xml:id="Absyrtus">
                        <persName>Absyrtus</persName>
                        <note>Medeae frater</note>
                     </person>
                     <person xml:id="Accius">
                        <persName>Accius</persName>
                        <note>Poeta</note>
                     </person>
                     <person xml:id="Actaeon">
                        <persName>Actaeon</persName>
                     </person>
                  </listPerson>
               </egXML>

               <p>Where names of people in the reference list appear in the edition text, they
                  should be encoded with <gi>persName</gi> and <att>ref</att> pointing to the
                     <att>xml:id</att> of the person.</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <l n="6">constat ab <persName ref="#Absyrtus">Absyrti</persName> caede fuisse
                     loco.</l>
               </egXML>

               <p>It is also possible to encode indirect references to people:</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <l n="9">conscia percussit meritorum pectora <persName ref="#Medea"
                        >Colchis</persName></l>
               </egXML>
            </div>
            <!-- End of section on people -->

            <div xml:id="edition-text-places">
               <head>Places</head>
               <p>Place names, and the names of peoples, can be encoded in LDLT editions to
                  facilitate creation of an index or to assist readers in identifying the places
                  mentioned in the text. If it is desirable to encode this information, the
                  following guidelines should be followed.</p>

               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="placeName"/>
                     <specDesc key="orgName"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>

               <list>
                  <item><gi>placeName</gi> contains the name of a place, with <att>ref</att> and the
                     canonical Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) for it at <ref
                        target="http://pleiades.stoa.org">Pleiades</ref> or some other standard
                     source of URI's for place names.</item>
                  <item><gi>orgName</gi> (organization name) contains the name of the inhabitants of
                     a place, with <att>ref</att> and the canonical Uniform Resource Identifier
                     (URI) for the place at <ref target="http://pleiades.stoa.org"
                     >Pleiades</ref>.</item>
               </list>

               <p>Only the first reference in a section to a place or its inhabitants needs to be
                  encoded for indexing purposes, but it is up to the editor to decide which
                  references to encode. The following example from Caesar's <bibl><title>de bello
                        Gallico</title></bibl> demonstrates how to encode place names and
                  organization names.</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <p><placeName ref="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/993">Gallia</placeName> est
                     omnis divisa in partes tres, quarum unam incolunt <orgName
                        ref="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/79326">Belgae</orgName>, aliam <orgName
                        ref="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/246175">Aquitani</orgName>, tertiam qui
                     ipsorum lingua <orgName ref="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/993"
                        >Celtae</orgName>, nostra <orgName ref="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/993"
                        >Galli</orgName> appellantur. Hi omnes lingua, institutis, legibus inter se
                     differunt. Gallos ab Aquitanis <placeName
                        ref="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/138369">Garumna</placeName> flumen, a
                     Belgis <placeName ref="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/109147"
                        >Matrona</placeName> et <placeName
                        ref="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/109341">Sequana</placeName> dividit.
                     Horum omnium fortissimi sunt Belgae, propterea quod a cultu atque humanitate
                     provinciae longissime absunt, minimeque ad eos mercatores saepe commeant atque
                     ea quae ad effeminandos animos pertinent important, proximique sunt <orgName
                        ref="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/20468">Germanis</orgName>, qui trans
                        <placeName ref="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/393483">Rhenum</placeName>
                     incolunt, quibuscum continenter bellum gerunt. Qua de causa <orgName
                        ref="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/177534">Helvetii</orgName> quoque
                     reliquos Gallos virtute praecedunt, quod fere cotidianis proeliis cum Germanis
                     contendunt, cum aut suis finibus eos prohibent aut ipsi in eorum finibus bellum
                     gerunt. Eorum una, pars, quam Gallos obtinere dictum est, initium capit a
                     flumine <placeName ref="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/148168"
                        >Rhodano</placeName>, continetur Garumna flumine, <placeName
                        ref="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/845">Oceano</placeName>, finibus
                     Belgarum, attingit etiam ab Sequanis et Helvetiis flumen Rhenum, vergit ad
                     septentriones. Belgae ab extremis Galliae finibus oriuntur, pertinent ad
                     inferiorem partem fluminis Rheni, spectant in septentrionem et orientem solem.
                        <placeName ref="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/981505"
                        >Aquitania</placeName> a Garumna flumine ad <placeName
                        ref="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/246582">Pyrenaeos montes</placeName> et
                     eam partem Oceani quae est ad <placeName
                        ref="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/1027">Hispaniam</placeName> pertinet;
                     spectat inter occasum solis et septentriones.</p>
               </egXML>
            </div>
            <!-- End of section on places -->

            <div xml:id="edition-text-symbols">
               <head>Symbols Commonly Used in the Text of a Critical Edition</head>

               <p>Over time, certain typographical conventions have become standard for representing
                  emendations, lacunae, omissions, gaps, editorial deletions, and other information.
                  The present guidelines observe the standards as described by <ref target="#West"
                     >West</ref> (80–81), but they call for semantically encoding them instead of
                  simply inserting the various punctuation marks and other symbols that represent
                  complex information. The encoding will still produce the standard symbols, but the
                  information they represent will be explicit and in a form readable by humans and
                  machines. That means that it will also be available for processing, querying, and
                  analyzing with digital tools.</p>

               <p>Since most of the standard symbols usually have corresponding annotations in the
                  critical apparatus, the encoding guidelines for many of them can be found in
                  subsections of the guidelines for encoding entries in the critical apparatus. The
                  following list identifies the symbols and points to the guidelines for encoding them:<list>
                     <item>( ) = <ref target="#edition-text-abbreviation-expansion">expansion of an
                           abbreviation</ref></item>
                     <item>a&#x323;b&#x323;c&#x323;d&#x323; = <ref
                           target="#edition-text-uncertain-characters">text uncertainly
                           restored</ref>.</item>
                     <item>&lt; &gt; = <ref target="#apparatus-criticus-conjecture-and-emendation"
                           >text added by conjecture or emendation</ref></item>
                     <item>[ *** ] = <ref target="#apparatus-criticus-lacuna-physical-loss">text
                           lost through physical damage</ref></item>
                     <item>&lt; *** &gt; = <ref target="#apparatus-criticus-lacuna-conjecture"
                           >conjectured lacuna</ref></item>
                     <item>[ ... ] = <ref target="#apparatus-criticus-symbols-known-loss-characters"
                           >known amount of characters lost</ref></item>
                     <item>&#10214; &#10215; = <ref target="#apparatus-criticus-deletions">deletion
                           by a scribe in a witness</ref>.</item>
                     <item>{ } = <ref target="#apparatus-criticus-deletion-editorial">editorial
                           deletion</ref></item>
                     <item>† † = <ref target="#apparatus-criticus-crux">text deemed to be
                           irretrievably corrupt</ref>.</item>
                  </list></p>
            </div>
            <!-- End section on symbols in the main text. -->

            <div xml:id="edition-text-abbreviation-expansion">
               <head>Expansion of Abbreviation</head>

               <p>( ) = An editor expands an abbreviation as an aid to reading or to remove
                  ambiguity. Encoded according to the following guidelines, a digital edition will
                  display the abbreviated forms by default, but a user will be able to toggle
                  between the abbreviated and expanded forms.</p>

               <p>The preface should indicate whether or not abbreviations are expanded.</p>
               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="choice"/>
                     <specDesc key="abbr"/>
                     <specDesc key="ex"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item><gi>expan</gi> (expansion) contains the full expansion of an
                     abbreviation.</item>
                  <item><gi>abbr</gi> (abbreviation) contains the abbreviated part, i.e. the letters
                     actually on the page.</item>
                  <item><gi>ex</gi> (editorial expansion) contains a sequence of letters added by an
                     editor or transcriber when expanding an abbreviation.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <quote>M(arcus) Cicero S(alutem) D(ixit) L(ucio) Lucceio Q(uinti) F(ilio)</quote>
               </p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <p><expan><abbr>M</abbr><ex>arcus</ex></expan> Cicero
                           <expan><abbr>S</abbr><ex>alutem</ex><abbr>D</abbr><ex>ixit</ex></expan>
                     <expan><abbr>L</abbr><ex>ucio</ex></expan> Lucceio
                           <expan><abbr>Q</abbr><ex>uinti</ex></expan>
                     <expan><abbr>F</abbr><ex>ilio</ex></expan></p>
               </egXML>

               <p>Multiple &lt;abbr&gt; elements within a single &lt;expan&gt; compose a single
                  abbreviation between them. For example, e.g. is one abbreviation for the phrase
                  "exempli gratia."</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>e</abbr>
                     <ex>xempli</ex>
                     <abbr>g</abbr>
                     <ex>ratia</ex>
                  </choice>
               </egXML>
            </div>
            <!-- End section on expansion of abbreviations. -->

            <div xml:id="edition-text-uncertain-characters">
               <head>Uncertainly Deciphered Characters</head>

               <p>When an edition is based on a limited number of witnesses, it may be necessary to
                  indicate that characters are difficult to read. The accepted way to do this is
                  with dots underneath the uncertainly deciphered characters.</p>

               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="unclear"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>

               <p><gi>unclear</gi> contains characters, words, or phrases that cannot be transcribed
                  with certainty.</p>

               <p>For example, the entry for <foreign xml:lang="lat">Mensae</foreign> in Lindsay's
                  edition of Festus (157M) has the following uncertainly deciphered text:</p>

               <p>a&#x323;m&#x323;e&#x323; . . . a&#x323;
                  t&#x323;e&#x323;n&#x323;e&#x323;b&#x323;a&#x323;t&#x323;
                  a&#x323;r&#x323;a&#x323;m&#x323; . . . . . . . . . .</p>

               <p>In an LDLT edition, that should be encoded as follows:</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <unclear>ame</unclear>
                  <gap reason="lost" quantity="3" unit="characters"/>
                  <unclear>a tenebat aram</unclear>
                  <gap reason="lost" quantity="10" unit="characters"/>
               </egXML>

            </div>
            <!-- End section on uncertainly deciphered characters. -->

         </div>
         <!-- End section on edition text. -->

         <div xml:id="apparatus-fontium">
            <head>Apparatus Fontium</head>

            <p>An apparatus fontium collects references to texts quoted, cited, or referred to
               indirectly in the text of the edition. This section demonstrates how to encode such
               references so that they will be displayed appropriately in the text and so that
               bibliographical information about them will appear in the apparatus fontium. </p>

            <p>
               <specList>
                  <specDesc key="cit"/>
                  <specDesc key="quote"/>
                  <specDesc key="ref"/>
                  <specDesc key="bibl"/>
               </specList>
            </p>

            <list>
               <item><gi>cit</gi> (cited quotation) contains a quotation (in <gi>quote</gi>) from
                  another source or a reference (in <gi>ref</gi>) to another source, together with
                  bibliographical information about the source (in <gi>bibl</gi>).</item>
               <item><gi>quote</gi> (quotation) contains a phrase or passage attributable to some
                  agency external to the text.</item>
               <item><gi>ref</gi> (reference) contains a reference to a phrase or passage
                  attributable to some agency external to the text.</item>
               <item><gi>bibl</gi> (bibliographic citation) contains the information required to
                  retrieve the source of the quotation or reference. If a digital copy of the source
                  is available, a link can be provided with <gi>ptr</gi>.</item>
            </list>

            <p>Any text in <gi>quote</gi> will be displayed or printed in quotation marks on the
               same line as the rest of the text. Any text in <gi>quote</gi> with
               <att>rend</att>="blockquote" will be displayed or printed on a new line and indented.
               In the latter case, prose and verse text within <gi>quote</gi> should be encoded
               according to the guidelines in the sections "<ref target="#edition-text-prose"
                  >Prose</ref>" and "<ref target="#edition-text-verse">Verse</ref>."</p>

            <p><bibl><author>Macrobius'</author>
                  <title>Saturnalia</title> 3.16.1–5 has examples of block quotations of prose and
                  verse texts, and an inline quotation of a prose text</bibl>. Note that it is also
               an example of <ref target="#edition-text-speech">direct speech</ref>, since the
               entire passage is spoken by a character (Rufius):</p>

            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
               <said who="#Rufius">
                  <p>Nec acipenser, quem maria prodigis nutriunt, illius saeculi delicias evasit; et
                     ut liqueat secundo Punico bello celebre nomen huius piscis fuisse, accipite ut
                     meminerit eius Plautus in fabula quae inscribitur Baccaria ex persona parasiti<cit>
                        <quote rend="blockquote"><!-- Verse quotation to be displayed/printed on new line and indented -->
                           <l>quis est mortalis tanta fortuna adfectus umquam</l>
                           <l>qua ego nunc sum, cuius haec ventri portatur pompa?</l>
                           <l>vel nunc, qui mihi in mari acipenser latuit antehac,</l>
                           <l>cuius ego latus in latebras reddam meis dentibus et manibus.</l>
                        </quote>
                        <bibl>
                           <author>Plautus</author>
                           <title>Baccar.</title> 16–20</bibl>
                     </cit>.</p>
                  <p>et ne vilior sit testis poeta, accipite assertore Cicerone in quo honore fuerit
                     hic piscis apud P. Scipionem Africanum illum et Numantinum, haec sunt in
                     dialogo de fato verba Ciceronis<cit>
                        <quote rend="blockquote"><!-- Prose quotation to be displayed/printed on new line and indented -->
                           <p>nam cum esset apud se ad Lavernium Scipio unaque Pontius adlatus est
                              forte Scipioni acipenser, qui admodum raro capitur, sed est piscis, ut
                              ferunt, in primis nobilis. cum autem Scipio unum et alterum ex his qui
                              eum salutatum venerant invitavisset pluresque etiam invitaturus
                              videretur, in aurem Pontius, <said who="#Pontius">Scipio,</said>
                              inquit, <said who="#Pontius">vide quid agas, acipenser iste paucorum
                                 hominum est.</said></p>
                        </quote>
                        <bibl><author>Cicero</author>
                           <title>De Fato</title> fr. 4</bibl>
                     </cit></p>
                  <p>nec infitias eo temporibus Traiani hunc piscem in magno pretio non fuisse,
                     teste Plinio Secundo, qui in Naturali historia cum de hoc pisce loqueretur sic
                     ait: <cit><!-- Prose quotation to be displayed/printed in line -->
                        <quote>nullo nunc in honore est, quod equidem miror, cum sit rarus
                           inventu.</quote>
                        <bibl><author>Plin.</author>
                           <title>HN</title> 9.60</bibl>.</cit></p>
               </said>
            </egXML>

            <p>In the following example, Duns Scotus has referred to a work by Boethius, but he has
               not quoted it:</p>

            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
               <p>Probatio minoris per <cit><ref>Boethium De
                           Trinitate</ref><bibl><author>Boethius</author>
                        <title>De Trin.</title> c. 4 (ed. R. Peiper 159; PL 64, 1353C)</bibl></cit>:
                  dicit quod septem praedicamenta non dicunt absolutas res, sed tantum
                  respectus.</p>
            </egXML>

            <p>In the edition text, the text would be displayed or printed without interruption
               (i.e., <foreign xml:lang="lat">Probatio minoris per Boethium De Trinitate: dicit quod
                  septem praedicamenta non dicunt absolutas res, sed tantum respectus</foreign>).
               The apparatus fontium would include the following entry: "Boethius <hi rend="italic"
                  >De Trin.</hi> c. 4 (ed. R. Peiper 159; PL 64, 1353C).</p>

            <p>If it is desirable to provide the text of the reference in the apparatus fontium, it
               may be inserted in <gi>quote</gi> after <gi>bibl</gi>:</p>

            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
               <p>Probatio minoris per <cit><ref>Boethium De Trinitate</ref><bibl>Boethius <title>De
                           Trin.</title> c. 4 (ed. R. Peiper 159; PL 64, 1353C)</bibl>: <quote>Iamne
                        patet quae sit differentia praedicationum? Quod aliae quidem quasi rem
                        monstrant, aliae vero quasi circumstantias rei; quodque illa quae ita
                        praedicantur, ut esse aliquid rem ostendant, illa vero ut non esse, sed
                        potius extrinsecus aliquid quodam modo adfigant?</quote></cit>: dicit quod
                  septem praedicamenta non dicunt absolutas res, sed tantum respectus.</p>
            </egXML>

            <p>The text of the quotation will be displayed in the apparatus fontium.</p>
         </div>
         <!-- End section on apparatus fontium -->

         <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus">
            <head>Apparatus Criticus</head>

            <p>This section provides models for handling the different kinds of entries that occur
               in an apparatus criticus. It uses the terminology, elements, and attributes of the
               TEI's module <ref
                  target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html">12 Critical
                  Apparatus</ref>, but it also defines terms and encoding methods specific to LDLT
               editions. It is not an instructional manual for composing an apparatus criticus.
               Rather, this section presents a model for semantically encoding the information to be
               included in the apparatus criticus of an LDLT edition.</p>

            <p>In a digital context, critical editions encoded according to these guidelines will
               have certain interactive features:<list>
                  <item>Readings from manuscripts and other sources can be filtered in or out of the
                     text.</item>
                  <item>Certain types of variant readings (e.g., orthographic variants, conjectures,
                     corrections) can be filtered in or out of the text.</item>
                  <item>A variant reading can be swapped into the text so that it can be viewed
                        <foreign xml:lang="lat">in situ</foreign>.</item>
                  <item>Line transpositions can be activated and viewed in the text.</item>
               </list></p>

            <p>In a printed version, critical editions encoded according to these guidelines will
               have an apparatus criticus in a format familiar from standard critical ediitons.</p>

            <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-concepts-definitions">
               <head>Concepts and Definitions</head>

               <p>The apparatus criticus is where editors assemble the variant readings from
                  witnesses and sources they believe to be important for establishing the text,
                  occasionally with brief comments, bibliographical citations, and palaeographical
                  details. This section defines the terms used in these guidelines.</p>

               <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-concepts-definitions-readings">
                  <head>Readings</head>

                  <p xml:id="reading">In the context of a critical edition, <hi rend="bold"
                        >reading</hi> is the generic term for any unit of information that has
                     meaning in constituting the text of the edition. A critical edition contains
                     two types of reading: lemma and variant.</p>

                  <p xml:id="lemma">A <hi rend="bold">lemma</hi> (pl. lemmata) is a word or phrase
                     (or the absence thereof) judged by the editor to be authentic, accurate, and/or
                     authoritative. It may be attested by documentary sources (e.g., a manuscript,
                     an early edition) or it may be an emendation. Lemmata constitute the text
                     printed in the main portion of a critical edition.</p>

                  <p xml:id="variant">A <hi rend="bold">variant reading</hi> is a word or phrase (or
                     absence thereof) judged by the editor to be unsatisfactory for linguistic
                     and/or stylistic reasons, but of interest for establishing the text. This type
                     of reading is a "variant" insofar as it varies from what the editor has judged
                     to be the lemma. A variant reading may be attested by a manuscript or it may be
                     a conjecture or the result of a correction. By default in LDLT editions,
                     variant readings are displayed or printed in the apparatus criticus. In digital
                     versions, variants can be swapped into the edition text.</p>

                  <p xml:id="emendation">An <hi rend="bold">emendation</hi> is a reading not
                     supported by documentary evidence, but expressly proposed by some person
                     (possibly the editor) and accepted by the editor into the main text of an
                     edition.</p>

                  <p xml:id="conjecture">A <hi rend="bold">conjecture</hi> is a reading not
                     supported by known documentary evidence, but proposed by some person and
                     determined by an editor to be worthy of consideration for establishing the
                     text, but not to be printed in the main text of the edition.</p>

                  <p xml:id="correction"><hi rend="bold">Correction</hi> describes any attempt by
                     the original copyist or some other hand to alter a witness' reading, regardless
                     of whether the result of the correction matches the lemma of the current
                     edition. It is a matter of perspective whether or not the result of a
                     correction is "correct." Opinions can differ from editor to editor about what
                     the "correct" reading is, which is why having more than one critical edition of
                     a text is not necessarily redundant. Similarly, copyists and other users of
                     manuscripts have their own idea of what the "correct" reading is. The original
                     copyist might notice a slip of the pen in his own work and correct it. A later
                     hand might correct a mistake missed by the copyist. Another reader comparing
                     two manuscripts might "correct" one of them based on the other's reading. In
                     these cases and others, the motivation is to correct what is perceived to be
                     incorrect. For all of these reasons, "correction" is used in these guidelines
                     to refer to an attempt to alter existing text so that it conforms to some
                     perceived standard, whether or not that standard matches the editor's view of
                     what the correct reading is.</p>

                  <p>The next two sections discuss where readings are found, i.e., in witnesses and
                     sources.</p>
               </div>
               <!-- End of section on readings -->

               <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-concepts-definitions-witness">
                  <head>Witnesses</head>

                  <p>A <hi rend="bold">witness</hi> may be a manuscript, the individual hands that
                     wrote in a manuscript, or an early printed edition (e.g., <foreign
                        xml:lang="lat">editio princeps</foreign>) that may preserve the readings of
                     a single manuscript.</p>

                  <p xml:id="hands">The physical object referred to as a manuscript is not by itself
                     a witness. Rather, it preserves a record of the activities of the copyist(s),
                     rubricator(s), corrector(s), and/or other annotator(s) who wrote on its pages,
                     each of whom might be a witness to a different exemplar. At the very least,
                     they represent different perceptions of the same exemplar. By synechdoche,
                     those people are referred to as "hands." (These hands are not to be confused
                     with the drawings of hands, known as manicules, that sometimes appear in the
                     margins of manuscripts to point out passages of interest.) The manuscript's
                     hands are represented in a critical edition by superscript numerals appended to
                     its siglum. A change in number, however, does not necessarily indicate a change
                     of person. For example, the copyist and corrector might be one and the same
                     person, but it can be important to distinguish them, since they represent
                     different views of the text.</p>

                  <p>Confusion can arise from assigning numbers only to hands subsequent to the
                     original copyist. That is, the siglum for the manuscript by itself (i.e.,
                     without a superscript numeral) is understood to represent both the physical
                     object and the hand of the original copyist who wrote in it; every subsequent
                     hand, including the original copyist correcting his own mistakes, is numbered
                     in descending order from "1". Strictly speaking, the original copyist is "hand
                     zero," but adding a superscript zero to every siglum would be redundant, since
                     it can be inferred from the absence of a numeral that the original copyist is
                     meant.</p>

                  <p>In some cases, it is not necessary, possible, or desirable to make such a sharp
                     distinction between hands. It may be sufficient instead to refer to hands other
                     than the original copyist with the general <foreign xml:lang="lat">manus
                        recentior</foreign>, or <hi rend="italic">m.r.</hi> ("a later hand").
                     However the editor decides to represent the activities of a manuscript's hands
                     and the relationships between them, an explanation should be provided in the
                     preface.</p>

                  <p>For more information on representing the hands in manuscripts, see the sections
                        "<ref target="#bibliography-manuscript-description">Manuscript
                        Description</ref>" and "<ref target="#bibliography-sigla">Sigla</ref>."</p>

                  <p>In sum, for the purposes of these guidelines, manuscript hands are witnesses,
                     and the following scheme should be used to indicate them: <list>
                        <item>siglum without a superscript number (= "hand zero"): the original
                           copyist.</item>
                        <item>siglum with superscript 1 (= "hand one"): a hand that wrote in the
                           manuscript after the original copyist wrote the text, even if it belongs
                           to the original copyist.</item>
                        <item>siglum with superscript 2 (="hand two"): a hand that wrote at the same
                           time or later than hand one.</item>
                        <item>siglum with superscript letters "mr" (= manus recentior) some hand
                           after the original copyist.</item>
                        <item>etc.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>

                  <p>Another acceptable approach is to append abbreviations such as "ac" and "pc"
                        (<foreign xml:lang="lat">ante corrections</foreign> and <foreign
                        xml:lang="lat">post correctionem</foreign>) as superscript notations on the
                     manuscript's siglum. It all depends on what suits the editor's purposes,
                     provided that the method of distinguishing hands is explained in the
                     description of manuscripts and both human- and machine-readable sigla are
                     assigned to them.</p>

                  <p>If it is desirable to identify different copyists (e.g., if the manuscript was
                     originally copied by more than one person), subscript notations should be used
                     (e.g, A<hi rend="subscript">1</hi>, A<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>, A<hi
                        rend="subscript">3</hi>, etc.). Each copyist's hand should be described and
                     assigned a human- and machine-readable siglum in the description of the
                     manuscript.</p>
               </div>
               <!-- End of section on witnesses -->

               <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-concepts-definitions-source">
                  <head>Source</head>

                  <p>A <hi rend="bold">source</hi> may be any modern critical edition, commentary,
                     article, review, or other item (e.g., personal correspondence) in which an
                     argument about the text has been advanced or discussed.</p>
               </div>
               <!-- End of section on sources -->

               <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-concepts-definitions-order">
                  <head>Order</head>

                  <p>As in traditional printed editions, the order in which certain information is
                     presented has meaning in LDLT editions, though the order's meaning is not
                     itself explicitly encoded. Editors should follow the recommendations of West
                     (87–88) on the issue of order. In brief:</p>

                  <list>
                     <item>Readings are presented in the following order of precedence: direct
                        manuscript tradition, indirect tradition, conjectures (in descending order
                        of merit, as determined by the editor).</item>
                     <item>Manuscripts should be given a regular order for citation, though editors
                        may deviate from the practice for the sake of clarity.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <!-- End of section on order -->
            </div>
            <!-- End of section apparatus-criticus-concepts-definitions -->

            <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-specs">
               <head>Encoding Specifications for the Apparatus Criticus</head>

               <p>To put the concepts discussed above into practice, the following attributes and
                  elements are required:</p>

               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="app"/>
                     <specDesc key="lem"/>
                     <specDesc key="rdg"/>
                     <specDesc key="wit"/>
                     <specDesc key="witDetail"/>
                     <specDesc key="note"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>

               <list>
                  <item xml:id="app"><gi>app</gi> (apparatus entry) contains the lemma and readings
                     for a single entry in the apparatus criticus, although it and its contents may
                     be nested inside of another <gi>app</gi>, if necessary.</item>
                  <item xml:id="lem"><gi>lem</gi> (lemma) contains a reading judged by the editor to
                     be authentic, or as close as possible to it. This type of reading constitutes
                     the text of the initial state (i.e., when first opened) of an LDLT edition's
                     text. A lemma may be an absence of text, if the editor has reason to doubt the
                     authenticity of the extant readings.</item>
                  <item xml:id="rdg"><gi>rdg</gi> (reading) contains text (or absence of text)
                     witnessed by a manuscript or found in an early printed edition (where it is not
                     expressly proposed), but judged by the editor to be unsatisfactory or corrupt
                     for linguistic and/or stylistic reasons. This text is initially in the
                     apparatus criticus, but it may be swapped with the lemma in the LDLT
                     viewer.</item>
                  <item xml:id="wit-att"><att>wit</att> (witness) contains machine-readable sigla
                     for any manuscript(s) (or manuscript hands) or early printed edition(s) (esp.
                     without an apparatus or commentary; i.e., <foreign xml:lang="lat">editiones
                        vetustiores</foreign>).</item>
                  <item xml:id="source-att"><att>source</att> (source) contains machine-readable
                     sigla for any printed edition(s) or other scholarly work(s) (e.g., article,
                     textual note, commentary) addressing an aspect of the text.</item>
                  <item><att>ana</att> (analysis) indicates that a reading belongs to at least one
                     category in the LDLT's taxonomy of readings. More than one value is possible.
                     See the section "<ref target="#apparatus-criticus-analysis">Tagging Readings
                        for Analysis</ref>."</item>
                  <item xml:id="wit"><gi>wit</gi> contains general information about a reading or a
                     group of witnesses.</item>
                  <item xml:id="witDetail"><gi>witDetail</gi> (witness detail) contains information
                     about a particular witness (<att>wit</att>) to a lemma (<gi>lem</gi>) or
                     reading (<gi>rdg</gi>). <gi>witDetail</gi> is especially important for
                     reporting <ref target="#correction">corrections</ref>.</item>
                  <item xml:id="note"><gi>note</gi> (note) contains editorial comments,
                     bibliographical references, or other information pertaining to the apparatus
                     entry.</item>
               </list>

               <p>In traditional printed editions, the lemma may appear in the apparatus criticus
                  for the purpose of disambiguation (e.g., if there are two instances of the word in
                  the same line or if the degree of variance makes it difficult to infer the lemma),
                  but more often the lemma must be inferred. This can lead to confusion and
                  frustration, particularly in readers not used to navigating a critical edition.
                  Moreover, variant readings are sequestered from the edition text and displayed at
                  the bottom of the page, an arrangement that can lead to false impressions about
                  the certainty and reliability of the edition text.</p>

               <p>In the <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html"
                     >TEI's model for the critical apparatus</ref>, which is the basis for these
                  guidelines, each entry includes the lemma and its variants. How that information
                  is displayed or printed is a separate issue, but at least the relationship between
                  the lemma and the variant readings is explicitly encoded. In digital
                  representations of an edition encoded according to the guidelines presented here,
                  readings may be swapped into or out of the edition text, but the editor's
                  determination about what is the lemma and what is a variant remains encoded to
                  preserve the argument the edition makes about the text. In this way, it is
                  possible for readers to experience many versions of a text in addition to the
                  edition's reference state (i.e., its default setting). The variety of readings
                  depends on what the editor decides to encode, and it is expected that those
                  decisions will be explained in the preface.</p>

               <p>The patterns displayed below are designed to handle the various kinds of
                  information conveyed in a typical apparatus criticus, including readings <foreign
                     xml:lang="lat">ante correctionem</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="lat">in
                     rasura</foreign>, among other paleographical and editorial details.</p>
            </div>
            <!-- End of section on apparatus specs -->

            <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-basic-entry">
               <head>Basic Reporting of a Variant Reading</head>

               <p>The most basic type of apparatus entry reports only a variant reading, without
                  editorial comment or a description of palaeographical details. The pattern is as
                  follows:</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app>
                     <lem><!-- text of lemma goes here --></lem>
                     <rdg wit="#siglum"><!-- text of variant reading goes here --></rdg>
                  </app>
               </egXML>

               <p>In other words, <gi>app</gi> begins the apparatus entry, followed by <gi>lem</gi>,
                  which contains the lemma for the entry. The lemma may be a single word or phrase
                  or the omission of a word or phrase. The variant reading follows, contained in
                     <gi>rdg</gi>. The attribute <att>wit</att> lists the witness(es) for the
                  variant. The hash or pound sign (#) before the siglum for the witness indicates
                  that the witness has been described elsewhere in the edition, making it possible
                  to retrieve that information through a link to it, if desired.</p>

               <p>If there is more than one witness for a reading, the sigla should be values for
                     <att>wit</att> separated by spaces.</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app>
                     <lem><!-- text of lemma goes here --></lem>
                     <rdg wit="#A #B #C"><!-- text of reading goes here --></rdg>
                  </app>
               </egXML>

               <p>If there is more than one variant reading to be reported, new <gi>rdg</gi>
                  elements should be added for each one.</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app>
                     <lem><!-- text of lemma goes here --></lem>
                     <rdg wit="#A #B #C"><!-- text of reading goes here --></rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#D #E #F"><!-- text of reading goes here --></rdg>
                  </app>
               </egXML>

               <p>If it is desirable to indicate that a variant appears in both a manuscript and a
                  modern edition or other source, the same pattern applies, with the addition of
                     <att>source</att>.</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app>
                     <lem><!-- text of lemma goes here --></lem>
                     <rdg wit="#A #B #C" source="#Vettel #Grosjean"
                        ><!-- text of reading goes here --></rdg>
                  </app>
               </egXML>

               <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-basic-entry-examples">
                  <head>Examples of basic apparatus criticus entries</head>

                  <p>At Calp. 1.2 (<foreign xml:lang="lat">quamvis et madidis incumbant praela
                        racemis</foreign>), the manuscript <hi rend="bold">P</hi> has <foreign
                        xml:lang="lat">praeda</foreign> where the lemma is <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                        >praela</foreign>. In a traditional apparatus criticus, this would be
                     printed as follows: 2 praeda <hi rend="bold">P</hi>.</p>

                  <p>The following pattern demonstrates how to encode the entry in XML:</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <l n="2">quamvis et madidis incumbant <app>
                           <lem>praela</lem>
                           <rdg wit="#P">praeda</rdg>
                        </app> racemis</l>
                  </egXML>

                  <p>This encoding can be rendered in the traditional manner, or it can be used in
                     an interactive apparatus to swap the variant with the lemma in the main edition
                     text.</p>

                  <p>The lemma <foreign xml:lang="lat">quamvis</foreign> in the same line
                     demonstrates how to indicate that a variant has more than one witness:</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <l n="2"><app>
                           <lem>quamvis</lem>
                           <rdg wit="#f #g #r #t">quatinus</rdg>
                        </app> et madidis incumbant praela racemis</l>
                  </egXML>

                  <p>The witnesses are listed here in chronological order, but an editor may wish to
                     use a different ordering principle. The order should be described and explained
                     in the preface.</p>

                  <p>The following example demonstrates how to encode a reading supported by a
                     witness and a source.</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app>
                        <lem>sequor</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#N" source="#Glaeser">sequar</rdg>
                     </app>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <!-- End section basic-entry-examples -->
            </div>
            <!-- End of section on basic apparatus entry -->

            <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-catch-all-references">
               <head>Use of Catch-all References in the Critical Apparatus</head>

               <p>If it is desirable to use a consensus reference (e.g., ω, ς) or a catch-all
                  reference (e.g., codd., mss., cett., edd.) the references must be defined in the
                  bibliography of the edition according to the guidelines in the section "<ref
                     target="#bibliography-sigla-catch-all">Catch-all References</ref>." This
                  section demonstrates how to insert catch-all references into the apparatus.</p>

               <p>If consensus or catchall references are used without any addition annotation, they
                  may be treated like any other witness or source (i.e., as values of <att>wit</att>
                  or <att>source</att>), provided that they have both machine- and human-readable
                  sigla.</p>

               <p>If they are annotated (e.g., edd. ante Glaeser), they must be encoded in
                     <gi>wit</gi> according to the guidelines below.</p>

               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="wit"/>
                     <specDesc key="ref"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>

               <list>
                  <item><gi>wit</gi> contains a catch-all reference to a group of manuscripts,
                     editions, or other materials.</item>
                  <item><gi>ref</gi> contains machine- and human-readable references to an item in
                     the bibliography.</item>
               </list>

               <p>In the following example, the editor wishes to show that the editions are divided,
                  with one in particular (Glaeser) marking a definitive shift in preference.</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app>
                     <lem wit="#N #P">vicit</lem>
                     <wit><ref target="#Glaeser">Glaeser</ref> sqq.</wit>
                     <rdg wit="#G">vīcit</rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#d">ludit</rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#V">lusit</rdg>
                     <wit>edd. ante <ref target="#Glaeser">Glaeser</ref></wit>
                     <rdg wit="#μ">visit</rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#γ"/>
                  </app>
               </egXML>

               <p>This may be displayed or printed as vicit] N P Glaeser sqq. : vīcit G : ludit d :
                  lusit V edd. ante Glaeser : visit μ : om. γ.</p>

            </div>
            <!-- End of section on the use of catch-all references -->

            <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-symbols-gaps-lacunae-omissions">
               <head>Lacunae and Omissions</head>

               <p>Traditionally, lacunae and omissions are represented typographically within the
                  text (e.g., [ ], ***, &lt;***&gt;) and/or noted in the apparatus criticus. The
                  following sections indicate how to encode those gaps to produce not only the
                  appropriate typographical representation in the main text of the edition, but also
                  annotations in the apparatus. Encoding this information will also turn it into
                  data that can be processed and searched.</p>

               <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-lacuna-physical-loss">
                  <head>Lacuna (Physical Loss)</head>

                  <p>[ *** ] = An unknown amount of text has been lost from one or more witnesses
                     because of damage.</p>


                  <p>For example, sections 1.1–1.33.3 of Julius Caesar's <bibl><title>de Bello
                           Civili</title></bibl> are missing from manuscript <hi rend="bold">M</hi>.
                        <ref target="#damon-caesar">Cynthia Damon's OCT</ref> edition has the
                     following in the main text: ***Litteris. The critical apparatus has
                        <quote>1.1.1–1.33.3 <hi rend="italic">M deest, vice eius m
                        citatur</hi></quote>.</p>

                  <p>In an LDLT edition, that should be encoded as follows:</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app>
                        <lem wit="#M" xml:id="M-lacuna-1.1"><lacunaStart/></lem>
                        <witDetail wit="#M" target="#M-lacuna-1.1">1.1.1–1.33.3 M deest, vice eius m
                           citatur.</witDetail>
                     </app>Litteris </egXML>

                  <p>At 1.33.3, the apparatus criticus has: <quote>-duum <hi rend="italic">hinc
                           adest M</hi></quote>. In an LDLT edition, that should be encoded as
                     follows:</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <p>Sic tri<app>
                           <lem>duum</lem>
                           <rdg wit="#M" xml:id="rdg-1.33.3-lacunaEnd"><lacunaEnd/></rdg>
                           <witDetail wit="#M" target="#rdg-1.33.3-lacunaEnd">hinc adest
                              M</witDetail>
                        </app> disputationibus …</p>
                  </egXML>

                  <p>Note that square brackets will surround ***.</p>

               </div>

               <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-lacuna-conjecture">
                  <head>Lacuna Conjectured, No Text Supplied</head>

                  <p>&lt;***&gt; = A lacuna has been conjectured on the grounds of style, context,
                     or some other reason. No text has been supplied in its place.</p>

                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="gap"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>

                  <list>
                     <item><gi>gap</gi> signifies that text is missing.</item>
                     <item><att>reason</att> with value "lost" indicates that the text has been
                        lost.</item>
                  </list>

                  <p>If the conjectured lacuna has been accepted by the editor of the edition,
                        <gi>lem</gi> with <att>type</att>="emendation" should contain <gi>gap</gi>.
                     If the conjectured lacuna is only noted in the apparatus criticus, then
                        <gi>rdg</gi> with <att>type</att>="conjecture" should contain <gi>gap</gi>.
                     For more on encoding conjecture and emendation see the section "<ref
                        target="#apparatus-criticus-conjecture-and-emendation">Conjecture and
                        Emendation</ref>".</p>

                  <p>For example, at the conclusion of section 3.8.4 of Julius Caesar's
                           <bibl><title>de Bello Civili</title></bibl>, <ref target="#damon-caesar"
                        >Cynthia Damon's OCT</ref> edition has the following in the main text: si in
                     Caesaris complexum uenire posset ***. The apparatus criticus has the following
                     annotation: <hi rend="italic">lacunam statuit Vascosanus</hi>.</p>

                  <p>In an LDLT edition, that should be encoded as follows:</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <p>si in Caesaris complexum uenire posset <app>
                           <lem source="#Vascosanus" type="emendation"><gap reason="lost"/></lem>
                        </app></p>
                  </egXML>

                  <p>The same encoding should be used to indicated the conjectured lacuna of a
                     number of lines of verse. For example, <ref target="#verdiere-calpurnius">Raoul
                        Verdière</ref> argues that nine verses have been omitted by the copyist of
                     the archetype of all manuscripts of Calpurnius Siculus' eclogues. He prints
                     nine lines of equally spaced dots in the text, and he writes in the apparatus
                     criticus, <quote>u. 1–9 <hi rend="italic">librarii incuria cecidisse
                        puto</hi>.</quote></p>

                  <p>If the editor of an LDLT edition of Calpurnius accepts this argument,
                     Verdière's conjecture would be encoded as follows:</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app type="line-omission">
                        <lem source="#Verdière" xml:id="lem-1.1-9">
                           <l n="1"><gap reason="lost"/></l>
                           <l n="2"><gap reason="lost"/></l>
                           <l n="3"><gap reason="lost"/></l>
                           <l n="4"><gap reason="lost"/></l>
                           <l n="5"><gap reason="lost"/></l>
                           <l n="6"><gap reason="lost"/></l>
                           <l n="7"><gap reason="lost"/></l>
                           <l n="8"><gap reason="lost"/></l>
                           <l n="9"><gap reason="lost"/></l>
                        </lem>
                        <note target="#lem-1.1-9">u. 1–9 librarii incuria cecidisse putavit
                           Verdière</note>
                     </app>
                  </egXML>

                  <p>In the digital or print version, nine lines of &lt; *** &gt; would be printed
                     at the beginning of the text, and the numbering of the lines that follow would
                     begin with 10. The apparatus criticus would have the entry <quote>u. 1–9
                        librarii incuria cecidisse putavit Verdière</quote>.</p>
               </div>
               <!-- End section "Lacuna Conjectured, No Text Supplied" -->
            </div>
            <!-- End of section on lacunae -->

            <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-symbols-known-loss-characters"
               corresp="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-lostcharknown.html">
               <head>Known Amount Of Characters Lost</head>

               <p>[ . . . ] = The editor knows from context and/or observation how many characters
                  have been lost. Each dot represents a missing character.</p>

               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="gap"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>

               <list>
                  <item><gi>gap</gi> signifies text missing.</item>
                  <item><att>reason</att> with value "lost" indicates that the text has been
                     lost.</item>
                  <item><att>quantity</att> indicates the number of characters lost.</item>
                  <item><att>unit</att> with value "characters" indicates the unit measured in
                        <att>quantity</att>.</item>
               </list>

               <p>For example, in the apparatus criticus to Calp. 4.4, <ref
                     target="#giarratano-calpurnius">Giarratano</ref> has the following with
                  reference to lemma <foreign xml:lang="lat">spiritus amnis</foreign>:
                     <quote>sp&#099;&#773; N (deinde lac. 6 litt.)</quote>.</p>

               <p>In an LDLT edition, that would be encoded as follows:</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <l n="4">ripa levatque diem vicini <app>
                        <lem>spiritus amnis</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#N">sp&#099;&#773; <gap reason="lost" quantity="6"
                              unit="characters"/></rdg>
                     </app>? </l>
               </egXML>

               <p>That encoding would produce the following entry in the apparatus: <quote>spc̅
                     [......]</quote>. If it is desirable to supplement that with a note, the
                     <gi>rdg</gi> should be given an <att>xml:id</att> and the note should be
                  inserted in a <gi>witDetail</gi> pointing to it:</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <l n="4">ripa levatque diem vicini <app>
                        <lem>spiritus amnis</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#N" xml:id="rdg-4.4-spiritus-amnis">sp&#099;&#773; <gap
                              reason="lost" quantity="6" unit="characters"/></rdg>
                        <witDetail wit="#N" target="#rdg-4.4-spiritus-amnis">lac. 6
                           litt.</witDetail>
                     </app>? </l>
               </egXML>
            </div>
            <!-- End section "Known amount of text lost" -->

            <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-omission">
               <head>Omission</head>

               <p>This section explains how to encode omission of text from a witness. Omission is
                  different from a lacuna because omission may be the result of something other than
                  physical damage to a witness. Omission can occur when a copyist accidentally skips
                  a word, a line, or a whole section.</p>

               <p>For example, the witness known as "P" has omitted the word <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                     >pecus</foreign> from the Calp. 1.38: <foreign xml:lang="lat">securo custode
                     pecus nocturnaque pastor</foreign>. The traditional apparatus criticus
                  indicates the omission as follows: pecus <hi rend="italic">om.</hi>
                  <hi rend="bold">P</hi></p>

               <p>In these guidelines, omission is represented by a so-called "self-closing" or
                  empty <gi>rdg</gi> (i.e., &lt;rdg/&gt;):</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <l>securo custode <app>
                        <lem>pecus</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#P"/>
                     </app> nocturnaque pastor</l>
               </egXML>

               <p>The same model applies to the omission of an entire line of verse by a witness or
                  witnesses, but in that case <gi>app</gi> has <att>type</att>="line-omission" and
                     <gi>lem</gi> contains the entire line, with the omission marked by a
                  self-closing <gi>rdg</gi>:</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app type="line-omission">
                     <lem>
                        <l n="3">et spument rauco ferventia musta susurro.</l>
                     </lem>
                     <rdg wit="#n #h"/>
                  </app>
               </egXML>

               <p>This will be displayed in the apparatus criticus as <quote><hi rend="italic">vers.
                        om.</hi>
                     <hi rend="bold">n h</hi></quote></p>
            </div>
            <!-- End of section on omission -->

            <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-addition">
               <head>Addition</head>

               <p>The following guidelines demonstrate how to indicate that text has been added to a
                  witness. There are two methods for encoding additions: prose description and
                  semantic markup. Both are described in this section. The same information is
                  presented in both cases, but the semantic markup version would support additional
                  functionality such as querying and filtering on readings added in the margin (or
                  elsewhere).</p>

               <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-addition-prose">
                  <head>Addition: Prose Description</head>

                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="witDetail"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>

                  <p><gi>witDetail</gi> (witness detail) contains a prose description of the
                     addition.</p>

                  <p>For example, the copyist of manuscript <hi rend="bold">G</hi> has the <ref
                        target="#lem">lemma</ref>
                     <foreign xml:lang="lat">certare</foreign>, but a later hand has added the
                     variant reading <foreign xml:lang="lat">certate</foreign> in the margin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <quote>89 certare] certate <hi rend="bold">G<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">in mg.</hi></quote>
                  </p>

                  <p>The prose description method uses <gi>witDetail</gi> to describe the
                     addition:</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app>
                        <lem>certare</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#G1" xml:id="rdg-certate">certate</rdg>
                        <witDetail wit="#G1" target="#rdg-certate">(add. in mg.)</witDetail>
                     </app>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <!-- End of section on addition: prose description -->

               <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-addition-semantic">
                  <head>Addition: Semantic Markup</head>

                  <p>The semantic markup method uses <gi>add</gi> to encode the addition:</p>

                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="add"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>

                  <list>
                     <item><gi>add</gi> (addition) contains text that has been added.</item>

                     <item><att>place</att> indicates the placed where the text has been added.
                        Possible values: <list>
                           <item><hi rend="bold">above</hi>: above the line (<hi rend="italic"
                                 >suprascr. = superscriptum/a</hi>)</item>
                           <item><hi rend="bold">below</hi>: below the line (<hi rend="italic"
                                 >subscr. = subscriptum/a</hi>)</item>
                           <item><hi rend="bold">bottom</hi>: bottom of the page (<hi rend="italic"
                                 >ad fin. = ad finem</hi></item>
                           <item><hi rend="bold">inline</hi>: within the body of the original text
                                 (<hi rend="italic">in textu</hi>)</item>
                           <item><hi rend="bold">inRas</hi>: in the space where text has been
                              erased. (<hi rend="italic">in ras. = in rasura</hi>)</item>
                           <item><hi rend="bold">margin</hi>: right, left, or both (<hi
                                 rend="italic">in mg. = in margine</hi>)</item>
                           <item><hi rend="bold">top</hi>: at the top of the page (<hi rend="italic"
                                 >ad init. = ad initium</hi></item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app>
                        <lem>certare</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#G1"><add place="margin">certate</add></rdg>
                     </app>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <!-- End of section on addition: semantic markup -->
            </div>
            <!-- End of section on additions -->

            <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-deletions">
               <head>Deletions</head>

               <p>The following guidelines demonstrate how to produce a notation about the deletion
                  of text from a witness by a scribe, along with the method of deletion (if
                  known).</p>

               <p>For deletions made by the editor of the current edition or a previous editor, see
                  the section "<ref target="#apparatus-criticus-deletion-editorial">Editorial
                     Deletions</ref>."</p>

               <p>Deletion almost always occurs as part of a correction. In that case, this section
                  should be used in combination with the guidelines in "<ref
                     target="#apparatus-criticus-correction">Correction</ref>." The examples in this
                  section represent deletion as part of a correction.</p>

               <p>There are two methods for encoding deletions: prose description and semantic
                  markup. Both are described in this section. The same information is presented in
                  both cases, but the semantic markup version will support additional functionality
                  such as querying and filtering on deleted readings and the method of deletion.</p>

               <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-deletion-prose">
                  <head>Deletion: Prose Description</head>

                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="witDetail"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>

                  <p><gi>witDetail</gi> (witness detail) contains a prose description of the
                     deletion.</p>

                  <p>The prose description method uses <gi>witDetail</gi> to describe the
                     deletion:</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app>
                        <lem>amotae</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#G" xml:id="rdg-adamote">adamote</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#G1" xml:id="rdg-amote">amote</rdg>
                        <witDetail wit="#G" target="#rdg-adamote" type="correction-original"/>
                        <witDetail wit="#G1" target="#rdg-amote" type="correction-altered">(ad <hi
                              rend="italic">exp.</hi>)</witDetail>
                     </app>
                  </egXML>

                  <p>The output of this encoding would be amotae] adamote <hi rend="bold">G</hi>
                     (a.c.), amote <hi rend="bold">G<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></hi> (ad <hi
                        rend="italic">exp</hi>.)</p>
               </div>
               <!-- End of section on deletion: prose description -->

               <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-deletion-semantic">
                  <head>Deletion: Semantic Markup</head>

                  <p>The semantic markup method uses <gi>del</gi> to encode the deletion. Deletions
                     encoded according to these guidelines will be displayed or printed enclosed in
                     double brackets: &#10214; &#10215;.</p>

                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="del"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>

                  <list>
                     <item><gi>del</gi> (deletion) contains text that has been deleted.</item>
                     <item><att>rend</att> (rendition) indicates the method of deletion. Use of
                           <att>rend</att> is optional. Without it, the generic notation <hi
                           rend="italic">del.</hi> for <foreign xml:lang="lat">delevit</foreign> or
                           <foreign xml:lang="lat">delevi</foreign> will be inserted. Otherwise,
                           <att>rend</att> with one of the following values will generate a more
                        specific notation:<list>
                           <item><hi rend="bold">erasure</hi>: text has been erased or scraped off
                              of the page, but it is possible to detect what was deleted (<hi
                                 rend="italic">ante ras.</hi>).</item>
                           <item><hi rend="bold">expunction</hi>: dots have been written under a
                              word to indicate that it should be deleted (<hi rend="italic"
                                 >exp.</hi>).</item>
                        </list></item>
                  </list>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app>
                        <lem>amotae</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#G" xml:id="rdg-adamote">adamote</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#G1" xml:id="rdg-amote"><del rend="expunction">ad</del>amote</rdg>
                        <witDetail wit="#G" target="#rdg-adamote" type="correction-original"/>
                        <witDetail wit="#G1" target="#rdg-amote" type="correction-altered">ad <hi
                              rend="italic">exp.</hi></witDetail>
                     </app>
                  </egXML>

                  <p>The output of this encoding would be amotae] adamote <hi rend="bold">G</hi>
                        (<hi rend="italic">a.c.</hi>), &#12314;ad&#12315;amote <hi rend="bold">G<hi
                           rend="superscript">1</hi></hi> (<hi rend="italic">p.c.</hi>, ad <hi
                        rend="italic">exp.</hi>)</p>
               </div>
               <!-- End of section on deletion: semantic markup -->
               <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-deletion-editorial">
                  <head>Editorial Deletion</head>

                  <p>{ } = Text suspected by the editor to be superfluous, but retained in the
                     edition text to indicate its traditional attribution to the author.</p>

                  <p>Square brackets have been used to indicate editorial deletions in the past,
                     but, as <ref target="#West">West</ref> argues (p. 80), this is apt to cause
                     confusion, since they have a different meaning for papyrologists and
                     epigraphists (see "Undetermined Amount Of Text Lost" in these guidelines).
                     Accordingly, LDLT editions follow West's suggestion to use braces to indicate
                     editorial deletions.</p>

                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="surplus"/>
                        <specDesc key="note"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>

                  <list>
                     <item><gi>surplus</gi> signifies text identified by the editor as added by
                        someone other than the original author.</item>
                     <item><gi>note</gi> contains information about the deletion (e.g.,
                        bibliography, comments). This allows editors to make the distinction between
                        the usage of <hi rend="italic">secl.</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >del.</hi></item>
                  </list>

                  <p>For example, at section 29 of Suetonius' life of Claudius, <ref
                        target="#kaster-suetonius">Robert Kaster</ref> indicates in the text of his
                     OCT edition that two words have been deleted by previous scholars: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">His, ut dixi, uxoribusque addictus non principem {se} sed
                        ministrum egit, compendio cuiusque horum uel etiam studio aut libidine
                        honores exercitus impunitates supplicia largitus {est} et quidem insciens
                        plerumque et ignarus.</quote></p>

                  <p>The entry for the first one in the apparatus criticus has the following:
                        <quote>se <hi rend="italic">secl. Graev. 1697, 411 (Polak 1882,
                        12)</hi></quote>. The entry for the second one is as follows: <quote>est <hi
                           rend="italic">del. Bent.</hi></quote>.</p>

                  <p>In an LDLT edition, the deletion would be encoded in the text as follows:</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <p>His, ut dixi, uxoribusque addictus non principem <app>
                           <lem xml:id="lem-29-se">
                              <surplus>se</surplus></lem>
                           <note target="#lem-29-se">secl. <ref target="#Graev.">Graev. 1697,
                                 411</ref> (<ref target="#Polak">Polak 1882, 12</ref>)</note>
                        </app> sed ministrum egit, compendio cuiusque horum uel etiam studio aut
                        libidine honores exercitus impunitates supplicia largitus <app>
                           <lem xml:id="#lem-29-est">
                              <surplus>est</surplus>
                           </lem>
                           <note target="#lem-29-est">del. <ref target="#Bent."
                           >Bent.</ref></note></app> et quidem insciens plerumque et ignarus.</p>
                  </egXML>

                  <p>The use of <gi>surplus</gi> will cause the braces { } to be inserted on both
                     sides of the word(s) to be deleted. The rest of the information is handled as a
                     normal entry in the apparatus criticus.</p>

                  <p>If it is desirable to indicate in the apparatus criticus that a previous editor
                     has proposed deleting some text, even if the deletion has not been adopted for
                     the main text of the edition, <gi>surplus</gi> should be used inside of
                        <gi>rdg</gi>. If the reading is swapped into the main text in the digital
                     version, the braces { } will be displayed around the reading.</p>
               </div>
               <!-- End of section on editorial deletion -->
            </div>
            <!-- End of section on deletion -->

            <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-transposition">
               <head>Transpositions</head>

               <p>Transpositions may be handled in two ways: prose description or semantic markup.
                  Prose description produces a note in the apparatus criticus. Semantic encoding
                  also produces a note in the apparatus criticus, but it will also enable readers to
                  swap the transpositions in and out of the text in a digital version.</p>

               <p>The sections below demonstrate the prose description and semantic markup methods
                  for the following examples:</p>

               <p>Example 1: In the Teubner edition of Ovid's <bibl><title>Tristia</title></bibl>,
                     <ref target="#hall-ovid">J.B. Hall</ref> follows the recommendation of
                  Wilamowitz and transposes lines 41–42 of poem 3.12 so that they follow line 36. In
                  the apparatus criticus, Hall writes <quote><hi rend="bold">41–42</hi>
                     <hi rend="italic">post 36 transposuit Wilamowitz.</hi></quote></p>

               <p>Example 2: In <ref target="#tarrant-ovid">Richard Tarrant's OCT</ref> of Ovid's
                        <bibl><title>Metamorphoses</title></bibl>, the text of 1.304–305 is as
                  follows:</p>

               <l>nat lupus inter oues, fuluos uehit unda leones,</l>
               <l>unda uehit tigres; nec uires fulminis apro</l>

               <p>In the apparatus criticus, Tarrant notes the following: 304–5 fuluos … tigres <hi
                     rend="italic">om HM<hi rend="superscript">ac</hi>(N<hi rend="superscript"
                        >ac</hi></hi>); <hi rend="italic">habet Bern, sed ordine turbato</hi> (nat …
                  oues nec uires f. apro | unda u. tigres, fuluos … leones)</p>

               <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-transposition-prose-description">
                  <head>Transposition: Prose Description</head>

                  <p>To describe this transposition in the apparatus criticus, <gi>app</gi> encloses
                     the affected passage, and <gi>witDetail</gi> or <gi>note</gi> contains the
                     description.</p>

                  <p>Example 1 (Ov. <bibl><title>Tr.</title></bibl> 3.12.36ff.)</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <l n="35">ille quidem mirum ni de regione propinqua</l>
                     <l n="36">non nisi uicinas tutus ararit aquas.</l>
                     <app>
                        <lem xml:id="lem-3.12.41-42">
                           <l n="41">fas quoque ab ore freti longaeque Propontidos undis</l>
                           <l n="42">huc aliquem certo uela dedisse Noto.</l>
                        </lem>
                        <note target="#lem-3.12.41-42">41–42 post 36 transposuit <ref
                              target="#Wilamowitz">Wilamowitz</ref>.</note>
                     </app>
                     <l n="37">rarus ab Italia tantum mare nauita transit,</l>
                     <l n="38">litora rarus in haec portubus orba uenit.</l>
                  </egXML>

                  <p>Example 2 (Ov. <bibl><title>Met.</title></bibl>, 1.304–305):</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app>
                        <lem xml:id="lem-1.304–305">
                           <l n="304">nat lupus inter oues, fuluos uehit unda leones,</l>
                           <l n="305">unda uehit tigres; nec uires fulminis apro</l>
                        </lem>
                        <note target="#lem-1.304–305"> fuluos … tigres <hi rend="italic">om</hi>.
                              <ref target="#H">H</ref><ref target="#Mac">M<hi rend="superscript"
                                 >ac</hi></ref>(<ref target="#Nac">N<hi rend="superscript"
                              >ac</hi></ref>)</note>
                        <note target="#lem-1.304–305">304–5 <hi rend="italic">habet <ref
                                 target="#Bern">Bern</ref>, sed ordine turbato</hi> (nat … oues nec
                           uires f. apro | unda u. tigres, fuluos … leones)</note>
                     </app>
                  </egXML>

                  <p>Neither one of these examples would support the functionality of swapping the
                     transpositions in and out of the main text of the edition. Instead, readers
                     would just see a note in the apparatus criticus describing the
                     transposition.</p>

               </div>
               <!-- End of section on prose description of transpositions -->
               <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-transposition-semantic-encoding">
                  <head>Transposition: Semantic Encoding</head>

                  <p>In some cases, a transposition may be semantically encoded using the basic
                     pattern for an apparatus entry. In example 1 (Ov.
                        <bibl><title>Tr.</title></bibl> 3.12.36ff., <ref
                        target="#apparatus-criticus-transposition">text above</ref>), there are
                     basically two forms of the text: with and without the transposition. Since the
                     editor (Hall) has accepted Wilamowitz' proposed transposition, the transposed
                     version is contained in <gi>lem</gi> and the original is contained in
                        <gi>rdg</gi>:</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <l n="35">ille quidem mirum ni de regione propinqua</l>
                     <l n="36">non nisi uicinas tutus ararit aquas.</l>
                     <app>
                        <lem xml:id="lem-3.12.41-42" exclude="#rdg-3.12.41–42" type="emendation">
                           <l n="41">fas quoque ab ore freti longaeque Propontidos undis</l>
                           <l n="42">huc aliquem certo uela dedisse Noto.</l>
                        </lem>
                        <note target="#lem-3.12.41-42">41–42 post 36 transposuit <ref
                              target="#Wilamowitz">Wilamowitz</ref>.</note>
                     </app>
                     <l n="37">rarus ab Italia tantum mare nauita transit,</l>
                     <l n="38">litora rarus in haec portubus orba uenit.</l>
                     <l n="39">siue tamen Graia scierit siue ille Latina</l>
                     <l n="40">uoce loqui—certe gratior huius erit</l>
                     <app>
                        <rdg xml:id="rdg-3.12.41–42" exclude="#lem-3.12.41–42">
                           <l n="41">fas quoque ab ore freti longaeque Propontidos undis</l>
                           <l n="42">huc aliquem certo uela dedisse Noto.</l>
                        </rdg>
                     </app>
                  </egXML>

                  <p>This will allow users to toggle between the original and emended versions of
                     the text. <att>exclude</att> ensures that lines 41–42 will never be displayed
                     in two places at once. When the lemma (i.e., Wilamowitz' emendation) is
                     displayed in the edition text, lines 41–42 will follow line 36. When the
                     reading that has lines 41–42 following line 40 is selected for display,
                     Wilamowitz' emendation will be excluded from the display.</p>

                  <p>More complicated transpositions, like the one in example 2 below, operate in
                     the same way: <att>exclude</att> ensures that mutually exclusive readings are
                     never displayed together.</p>

                  <p>Keeping track of the mutually exclusive readings can be a challenge, as the
                     example below demonstrates. It can be helpful to make a table or to use some
                     other method of keeping track of the mutually exclusive readings.</p>

                  <p>Example 2 (Ov. <bibl><title>Met.</title></bibl>, 1.304–305, <ref
                        target="#apparatus-criticus-transposition">text above</ref>). In this
                     example, the witness known as Bern transposes portions of two lines. Witnesses
                     H M<hi rend="superscript">ac</hi> (and N<hi rend="superscript">ac</hi>)
                     conflate the lines, which is another kind of transposition. That is, it can be
                     assumed that they did not write the first half the line at 304 and the second
                     half of the line at 305, but rather wrote the two halves together on the same
                     line (i.e., nat lupus inter oues, nec uires fulminis apro).</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <l n="304">nat lupus inter oues, <app>
                           <lem xml:id="lem-304-fuluos"
                              exclude="#rdg-305-HM1 #rdg-305-HM2 #rdg-305-Bern">fuluos uehit unda
                              leones,</lem>
                           <rdg wit="#H #M" xml:id="rdg-304-HM"
                              exclude="#lem-305-unda #lem-305-nec #rdg-305-Bern">nec uires fulminis
                              apro</rdg>
                           <rdg wit="#Bern" xml:id="rdg-304-Bern"
                              exclude="#lem-305-nec #rdg-305-HM1 #rdg-305-HM2">nec uires fulminis
                              apro</rdg>
                           <witDetail wit="#M" target="#rdg-304-HM" type="ante-corr">(N<hi
                                 rend="superscript">ac</hi>)</witDetail>
                        </app>
                     </l>
                     <l n="305">
                        <app>
                           <lem xml:id="lem-305-unda" exclude="#rdg 304-HM #rdg-305-HM2">unda uehit
                              tigres</lem>
                           <rdg wit="#H #M" xml:id="rdg-305-HM1"
                              exclude="#lem-304-fuluos #rdg-304-Bern #lem-305-nec #rdg-305-Bern"/>
                        </app>; <app>
                           <lem xml:id="lem-305-nec" exclude="#rdg-304HM #rdg-304-Bern #rdg-305-HM1"
                              >nec uires fulminis apro</lem>
                           <rdg wit="#H #M" xml:id="rdg-305-HM2"
                              exclude="#lem-304-fuluos #rdg-304-Bern #lem-305-unda"/>
                           <rdg wit="#Bern" xml:id="rdg-305-Bern"
                              exclude="#lem-304-fuluos #rdg-304-HM #rdg-305-HM1">fuluos uehit unda
                              leones</rdg>
                        </app>
                     </l>
                  </egXML>

                  <p>The effort required to keep track of the mutually exclusive readings pays off
                     in the ability to swap the transpositions in and out of the edition text in the
                     digital version.</p>
               </div>
               <!-- End of section on semantically encoded transpositions. -->
            </div>
            <!-- End of section on transposition. -->

            <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-connected-readings">
               <head>Connected Readings</head>

               <p>In some cases, it may be necessary to show that a witness or a source has variants
                  in separate places that are related to each other. For example, the text of Calp.
                  6.68 is as follows: <quote><foreign xml:lang="lat">imminet exesa veluti testudine
                        concha.</foreign></quote>. Heinsius proposes <foreign xml:lang="lat">exesae
                     - conchae</foreign>. That means that whenever <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                     >exesa</foreign> is displayed, <foreign xml:lang="lat">concha</foreign> must
                  also be displayed, and whenever one of Heinsius' conjectures is displayed, the
                  other one must accompany it.</p>

               <p>As with line transpositions, <att>exclude</att> is used to prevent mutually
                  exclusive readings from being displayed together. Calp. 6.68 should be encoded as
                  follows:</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <l>imminet <app>
                        <lem xml:id="lem-6.68-exesa" exclude="#rdg-6.68-conchae">exesa</lem>
                        <rdg source="#Heinsius" xml:id="rdg-6.68-exesae" exclude="#lem-6.68-concha"
                           >exesae</rdg>
                     </app> veluti testudine <app>
                        <lem xml:id="lem-6.68-concha" exclude="#rdg-6.68-exesae">concha</lem>
                        <rdg xml:id="rdg-6.68-conchae" exclude="#lem-6.68-exesa">conchae</rdg>
                     </app>
                  </l>
               </egXML>

            </div>

            <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-correction">
               <head>Corrections</head>

               <p>Correction has been discussed in the section "<ref
                     target="#apparatus-criticus-concepts-definitions">Concepts and
                     Definitions</ref>." In short, for the purposes of these guidelines,
                  "correction" describes any attempt by the original copyist or some other hand to
                  alter a witness' reading, whether or not the result matches what is in the main
                  edition text.</p>

               <p>Since the amount of detail to report is a matter for editors to decide, this
                  section describes a range of options for encoding corrections. All are acceptable
                  and will be supported by the LDLT's viewer application. When determining the
                  method to use, editors should bear in mind not only the amount of detail necessary
                  to communicate the nature of a correction, but also the functionality they want
                  their edition to support. The subsections below include discussions intended to
                  help editors make those determinations.</p>

               <p>Before reading the encoding guidelines for corrections, it is recommended to read
                  the section "<ref target="#apparatus-criticus-correction-as-metadata">Correction
                     as Metadata</ref>" to understand the concepts behind the guidelines.</p>

               <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-correction-as-metadata">
                  <head>Correction as Metadata</head>

                  <p>Over time, editors have devised creative ways of reporting corrections. The
                     simplest method is to report readings and annotate them with <foreign
                        xml:lang="lat">ante correctionem</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="lat">post
                        correctionem</foreign>, or something similar. Another method is to add
                     abbreviations for those phrases as superscript notations on manuscript sigla
                     (e.g., B<hi rend="superscript">ac</hi>, B<hi rend="superscript">pc</hi>).
                     Sometimes it is necessary to provide more detail about the method of
                     correction, in which cases editors will either describe the correction (e.g., t
                        <hi rend="italic">exp.</hi>, r <hi rend="italic">add. s.l.</hi>) or they
                     will try to represent it typographically (e.g., referṭ<hi rend="superscript"
                        >r</hi>e). Some rely on superscript notation for all of these details (e.g.,
                        P<hi rend="superscript">csl</hi> = P <foreign xml:lang="lat">correctio supra
                        lineam</foreign>).</p>

                  <p>The different methods have advantages and disadvantages, but each one
                     effectively demonstrates that correction is a complex subject. Even the word
                     "correction" is problematic, since it can refer to the result of a process or
                     the process itself. Representing correction faithfully in a digital critical
                     edition depends on careful analysis of the information included in a
                     correction.</p>

                  <p>Aside from judgments about correctness, "correction" may involve at least four
                     kinds of information: <list>
                        <item>a reading.</item>
                        <item>the state of the reading: original or altered.</item>
                        <item>an agent or agents (i.e., the correcting hand or hands).</item>
                        <item>a method or methods of correction (i.e., deletion, addition above the
                           line, etc.).</item>
                        <item>the relationship between the original reading and the altered
                           reading.</item>
                     </list></p>

                  <p>Since the primary mission of an apparatus criticus is to report variant
                     readings, it is useful to think of the reading as the data and the information
                     state, agency, method, and relationship as metadata, or data about the
                     data.</p>

                  <p>Not all of these metadata items will be reported in every instance. The
                     original reading, for example, obviously does not have an agent (beyond the
                     witness to the reading) or a method of correction, but it will have a state
                     (original). It might have a correspondence to show that it is related to its
                     altered form, if one is provided, but it is not always necessary to report the
                     altered form. For example, if the altered form matches the lemma in the main
                     text of the edition, it is sufficient to report the original form with a note
                     that it was corrected (the inference being that it was corrected to the
                     "correct" form of the lemma, if no other form is reported). Similarly, it may
                     not be necessary to report the method of correction.</p>

                  <p>The LDLT supports two ways of reporting corrections: prose description and
                     semantic markup. In both cases, the model of readings as data and the details
                     of the correction as metadata applies, but the approach to encoding is
                     different, as are the features they will support.</p>

                  <p>Editors should declare in the preface which method(s) they have adopted so that
                     users will know to what extent the data about corrections is structured.</p>

               </div>
               <!-- End of section on correction as metadata -->

               <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-correction-specs">
                  <head>Correction: Specifications</head>

                  <p>Readings before and after correction are reported as any other readings, i.e.,
                     with <gi>rdg</gi> inside of <gi>app</gi>. The details of the correction are
                     contained in <gi>witDetail</gi>, with the use of several attributes to
                     determine how the information is processed.</p>

                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="witDetail"/>
                        <specDesc key="wit"/>
                        <specDesc key="target"/>
                        <specDesc key="corresp"/>
                        <specDesc key="type"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>

                  <p><gi>witDetail</gi> (witness detail) may be empty or it may contain a prose
                     description.</p>
                  <p><att>wit</att> (witness) has as its value the machine-readable siglum of the
                     witness that has the original or the altered reading.</p>
                  <p><att>target</att> has as its value the <att>xml:id</att> of the reading in
                     question.</p>
                  <p><att>corresp</att> (corresponds) has as its value the <att>xml:id</att> of the
                     related reading (i.e., the original reading corresponds to the corrected
                     reading and vice versa).</p>
                  <p><att>type</att> has one of the following values to classify the correction.
                     Possible values:<list>
                        <item>correction-original: the original reading, i.e., before correction
                              (<foreign xml:lang="lat">ante correctionem</foreign> or a.c.)</item>
                        <item>correction-altered: the altered reading, i.e., after correction
                              (<foreign xml:lang="lat">post correctionem</foreign> or p.c.)</item>
                     </list></p>

                  <p>In the sections on prose and semantic markup methods below, the following
                     examples are used:</p>

                  <p>Example 1: the original reading is <foreign xml:lang="lat">voca</foreign>, and
                     a correcting hand has added the letter "t" to the end of the word to make
                        <foreign xml:lang="lat">vocat</foreign>.</p>

                  <p>Example 2: witness <hi rend="bold">N</hi> originally had <hi rend="italic"
                        >co</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ice</hi> with an erasure of two characters
                     between them. A correcting hand has inserted the letters "r" and "t" in the
                     erasure. The corrected form (<hi rend="italic">cortice</hi>) matches the
                     reading in witnesses <hi rend="bold">P</hi> and <hi rend="bold">V</hi>. Another
                     reading is present in witnesses <hi rend="bold">G</hi> and <hi rend="bold"
                        >A</hi>. It is important to report both the original and the corrected
                     readings in witness <hi rend="bold">N</hi> so that there is no ambiguity.</p>


                  <!-- End of section on correction specs. -->

                  <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-correction-prose-method">
                     <head>Correction: Prose Method</head>

                     <p>In the prose method, readings are reported in their original and altered
                        form (i.e., after correction).</p>

                     <p>In the first example above, the original reading is <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                           >voca</foreign>. A correcting hand has added a "t" to the end, so the
                        altered reading is not <foreign xml:lang="lat">voca + t</foreign>, but
                           <foreign xml:lang="lat">vocat</foreign>. How and by whom the correction
                        was made is described in prose in <gi>witDetail</gi>:</p>

                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <app>
                           <lem>vocas</lem>
                           <rdg wit="#E" xml:id="rdg-voca">voca</rdg>
                           <rdg wit="#E1" xml:id="rdg-vocat">vocat</rdg>
                           <witDetail wit="#E" target="#rdg-voca" type="ante-corr"
                              corresp="#rdg-vocat"/>
                           <witDetail wit="#E1" target="#rdg-vocat" type="correction"
                              corresp="#rdg-voca">t <hi rend="italic">add. in
                           textu</hi></witDetail></app>
                     </egXML>

                     <p>This encoding will produce the following entry in the apparatus criticus:
                        vocas] voca E (a.c.) : vocat E<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> (<hi
                           rend="italic">corr</hi>., t <hi rend="italic">add. in textu</hi>)</p>

                     <p>In the second example, the original reading is represented as <foreign
                           xml:lang="lat">co..ice</foreign>, and witness N<hi rend="superscript"
                           >2</hi> is listed as a witness to the reading <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                           >cortice</foreign>. The details of the correction are described in prose
                        in <gi>witDetail</gi>.</p>

                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <app>
                           <lem wit="#N2 #P #V" xml:id="lem-cortice">cortice</lem>
                           <rdg wit="#N" xml:id="rdg-coice">co&#10214;..&#10215;ice</rdg>
                           <rdg wit="#G #A">codice</rdg>
                           <witDetail wit="#N" target="#rdg-coice" corresp="#lem-cortice"
                              type="correction-original"/>
                           <witDetail wit="#N2" target="#lem-cortice" corresp="#rdg-coice"
                              type="correction-altered">rt <hi rend="italic">add in
                              ras.</hi></witDetail>
                        </app>
                     </egXML>

                     <p>That encoding would produce cortice <hi rend="bold">N<hi rend="superscript"
                              >2</hi></hi> (<hi rend="italic">p.c.</hi>, rt <hi rend="italic">add.
                           in ras.</hi>) <hi rend="bold">PV</hi> : co&#10214;..&#10215;ice <hi
                           rend="bold">N</hi> (a.c.) : codice <hi rend="bold">G A</hi>.</p>

                  </div>
                  <!-- End section on correction: prose method -->

                  <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-correction-semantic-markup-method">
                     <head>Correction: Semantic Markup Method</head>

                     <p>The semantic markup method requires the correction to be encoded using
                        techniques described elsewhere in these guidelines:</p>

                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <app>
                           <lem>vocas</lem>
                           <rdg wit="#E" xml:id="rdg-voca">voca</rdg>
                           <rdg wit="#E1" xml:id="rdg-vocat">voca<add place="inline">t</add></rdg>
                           <witDetail wit="#E1" target="#rdg-vocat" type="correction"
                              corresp="#rdg-voca"/></app>
                     </egXML>

                     <p>This encoding will produce the following entry in the apparatus criticus:
                        vocas] voca E (a.c.) : vocat E<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> (<hi
                           rend="italic">corr</hi>., t <hi rend="italic">add. in textu</hi>).</p>

                     <p>For the second example, <gi>add</gi> and <gi>del</gi> will be used to encode
                        some of the details of the correction:</p>

                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <app>
                           <lem wit="#N2 #P #V" xml:id="lem-cortice">cortice</lem>
                           <rdg wit="#N" xml:id="rdg-coice">co<del rend="erasure"><gap reason="lost"
                                    quantity="2" unit="character"/></del>ice</rdg>
                           <rdg wit="#G #A">codice</rdg>
                           <witDetail wit="#N" target="#rdg-coice" corresp="#lem-cortice"
                              type="correction-original"/>
                           <witDetail wit="#N2" target="#lem-cortice" corresp="#rdg-coice"
                              type="correction-altered"><add place="inRas">rt</add></witDetail>
                        </app>
                     </egXML>

                     <p>That encoding would produce cortice <hi rend="bold">N<hi rend="superscript"
                              >2</hi></hi> (<hi rend="italic">p.c.</hi>, rt <hi rend="italic">add.
                           in ras.</hi>) <hi rend="bold">PV</hi> : co&#10214;..&#10215;ice <hi
                           rend="bold">N</hi> (a.c.) : codice <hi rend="bold">G A</hi>.</p>
                  </div>
                  <!-- End section correction: semantic markup method -->
               </div>
               <!-- End section correction: specifications -->
            </div>
            <!-- End of section on correction -->

            <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-conjecture-and-emendation">
               <head>Conjecture and Emendation</head>

               <p>&lt; &gt; = A conjecture has been adopted by the editor for the main edition
                  text.</p>

               <p>As explained in the section <ref target="#apparatus-criticus-concepts-definitions"
                     >Concepts and Definitions</ref>, conjectures are readings that are not
                  supported by documentary evidence, but are instead proposed by someone and
                  considered by the editor to be worthy of inclusion in a critical edition. A
                  conjecture is called an emendation if it is adopted as the official reading of a
                  particular criticial edition's main text. In other words, for the purposes of
                  these guidelines, an emendation is a successful conjecture. But above all,
                  conjectures and emendations are readings, and they are encoded as such in LDLT
                  editions.</p>

               <p>Traditionally, conjectures and emendations have been annotated in various ways in
                  critical editions (e.g., <foreign xml:lang="lat">ci.</foreign> or <foreign
                     xml:lang="lat">conj.</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="lat">coniecit</foreign>,
                     <foreign xml:lang="lat">em.</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                     >emend.</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="lat">emendavit</foreign>, among
                  others). They should be annotated in digital editions, too, both to facilitate
                  their identification, and to enable features such as filtering and searching for
                  them. The annotation is accomplished with <att>type</att>.</p>

               <p>Since an emendation is a conjecture that has been adopted for the main text of the
                  edition, only <gi>lem</gi> can have <att>type</att> with the value "emendation."
                  It could be inferred that a lemma with <att>source</att> only is an emendation,
                  but in the interest of being explicit, an emendation should be annotated
                  accordingly. Using <att>type</att> with the value of "emendation" will also ensure
                  that the lemma will be displayed or printed with the appropriate symbols around it
                  (i.e., &lt; &gt;) in the main text of the edition.</p>

               <p>Conversely, only <gi>rdg</gi> may have <att>type</att> with the value
                  "conjecture." It could be inferred that a reading with <att>source</att> only is a
                  conjecture, but it is best to be explicit in the identification if for no other
                  reason than ensuring that the conjecture will be displayed with the appropriate
                  symbols around it (i.e., &lt; &gt;) if it is swapped into the main text in the
                  LDLT text viewer.</p>

               <p>The following example demonstrates how to encode both an emendation and a
                  conjecture.</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app>
                     <lem source="#Haupt1854" type="emendation" xml:id="lem-plenumque"
                        >plenumque</lem>
                     <rdg wit="#ω" source="#edd.">primumque</rdg>
                     <rdg source="#Baehr." type="conjecture">rivumque</rdg>
                     <rdg source="#CSchenkl" type="conjecture">pronumque</rdg>
                     <note target="#lem-plenumque">prob. <ref taret="#Keene">Keene</ref> et <ref
                           target="#Schenkl">Schenkl</ref></note>
                  </app>
               </egXML>

               <p>This encoding will produce "&lt;plenumque&gt;" in the main text of the edition the
                  following in the apparatus criticus: plenumque] <hi rend="italic">em</hi>. Haupt
                     (<hi rend="italic">prob</hi>. Keene <hi rend="italic">et</hi> Schenkl),
                  primumque <hi rend="bold">ω</hi>
                  <hi rend="italic">edd</hi>., rivumque <hi rend="italic">ci.</hi> Baehr., pronumque
                     <hi rend="italic">ci</hi>. C. Schenkl.</p>

               <p>Multiple conjectures proposed by a single person should be contained in
                     <gi>rdgGrp</gi> with <att>type</att> and value "conjecture."</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app>
                     <lem>pallenti</lem>
                     <rdgGrp type="conjecture">
                        <rdg source="#Heins.">ridenti</rdg>
                        <rdg source="#Heins.">varianti</rdg>
                        <rdg source="#Heins.">vernanti</rdg>
                        <rdg source="#Heins.">roranti</rdg>
                     </rdgGrp>
                  </app>
               </egXML>

               <p>This would be displayed in the apparatus criticus as pallenti] ridenti <hi
                     rend="italic">vel</hi> varianti <hi rend="italic">vel</hi> vernanti <hi
                     rend="italic">vel</hi> roranti <hi rend="italic">ci</hi>. Heins.</p>
               <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-conjecture-and-emendation-partial">
                  <head>Letters Added by Conjecture</head>

                  <p>If it is necessary to represent letters added by conjecture in a <gi>rdg</gi>
                     within an apparatus entry, <gi>add</gi> with <att>type</att>="conjecture"
                     should be used.</p>
               </div>
               <!-- End section on letters added by conjecture -->
            </div>
            <!-- End of section on conjecture and emendation -->

            <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-crux"
               corresp="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-ambiguous.html">
               <head>Crux</head>
               <p>† † = Text deemed by the editor to be irredeemably corrupt.</p>
               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="sic"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>
               <p><gi>sic</gi> indicates that the text is readable but not understandable. In this
                  usage it is not paired with its customary partner <gi>corr</gi> because the nature
                  of a crux is that it cannot be corrected.</p>

               <p>For example, at section 2.4.12 of Macrobius'
                     <bibl><title>Saturnalia</title></bibl>, <ref target="#kaster-macrobius">Robert
                     Kaster</ref> marks two words in the text of his OCT edition with <foreign
                     xml:lang="lat">cruces</foreign>:<quote rend="blockquote">… "vale mel gentium
                     †meculle†, ebur ex Etruria, lasar Arretinum, adamas Supernas, Tiberinum
                     margaritum, Cilniorum smargde, iaspi figulorum, berulle Porsenae, carbunculum
                     †habeas†, ἵνα συντέμω πάντα, ᾶλλαγμα moecharum."</quote></p>

               <p>In the apparatus criticus for the first crux, Kaster has the following:
                     <quote>meculle <hi rend="italic">Nβ</hi>(melcule <hi rend="italic">DP<hi
                           rend="superscript">2</hi>G</hi>, <hi rend="italic">n.l. P<hi
                           rend="superscript">1</hi></hi>): Medulliae <hi rend="italic">Turnebus
                        1604, 584</hi>.</quote> The second one is simpler: <quote>habeas] Hadriae
                        <hi rend="italic">Jahn</hi></quote>.</p>

               <p>The following example demonstrates how these <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                     >cruces</foreign> would be encoded in an LDLT edition:</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <p>
                     <quote>vale mel gentium <app>
                           <lem>
                              <sic>meculle</sic>
                           </lem>
                           <rdg wit="#N #β" xml:id="rdg-meculle">meculle</rdg>
                           <note target="#rdg-meculle">melcule <ref target="#D">D</ref>
                              <ref target="#P2">P<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></ref>
                              <ref target="#G">G</ref>, n.l. <ref target="#P1">P<hi
                                    rend="superscript">1</hi></ref>
                           </note>
                           <rdg source="#Turnebus" xml:id="rdg-Medulliae">Medulliae</rdg>
                           <note target="#rdg-Medulliae">584</note>
                        </app>, ebur ex Etruria, lasar Arretinum, adamas Supernas, Tiberinum
                        margaritum, Cilniorum smaragde, iaspi figulorum, berulle Porsenae,
                        carbunculum <app>
                           <lem><sic>habeas</sic></lem>
                           <rdg source="#Jahn">Hadriae</rdg>
                        </app>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἵνα συντέμω πάντα, ἄλλαγμα</foreign>
                        moecharum.</quote>
                  </p>
               </egXML>

               <p>The use of <gi>sic</gi> would cause the symbol † to be placed on both ends of each
                  crux. The rest of the information would be handled in the normal manner for
                  readings in the apparatus criticus.</p>
            </div>
            <!-- End of section "Crux" -->

            <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-analysis">
               <head>Tagging Readings for Analysis</head>

               <p>An editor may enhance an edition's functionality by adding one or more of the
                  analytical "tags" listed below. Use of these tags will enable additional filtering
                  and querying functionality, such as filtering out purely orthographical variants
                  or focusing on variants that affect the syntax of the text.</p>

               <p>It is up to the editor to decide how extensively to apply these analytical tags,
                  if at all. If analytical tags are used, the preface should make clear which ones
                  are used and why they are used. For example, an editor may wish only to tag
                  orthographical variants so that users can filter them in or out of the text as
                  they please.</p>

               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="ana"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>

               <p><att>ana</att> (analysis) on <gi>rdg</gi> applies one or more of the following
                  values to a reading:<list>
                     <item>lexical: the reading differs from the lemma by offering an entirely
                        different lexeme.</item>
                     <item>morphological: the reading differs from the lemma in its grammatical
                        form.</item>
                     <item>ordinal: the reading changes the order in which units (letters, words,
                        phrases, sentences, lines) occur in the lemma.</item>
                     <item>orthographical: the reading differs from the lemma only in spelling
                        (i.e., not in any grammatically significant way).</item>
                     <item>syntactic: the reading differs from the lemma in its grammatical
                        construction or arrangement.</item>
                     <item>subtractive: omission of some unit of text through oversight, erasure, or
                        some other cause.</item>
                     <item>additive: an interpolation, i.e., some text judged by the editor to have
                        entered the tradition through the mistaken or deliberate copying of
                        auxiliary material (e.g., glosses, marginalia, etc.).</item>
                  </list>
               </p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app>
                     <lem wit="#N #P #GlaeserSqq">vicit</lem>
                     <rdg wit="#G" ana="#morphological">vīcit</rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#d" ana="#lexical">ludit</rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#V" ana="#lexical">lusit</rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#μ" ana="#lexical">visit</rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#γ" ana="#subtractive"/>
                  </app>
               </egXML>

               <p>If a value for <att>ana</att> may be applied to all of the readings in an
                  apparatus entry, <att>ana</att> may be applied to <gi>app</gi> instead of each
                  individual reading:</p>

               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app ana="#orthographical">
                     <lem>Ornyte</lem>
                     <rdg wit="#N #G #V" source="#edd.">ornite</rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#P">ornyce</rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#s">ornithe</rdg>
                  </app>
               </egXML>
            </div>
            <!-- End of section on analytical tagging. -->

            <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-editorial-notes">
               <head>Editorial Notes</head>

               <p>These guidelines cover most of the kinds of information commonly found in a
                  critical apparatus, but not all of them, since it would be impossible to
                  anticipate everything any editor of a text would ever need to encode.</p>

               <p>If a certain kind of annotation or comment is needed, but a method for encoding it
                  is not described in these guidelines, <gi>witDetail</gi> or <gi>note</gi> may be
                  used <foreign xml:lang="lat">ad hoc</foreign>, depending on whether the subject is
                  a single witness (<gi>witDetail</gi>) or something of a more general nature
                     (<gi>note</gi>).</p>

               <p>These guidelines may also be extended as the community of users discovers and
                  proposes additional encoding patterns to the staff of the LDLT.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <!-- End of section on the apparatus criticus -->

         <div xml:id="textual-commentary">
            <head>Commentary</head>

            <p>Traditionally, extended commentary on textual matters has been published apart from
               the critical edition (e.g., as a monograph or in textual notes published in
               periodicals). Editors of LDLT editions are encouraged to include longer notes on
               textual matters in a section enclosed in <gi>div</gi> with
               <att>xml:id</att>="textual-commentary".</p>

            <p>This section demonstrates how to do encode longer notes.</p>

            <p>
               <specList>
                  <specDesc key="note"/>
               </specList>
            </p>
            <p><gi>anchor</gi> is an empty element placed at the point in the main text that is the
               subject of an extended note. It must have <att>xml:id</att> so that the note can
               point to it. It must also have <att>corresp</att> pointing to the <att>xml:id</att>
               of the note in the commentary so that a link can be inserted directly to the
               note.</p>
            <p><gi>note</gi> with <att>type</att>="commentary" and <att>target</att> pointing to the
                  <att>xml:id</att> of the <gi>anchor</gi> contains the text of the note, which is
               written in prose using <gi>p</gi>.</p>

            <p>For example, after Calp. 4.96, <ref target="#giarratano-calpurnius">Giarratano</ref>
               prints five unnumbered lines of dots to indicate that he believes a stanza is
               missing. At 4.97, he includes in his apparatus criticus an extended discussion about
               his rearrangement of several sets of lines. In an LDLT edition, it is preferable to
               put that sort of discussion in the textual commentary. The following example
               demonstrates how it would be encoded in an LDLT edition:</p>

            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
               <app type="line-omission">
                  <lem source="#Giarratano" type="emendation" xml:id="lem-4.96-gap">
                     <!-- Lines are not numbered so as not to interrupt the traditional numbering -->
                     <l><gap reason="lost"/></l>
                     <l><gap reason="lost"/></l>
                     <l><gap reason="lost"/></l>
                     <l><gap reason="lost"/></l>
                     <l><gap reason="lost"/></l>
                  </lem>
                  <note target="#lem-4.96-gap">quinque vv. deesse puto. <anchor xml:id="gap-4.96"
                        corresp="#comm-4.96"/></note>
               </app>
               <l n="97">Aspicis, ut virides audito Caesare silvae</l>
               <!-- Edition continues until end. -->
               <div xml:id="textual-commentary">
                  <note type="commentary" target="lem-4.96-gap" xml:id="comm-4.96">
                     <p>4.96: Carmen amoebaeum, quod vocatur, cum ex impari stropharum numero
                        constare nequeat, in hac ecloga integrum non esses <ref target="#Hermann">G.
                           Hermann</ref> (ad Bion. et Mosch. p. 46) primus sensit. <ref
                           target="#Schenkl">Schenkl</ref> autem censuit deesse stropham quae olim
                        opposita fuit strophae VIII itidemque comite carere III, quam ob rem in
                        editione priore vir doctissimus III post XI transposuit lacunameque in
                        utraque editione post F. Leo (Zeitsch. f. d. oesterr. Gymn. XXXVI p. 619)
                        XIII post III collocavit ut v. 141 carmen amoebaeum concluderetur. Mihi
                        quidem, cum strophae I, et II, IV et V, VI et VII, IX et X, XII et XIII
                        invicem sibi respondeant, visum est lacunem post III constituere et XI
                        transponere ante VIII.</p>
                  </note>
               </div>
            </egXML>

            <p>This encoding will produce the following in a digital or print version:<list>
                  <item>five unnumbered lines of &lt; *** &gt;</item>
                  <item>The following note in the apparatus criticus: quinque vv. deesse
                     puto.</item>
                  <item>The symbol &#9674; after the note indicating further discussion is available
                     in the textual commentary.</item>
                  <item>A note in the textual commentary.</item>
               </list></p>

            <p>The digital version will have the additional feature of links from the apparatus to
               the commentary and from the commentary to the apparatus.</p>
         </div>
         <!-- End of section on textual commentary -->

         <div xml:id="works-cited">
            <head>Works Cited</head>

            <p>The following is a list of works cited in these guidelines.</p>



            <listBibl>
               <head>Editions</head>
               <bibl xml:id="bazán-scots"><editor>Bazán, C.</editor>, <editor>K. Emery</editor>,
                     <editor>T. Noone</editor>, <editor>R. Plevano</editor>, <editor>A.
                     Traver</editor>, eds. <title>B. Ioannis Duns Scoti Quaestiones Super Secundum
                     et Tertium De Anima</title>. <series><title level="s">B. Ioannis Duns Scoti
                        Opera Philosophica</title>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope></series>. <pubPlace>Washington,
                     D.C.</pubPlace>: <publisher>The Catholic University of America
                     Press</publisher>, <date>2006</date>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="damon-caesar"><editor>Damon, C.</editor>, ed. <title>C. Iuli Caesaris
                     Commentariorum Libri III De Bello Civili</title>. <series><title level="s"
                        >Oxford Classical Texts</title></series>. <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>, <date>2015</date>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="giarratano-calpurnius"><editor>Giarratano, Caesar</editor>, ed.
                     <title>Calpurnii et Nemesiani Bucolica</title>. <pubPlace>Naples</pubPlace>:
                  Detken and Rocholl, <date>1910</date>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="hall-ovid"><editor>Hall, J. B.</editor>, ed. <title>Ovidius:
                     Tristia</title>. <series><title level="s">Bibliotheca Scriptorum Graecorum et
                        Romanorum Teubneriana</title></series>. <pubPlace>Stuttgart and
                     Leipzig</pubPlace>: <publisher>B. G. Teubner</publisher>,
                  <date>1995</date>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="kaster-macrobius"><editor>Kaster, Robert A.</editor>, ed.
                     <title>Macrobii Ambrosii Theodosii Saturnalia</title>. <series><title level="s"
                        >Oxford Classical Texts</title></series>. <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>, <date>2011</date>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="kaster-suetonius"><editor>———</editor>, ed. <title>C. Suetoni
                     Tranquilli De Vita Caesarum Libros VIII et De Grammaticis et Rhetoribus
                     Librum</title>. <series><title level="s">Oxford Classical
                     Texts</title></series>. <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>: <publisher>Clarendon
                     Press</publisher>, <date>2016</date>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="lindsay-festus"><editor>Lindsay, W. M.</editor>, ed. <title>Festus: De
                     Verborum Significatu cum Pauli Epitome</title>. <series><title level="s"
                        >Bibliotheca Scriptorum Graecorum et Romanorum Teubneriana</title></series>.
                     <pubPlace>Stuttgart and Leipzig</pubPlace>: <publisher>B. G.
                     Teubner</publisher>, <date>1913</date>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="tarrant-ovid"><editor>Tarrant, R. J.</editor>, ed. <title>P. Ovidi
                     Nasoni Metamorphoses</title>. <series><title level="s">Oxford Classical
                        Texts</title></series>. <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>: <publisher>Clarendon
                     Press</publisher>, <date>2004</date>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="verdiere-calpurnius"><editor>Verdière, Raoul</editor>, ed. <title>T.
                     Calpurnii Siculi De laude Pisonis et Bucolica et M. Annaei Lucani De laude
                     Caesaris Einsidlensia quae dicuntur carmina</title>. <series><title level="s"
                        >Collection Latomus</title>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope></series>.
                     <pubPlace>Berchem-Bruxelles</pubPlace>: Latomus: Revue d'Études Latines,
                     <date>1954</date>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <!-- End list of editions cited -->

            <listBibl>
               <head>Guidelines</head>
               <bibl xml:id="Epidoc"><author>Elliott, Tom</author>, <author>Gabriel Bodard</author>,
                     <author>Hugh Cayless</author> et al. <title>EpiDoc: Epigraphic Documents in TEI
                     XML</title>. Online material, available: <ref target="http://epidoc.sf.net"
                     >http://epidoc.sf.net</ref> (2016-09-17).</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="xml-id"><author>Marsh, Jonathan</author>
                  <author>Daniel Veillard</author>, <author>Norman Walsh</author>. <title>xml:id
                     Version 1.0</title>
                  <series><title level="s">W3C Recommendation 9 September 2005</title></series>
                  <ref target="https://www.w3.org/TR/xml-id/">https://www.w3.org/TR/xml-id/</ref>
                  (2016-09-17)</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="TEI"><editor>TEI Consortium</editor>, eds. <title>TEI P5: Guidelines
                     for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title>. Version 3.0.0. Last
                  updated on 29th March 2016, revision 89ba24e. <publisher>TEI
                     Consortium</publisher>. <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5/"
                     >http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5/</ref> (2016-09-17).</bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <!-- End list of guidelines cited -->


            <listBibl>
               <head>Other Works Cited</head>
               <bibl xml:id="Chicago"><author>University of Chicago Press Staff</author>. <title>The
                     Chicago Manual of Style</title>, 16th ed. <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>:
                     <publisher>Chicago University Press</publisher>, <date>2010</date></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="West"><author>West, M. L.</author>
                  <title>Textual Criticism and Editorial Technique Applicable to Greek and Latin
                     Texts</title>. <pubPlace>Stuttgart</pubPlace>: <publisher>B. G.
                     Teubner</publisher>, <date>1973</date>.</bibl>
            </listBibl><!-- End list of other works cited -->
         </div>
         <!-- End section works cited -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
