<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="edition-text-multiple-texts">
            <head>Multiple Versions of a Text</head>

            <p>In most cases, the main text of an edition will uniform, even though it may be
               composed of readings from multiple sources representing different branches of a
               textual tradition. In cases where there is more than one version of the text, and
               those versions cannot be reduced to variant readings in the critical apparatus, it
               may be desirable to represent multiple versions in the body of the text.</p>

            <p>For example, there are two versions of Servius' commentary on Vergil, commonly
               referred to as "Servius" and "Servius Auctus." Editors and publishers of print
               editions have used typographical conventions and page layout to signify where the two
               versions differ from each other. The following passage from the so-called "Harvard
               Servius" demonstrates the difficulties:</p>

            <p><graphic url="servius.png"/></p>

            <p>Reading from the top of the page, the first lines present commentary on Verg.
                     <bibl><title>Aen.</title></bibl> 3.8 from both Servius Auctus (left) and
               Servius (right). The two have the same text beginning with <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                     ><hi rend="smallcaps">vix</hi> mox, ut (I 34)</foreign>. They diverge again. At
               the comment on <bibl><title>Aen.</title></bibl> 3.9, the vertical line indicates that
               the comment is found only in Servius Auctus. The critical apparatus presents the
               entries for Servius Auctus first, then the entries for Servius.</p>

            <p>The same issues confront the editor of a digital edition, but those issues are
               handled not with typographical conventions, but with semantic encoding. Similar
               conventions might be used to format the text for screens or the printed page, but the
               encoding provides the foundation for that work.</p>

            

         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
